<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <id>2238978</id>
  <title>SuperCAT: a supertree database for combined and integrative multilocus sequence typing analysis of the Bacillus cereus group of bacteria (including B. cereus, B. anthracis and B. thuringiensis)
</title>
  <abstract>
 The Bacillus cereus group of bacteria is an important group including mammalian and insect pathogens, such as B. anthracis, the anthrax bacterium, B. thuringiensis, used as a biological pesticide and B. cereus, often involved in food poisoning incidents. To characterize the population structure and epidemiology of these bacteria, five separate multilocus sequence typing (MLST) schemes have been developed, which makes results difficult to compare. Therefore, we have developed a database that compiles and integrates MLST data from all five schemes for the B. cereus group, accessible at http://mlstoslo.uio.no/. Supertree techniques were used to combine the phylogenetic information from analysis of all schemes and datasets, in order to produce an integrated view of the B. cereus group population. The database currently contains strain information and sequence data for 1029 isolates and 26 housekeeping gene fragments, which can be searched by keywords, MLST scheme, or sequence similarity. Supertrees can be browsed according to various criteria such as species, isolate source, or genetic distance, and subtrees containing strains of interest can be extracted. Besides analysis of the available data, the user has the possibility to enter her/his own sequences and compare them to the database and/or include them into the supertree reconstructions.
</abstract>
  <content>
 Multilocus sequence typing (MLST) is a tool that is widely used for phylogenetic typing of bacteria. MLST is based on polymerase chain reaction (PCR) amplification and sequencing of internal fragments of usually seven essential or housekeeping genes spread around the bacterial chromosome. The genetic relatedness among isolates is then determined by comparison of the nucleotide sequence types (1,2). MLST is thus a method that is unambiguous and truly portable among laboratories. Since the initial development of this technique for Neisseria meningitidis in 1998, MLST schemes have been developed for about 30 species including some of the most important bacterial pathogens, e.g. Streptococcus pneumoniae, Streptococcus pyogenes, Haemophilus influenzae, Staphylococcus aureus, Campylobacter jejuni, Enterococcus faecium, Burkholderia pseudomallei, Escherichia coli, Salmonella enterica and the Bacillus cereus group (see (1) for a recent review). These MLST schemes have been used successfully to explore the population structure of bacteria, to study the evolution of their virulence properties, to identify antibiotic-resistant strains and epidemic clones, and for epidemiological surveillance. The B. cereus group includes bacterial species that are of medical and/or economic importance, such as B. anthracis, an obligate mammalian pathogen causing the lethal disease anthrax, B. cereus, an opportunistic human pathogen involved in food-poisoning incidents and contaminations in hospitals, B. thuringiensis, an insect pathogen and one of the world's most widely used biopesticide and B. weihenstephanensis, a cold-tolerant species known for contaminating dairies. These species are genetically very closely related and may be considered as one species based on genetic and genomic evidence (3&#x2013;5). Unlike other bacterial species that are typed using a single MLST scheme, five separate schemes have been developed for the B. cereus group, based on different sets of genes and isolates (5&#x2013;10). The Priest scheme (8) is currently the most widely used. Studies with the various schemes have independently indicated that the B. cereus group population is divided into three main phylogenetic clusters and that species are usually intermixed within the groups. One cluster contains the monomorphic B. anthracis isolates and a number of B. cereus and B. thuringiensis strains, many of which are from clinical sources. A second heterogeneous cluster includes B. cereus and B. thuringiensis isolates from various origins, while cold-tolerant B. weihenstephanensis and B. cereus isolates belong to the third group. The separate MLST analyses have also revealed that the B. cereus group population is weakly clonal overall due to numerous clinical and virulent isolates emerging from different phylogenetic positions (5&#x2013;8,11&#x2013;14), with the exception of the &#x2018;cold-tolerant&#x2019; cluster that seems to exhibit a panmictic (or sexual) population structure, i.e. with frequent genetic exchanges between strains (9). Despite the overall congruence between the various MLST studies, the use of separate schemes with no gene overlap and very little strain overlap has produced a confusing situation and makes the results difficult to compare directly. Therefore, we recently proposed a combined scheme based on genes taken from three of the four schemes available by then and for which we created a web-based database accessible at the University of Oslo's MLST server, http://mlstoslo.uio.no/ (5). Here, in order to provide the B. cereus group research community with a common MLST resource, we have developed on the same website a database, SuperCAT, that compiles and integrates MLST data from all the published B. cereus group schemes. In addition, we applied supertree reconstruction methods to build an integrated view of the B. cereus group population and phylogeny. Below we describe the content and main features of the new database as well as the process of supertree building. The five MLST schemes designed for typing bacteria of the B. cereus group aSpecific databases for the Priest and Tourasse&#x2013;Helgason schemes are accessible at http://pubmlst.org/bcereus/ and http://mlstoslo.uio.no/, respectively. A BLAST database for the Candelon&#x2013;Sorokin scheme is available at http://spock.jouy.inra.fr/cgi-bin/bacilliMLSopen.cgi. bWhile the Tourasse&#x2013;Helgason and Priest schemes use the same gene fragment for the pycA gene, the Ko scheme is based on a different and non-overlapping gene region. cThe B. cereus group-specific transcriptional regulator plcR was originally included in the Candelon&#x2013;Sorokin and Ko schemes. However, plcR follows a phylogeny different from the other MLST loci (7,10) and is no longer used for MLST; therefore, it is not included in SuperCAT. dThe Tourasse&#x2013;Helgason scheme is a combined scheme based on 3 genes from the Helgason scheme (adk, ccpA, and glpT), 3 genes from the Priest scheme (glpF, pta and pycA(2)), and the panC gene from the Candelon&#x2013;Sorokin scheme. eIncluding strains with fully sequenced genomes. eIncluding strains with fully sequenced genomes. SuperCAT is built as a relational database using the PostgreSQL management system, and data are accessible through a graphical web interface. User queries and results pages are processed and created on-the-fly via a highly modified version of the mlstdbNet software (16) written in PERL and based on the DataBase Interface (DBI) and Common Gateway Interface (CGI) modules. The database is implemented on a Linux Apache web server maintained through the facilities and support provided by the Norwegian EMBnet node. Some large supertree computations are run on a Linux supercomputer at the University of Oslo. The ATV (A Tree Viewer) Java applet is used for phylogenetic tree display (17). ATV notably supports horizontal and vertical zooming capabilities that are suitable for browsing large trees. The Jalview editor Java applet is also implemented in SuperCAT for advanced multiple sequence alignment display (18). Schematic overview of the B. cereus group supertree reconstruction procedure using Matrix Representation by Parsimony (MRP). See text for details. Schematic overview of the B. cereus group supertree reconstruction procedure using Matrix Representation by Parsimony (MRP). See text for details. It should be noted that the global 1029-strain supertree retains the phylogenetic signals from the individual schemes and contains the three main clusters of the B. cereus group population described in the section &#x2018;Introduction&#x2019;. The integrated SuperCAT system may also allow to infer new relationships between strains that were analyzed with different gene sets. Even though the 26 loci sequences are available for only 21 isolates, they apparently provide enough overlap information for building the main branches of the supertree. These 21 isolates cover all three clusters, although the majority of them are B. anthracis strains or clinical strains closely related to B. anthracis due to the focus of genome sequencing projects, making the part of the supertree containing these isolates likely to be more accurate than the rest of the tree. Furthermore, 111 other isolates have been typed by 10 genes or more, providing additional overlap (see the &#x2018;Gene Distribution&#x2019; page). Although about two-thirds of the sequence data are missing overall, it has been shown for other organisms that relevant supertrees could be reconstructed with datasets containing more than 90% of missing data, especially when the characters that are present are informative (20,22,23,34). Empirical and simulation studies have indicated that this behavior may be due to the fact that the characters which are present are more important for the tree-building process than those which are absent (see (20,34) and references therein). Precise within-cluster groupings may contain more uncertainty, as indicated by the large number of unresolved multifurcations in the B. cereus group supertree. Finally, it is also worth mentioning that the branching orders of the scheme-specific MRP supertrees are highly correlated to those of the published trees built with concatenated sequences and other phylogenetic algorithms. The complete list of isolates included in SuperCAT (currently 1029) with strain description, source and country of origin is available at the database home page. By default all isolates in the database are used in the analysis tools provided, but the user can select strains of interest by keywords, MLST scheme, entering a list of strain identifiers, or choosing isolates individually via checkboxes. All subsequent analyses will be based on the selected strain subset and their loci. The keyword search will look for matches in any of the strain, description, source, location and scheme fields. Complex keyword queries with several logical operators can be formulated in the &#x2018;advanced search&#x2019; page. Note that many isolates were referred by alternative names in different MLST schemes and publications, therefore synonyms have been included in the strain descriptions that allow a particular isolate to be looked up using any of its alternative identifiers. A sequence search is also possible using BLASTN (35), in order to select isolates that have allele sequences identical to user-entered query sequences. Throughout SuperCAT, clicking on a strain name will pop up an isolate-specific window showing all relevant information and giving access to the nucleotide sequences of individual loci for that isolate. Detailed information about the MLST schemes (e.g. loci names and lengths, genomic coordinates, literature references) and their overlap, the distribution of available loci among the isolates, and the supertree reconstruction procedure can be obtained by clicking the relevant links in the header line present at the top of every page. Examples of supertree browsing and manipulation in SuperCAT. A, supertree colored by species; B, specific highlighting of user-selected strains (in red); C, extracted subtree containing only the strains highlighted in B. Trees are displayed using ATV (17). Examples of supertree browsing and manipulation in SuperCAT. A, supertree colored by species; B, specific highlighting of user-selected strains (in red); C, extracted subtree containing only the strains highlighted in B. Trees are displayed using ATV (17). Besides the manipulation of the precomputed supertrees, SuperCAT offers the user the possibility to compute new supertrees by MRP using any combination of strains, schemes and genes. Supertree computations may be extremely time consuming, ranging from a few minutes to 2&#x2013;3 days with the complete database. Users are therefore requested to enter their e-mail addresses and will receive a notification containing a link to the results page when the supertree is ready. Note that when building a supertree for a user-selected subset of strains, the computation will first include all database isolates. A subtree containing only the user-selected isolates will then be extracted from the supertree of all strains. Although more time consuming, this strategy allows: (i) to avoid sampling artefacts as phylogenies built with different isolate sets may vary and (ii) to obtain relationships even if the selected isolates have been typed using non-overlapping gene sets, as the supertree of all isolates can always be built owing to the completely sequenced strains that are common to all schemes. Examples of query results in SuperCAT. A, multi-scheme BLAST search with sequence alignment; B, multi-scheme genetic search showing the list of isolates sharing one or more sequences with a query strain; C, multiple sequence alignment using Jalview (18). Examples of query results in SuperCAT. A, multi-scheme BLAST search with sequence alignment; B, multi-scheme genetic search showing the list of isolates sharing one or more sequences with a query strain; C, multiple sequence alignment using Jalview (18). All strain information data, sequences and phylogenetic trees, including user-made supertrees and extracted subtrees, can be saved and downloaded freely from the database. Users wishing to have their MLST data included as part of the SuperCAT release (and/or the Tourasse&#x2013;Helgason scheme-specific database) are welcome to contact N.J.T. or A.-B.K. at the e-mail addresses given on the Oslo MLST server front page. SuperCAT is a newly created database devoted to the B. cereus group of bacteria whose main objectives are to provide a common MLST repository and means for building a comprehensive genetic analysis of the group that has been typed by five separate schemes. The database is publicly and freely available at http://mlstoslo.uio.no/, along with the database specific for the combined scheme of (5). We plan to update SuperCAT quarterly. Future developments of the database may deal with refining the supertree-building procedure. In particular, a new improved method has recently been developed for taking into account both nucleotide substitutions and recombination events in phylogenies, as part of the ClonalFrame software, which has been applied to the B. cereus group and the Priest scheme (38). It would therefore be of interest to examine the suitability of ClonalFrame in the supertree context. It is also tempting to extend the supertree analysis beyond MLST data, by incorporating the phylogenies obtained previously from large-scale multilocus enzyme electrophoresis (MLEE; (3,39&#x2013;41)) and amplified fragment length polymorphism (AFLP; (42&#x2013;45)) studies. The MRP framework is ideal since it allows to integrate trees that can be built from different methods and data. As MLEE, AFLP and MLST have different levels of resolution, one can hope that combining them might provide an even more robust supertree for the B. cereus group.
</content>
</document>
