<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <id>2238914</id>
  <title>RNAJunction: a database of RNA junctions and kissing loops for three-dimensional structural analysis and nanodesign
</title>
  <abstract>
 We developed a database called RNAJunction that contains structure and sequence information for RNA structural elements such as helical junctions, internal loops, bulges and loop&#x2013;loop interactions. Our database provides a user-friendly way of searching structural elements by PDB code, structural classification, sequence, keyword or inter-helix angles. In addition, the structural data was subjected to energy minimization. This database is useful for analyzing RNA structures as well as for designing novel RNA structures on a nanoscale. The database can be accessed at: http://rnajunction.abcc.ncifcrf.gov/
</abstract>
  <content>
 Nucleic acid systems have proven to be very amenable to the design of nanostructures. While there are more published examples for DNA systems (1&#x2013;4), RNA has also been used to self-assemble into various shapes like squares and triangles (4,5). The corners of the assembled RNA complexes are based on known helical junctions (4) or loop&#x2013;loop interactions (6). These designed RNA structures highlight the importance of loop&#x2013;loop motifs and helical junctions. A database of such structural elements would significantly speed up the design process. Helical junctions are important for the structural and catalytic properties of RNAs. It has been shown, for example, that a four-way junction promotes the functional folded state of the hairpin ribozyme (7). Thus, characterizing and classifying RNA junctions can lead to a better understanding of the structural and functional capabilities of RNA. Several databases containing RNA structures exist. The basic repository for experimentally determined nucleic acid structures is the Protein Data Bank (PDB) (8). Because RNA structures are only part of the content of the PDB, several databases provide additional information by annotating and classifying RNA structures derived from the PDB. SCOR is a structural database that contains a classification of internal and hairpin loops (9&#x2013;11). Its classification scheme is based on a directed acyclic graph, allowing a node to have multiple parents. NCIR is a database of non-canonical interactions found in RNA structures (12). For each base pair type, NCIR provides information about sequence and structure contexts in which this base pair type has been found. The Nucleic Acid Database (NDB) is a database containing annotated and categorized RNA and DNA structures (13). Among other things, it provides categories for RNA junctions and DNA junctions. The provided junctions correspond to complete PDB structures and not the extracted fragments. The Metals in RNA (MeRNA) database catalogs RNA structures that are bound to metal ions (14). Lescoute and Westhof (15) analyzed RNA structures with respect to three-way junctions. They found that three-way junctions that contain two helices that are coaxially stacked can be classified into three main families depending on the relative lengths of the connecting loop regions. Lilley (16) reviewed helical junctions of DNA and RNA. This study showed a bias towards coaxial stacking and the importance of ion interactions. Lilley et al. (17) describe a NC-IUBMB recommended nomenclature for nucleic acids junctions. We have developed a database called RNAJunction that provides information about RNA junctions, kissing loops, internal loops and bulges in an extracted, annotated and searchable form. Our RNAJunction database is very useful for analyzing and understanding the principles of RNA structure formation. It is to our knowledge the only currently available database that also contains extracted RNA kissing loop elements. Its unique search capability allows the user to identify RNA junctions based on (among other criteria) inter-helical angles, which makes it an important resource for the design of novel RNA nanostructures from building blocks. Schematic drawing of a three-way junction. Schematic drawing of a three-way junction. We developed a Java program, &#x2018;JunctionScanner,&#x2019; for detecting, extracting and analyzing RNA junctions, kissing loops, internal loops and bulges from PDB coordinate files. The algorithm uses the RNAView (18) base pairing patterns to detect groups of interconnected helices corresponding to RNA junctions from a given structure in PDB format. Non-canonical base pairs are allowed. Given the list of base pairs, a list of all bulge-free helices is generated (a helix containing a bulge is represented as two helices). Each strand of each helix is used as a starting point of a &#x2018;path&#x2019; as follows: using a start strand and helix position, the strand is followed in the 5&#x2032; to 3&#x2032; direction to the next downstream helix. The opposing strand from this subsequent helix is now followed from its 5&#x2032; to its 3&#x2032; end to yet another helix and so forth. If one arrives in this fashion back at the helix one started with (a circular path), one can conclude that the helices of the path form a junction (compare Figure 1). Note that hairpin loops are currently not considered. The JunctionScanner program extracts the coordinate data corresponding to each unique detected junction. Also, the local orientation of each helix is approximated by superposing a helix represented by the idealized positions of C4&#x2032; atoms (19). This permits the computation of the angle between the direction-vectors of any two helices. Cut-off values for different filtering parameter sets called &#x2018;most strict&#x2019;, &#x2018;medium&#x2019; and &#x2018;least strict&#x2019; Note that the structural elements corresponding to the most strict parameter set are required to possess helices of lengths four (or greater) in the original structure, however the corresponding extracted coordinate files contain only three base pairs. Note that the structural elements corresponding to the most strict parameter set are required to possess helices of lengths four (or greater) in the original structure, however the corresponding extracted coordinate files contain only three base pairs. Schematic drawing of a kissing loop. Each circle represents one nucleotide; the single-stranded regions are indicated in gray. Schematic drawing of a kissing loop. Each circle represents one nucleotide; the single-stranded regions are indicated in gray. Counts of identified RNA junctions, internal loops, bulges and kissing loops The counts are given for three different filter parameters The last column shows the counts for the reduced-redundancy least-restricted data set whose representative structures can be part of either the most-strict, medium-strict or least-strict data set. The last column shows the counts for the reduced-redundancy least-restricted data set whose representative structures can be part of either the most-strict, medium-strict or least-strict data set. A simple scheme for optionally working with a reduced redundancy data set was adopted. All structural elements of the same type, consisting of the same sequences were clustered using single linkage clustering and a structural superposition cutoff of 3.0 &#xC5; DRMS (C4&#x2032; atom positions). For each cluster, one of its members is chosen to be the representative structure. The user can choose to search the original data or only the representative structures. This reduces the number of structural elements by a factor of about four (compare Table 2). Analyzing the structural variation within clusters, we found that in all but three cases the DRMS of the cluster members with respect to their cluster representative is smaller then 3.0 &#xC5;. The results of the JunctionScanner applied to PDB coordinate files was entered into a MySql relational database. These data include the quantitative analysis, sequence, geometric conformation and citation for the identified structural elements as well as references to the parent structure from the PDB and the extracted coordinate data (the full list of stored properties is given in the Supplementary Data). The web presentation tier is implemented using PHP. Images of the secondary structure (generated using RNAView) and tertiary structure [generated using Raster3D (23)] are available. The 3D coordinates of the structural element can be viewed interactively using the JMol Java applet. The text output of the JunctionScanner run is also provided and contains more detailed information such as the local coordinate systems of the fitted idealized helices. Additional data is included in the form of structures obtained by molecular mechanics minimization, calculated using Amber 8.0 (24) and the Cornell force field ff99 (25). Analyzing the minimized structures, we found that 68% of them have an RMSD of &lt;1 &#xC5; compared to their respective original structure; 31% have an RMSD between 1 and 2 &#xC5;, 0.7% exhibit an RMSD between 2 and 3 &#xC5;, 0.0003% show an RMSD between 3 and 5 &#xC5;. We plan to supplement the RNAJunction database also with molecular dynamics simulation results in the future. The essential tables underlying the RNAJunction database correspond to junctions, helices, strands, references and angles. In this way, helices and junctions, for example, are related through a many-to-one relationship, allowing in principle for junctions of arbitrarily large order. More detailed information about the design of the database tables is provided in the Supplementary Data. Internal loops, bulges and kissing loops are internally considered a special case of &#x2018;two-way&#x2019; junctions; a flag indicates the different strand connectivity of a kissing loop compared to an internal loop. The aim of this database is 2-fold: first, it is an important resource for RNA nanodesign, which requires a library of known RNA structural elements for the development of novel RNA structures (20,26). Second, we envision the database to be useful for analysis, in particular for understanding the principles of RNA structure and folding. RNAJunction (http://rnajunction.abcc.ncifcrf.gov/) is publicly available and its data can be accessed through a user-friendly website. The RNAJunction database contains detailed information about RNA structural elements (currently junctions, internal loops, bulges and kissing loops). Using the web interface, the user can search for structural elements based on their NC-IUBMB nomenclature (17), type of junction, inter-helical angles, PDB identifier, the RNAJunction identifier, sequence, experimental method, author of the corresponding published structure or parts of the text contained in the header records of the PDB structure. The results of a search are displayed by listing a summary of all matching structural elements. Users may then click on a database identifier which points to a page providing more detailed information about a particular structural element. Result page of an RNA loop&#x2013;loop interaction derived from PDB structure 2BJ2. Result page of an RNA loop&#x2013;loop interaction derived from PDB structure 2BJ2. The RNAjunction database is freely available at http://rnajunction.abcc.ncifcrf.gov General queries can be performed using virtually any web browser; displaying 3D structures with JMol requires the browser to be able to run Java applets. The database is available for download (structures, JunctionScanner output, images) upon request. Periodic updates will be made based upon the availability of new RNA structures.
</content>
</document>
