<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <id>2238937</id>
  <title>PROCOGNATE: a cognate ligand domain mapping for enzymes
</title>
  <abstract>
 PROCOGNATE is a database of protein cognate ligands for the domains in enzyme structures as described by CATH, SCOP and Pfam, and is available as an interactive website or a flat file. This article gives an overview of the database and its generation and presents a new website front end, as well as recent increased coverage in our dataset via inclusion of Pfam domains. We also describe navigation of the website and its features. The current version (1.3) of PROCOGNATE covers 4123, 4536, 5876 structures and 377, 326, 695 superfamilies/families in CATH, SCOP and Pfam, respectively. PROCOGNATE can be accessed at: http://www.ebi.ac.uk/thornton-srv/databases/procognate/
</abstract>
  <content>
 Frequently when enzyme structures are determined in vitro by X-ray crystallography or NMR, the resulting structures do not incorporate the natural substrate or product of an enzyme. Instead these ligands are often inhibitors or substrate analogues. The aim of this database is to first assign the binding of particular ligands to the evolutionary units, domains of the CATH (1), SCOP (2) and Pfam (3) databases (as observed in the experiment), and, second to make sure that the actual substrate from the enzyme's known reactions in vivo are assigned where possible. Thus, the range of actual ligands bound by a superfamily or family can be investigated. By cognate ligand, we mean one which would be found listed for that enzyme's Enzyme Commission (EC) number. We achieve this by combining data from the worldwide Protein Data Bank (wwPDB) (4) as provided in the Macromolecular Structure Database (MSD) (5), the ENZYME (6) enzyme nomenclature database and the KEGG (7) pathway database. A full description of the methodology and findings from the database can be found in Bashton et al. (8). Here we present an expanded coverage of our original dataset, notably by the addition of Pfam domain definitions and the development of a website front end. Various other websites or databases offer some but not all of the features of PROCOGNATE. These include PDBLIG (9), BIND (10), PDBsum (11), MSDsite (12), Relibase (13) and Ligand Depot (14) but none combine information on cognate ligands and domain assignments. Thus our database offers a unique resource in offering cognate-ligand information for domains of CATH, SCOP and Pfam and for facilitating the investigation of the evolutionary unit of proteins, domains, in relation to their molecular recognition roles. Our database provides a list of validated cognate ligands for domains and protein structures, avoiding the problem of using data directly from the PDB where many inhibitors or substrate analogues will be present. This &#x2018;validated&#x2019; data with corrected ligands is essential for the investigation of domain evolution and the prediction of protein function. We hope to use our data for the prediction of potential ligands bound by proteins of unknown function but known domain composition. Additionally, the database will be useful for the generation of test sets for benchmarking, programs, or methods that predict the binding of cognate ligands to proteins. This procedure involves two steps; first, we assign the binding of particular ligands to particular domains; second, we compare the chemical similarity of the PDB ligands to ligands in KEGG in order to assign cognate ligands. Database generation is automated via a series of scripts; no manual assignment is required. Binding sites may be located on different chains or even discontinuous segments of sequence. Some ligands may be bound by more than one domain, either proportionally in a shared manner, or disproportionately with the vast majority of contacts coming from one domain only. Therefore in order to produce the cognate-ligand mapping, we first assigned the binding of the PDB ligands to specific domains in protein structures. We retrieve the total number of contacts made to any one ligand by the whole structural assembly and each domain of CATH, SCOP and Pfam in each chain from the MSD. The contact data to each ligand is retrieved from the MSD per residue level. The MSD contains contact data for the following types of bonds: hydrogen bonds, van der Waals interactions, ionic and covalent bonds, aromatic ring interactions and in absence of another type of interaction, a generic 4 &#xC5; interaction. Further details of definition of these types of bonds and interactions in the MSD can be found in Golovin et al. (12). If any one domain has greater than, or equal to, 75% of the total contacts to a particular ligand, then the binding of that ligand is assigned to that domain, and the mode of binding is recorded as &#x2018;non-shared&#x2019;. If no one domain has 75% or more of the contacts, then all contacting domains are recorded as binding the ligand and the mode of binding is recorded as &#x2018;shared&#x2019;. All ligands in a PDB entry for a structure are compared using 2D graph matching to all compounds known to be substrates, products or cofactors for that enzyme, using data from the ENZYME and KEGG databases, and the most appropriate (i.e. chemically similar) cognate ligands are then matched up with the PDB ligands present in the PDB structure. We used 2D graph matching [using the Chemistry Development Kit libraries (15)] to compare the chemical structures of the PDB ligands and those from KEGG. We use the Tanimoto score to assess the similarity of the ligands:where Nsub is the number of atoms in the maximum common substructure, NA is the number of atoms of molecule A and NB the number of atoms in molecule B. In order to qualify as &#x2018;cognate-like&#x2019;, a PDB ligand needs to have a Tanimoto score of &gt;0.5. We chose this cutoff as &#x223C;99% of all random graph-matching scores are equal to or less than 0.5, hence we can safely consider values higher than that as significant. Finally, the domain-ligand mapping is cross-referenced with the cognate-ligand mapping to give a cognate ligand domain mapping whereby each domain, which binds a ligand, has an assigned potential cognate taken from the various reactions catalysed by the enzyme. The similarity score of the successfully assigned potential cognate ligands are quoted on the website adjacent to each assignment. Coverage for the various releases of PROCOGNATE. Pfam domains have only been in the dataset since version 1.3 Coverage for the various releases of PROCOGNATE. Pfam domains have only been in the dataset since version 1.3 Search categories available from the main page, examples are also provided along with description of the results of such a search Search categories available from the main page, examples are also provided along with description of the results of such a search Main per PDB view page for structure 9ldt. The page shows two domains, each of which binds various PDB ligands, which in turn have assigned cognate ligands. The cognate ligand NAD+ has been clicked which brings up its 2D structure in a separate window. Reaction page for NAD+ of 9ldt. Here the various EC numbers and associated KEGG reactions are shown for 9ldt, where NAD is used. Reaction page for NAD+ of 9ldt. Here the various EC numbers and associated KEGG reactions are shown for 9ldt, where NAD is used. Searching with a SCOP or CATH superfamily will list all families in that superfamily, and in addition all cognate ligands, EC numbers and KEGG reactions associated with that superfamily. Following the link for a family will re-launch the search but at the family (rather than superfamily) level and also bring up individual structures. Searching with Pfam takes place at the family level as no subfamilies are contained within a Pfam family. The results of searching for cognate ligand name glucose. The search first returns a list of cognate ligands with the text glucose in their name. Clicking on one of these then searches with that particular ligand&#x2014;this is shown in the second screen shot on the right. The results of searching for cognate ligand name glucose. The search first returns a list of cognate ligands with the text glucose in their name. Clicking on one of these then searches with that particular ligand&#x2014;this is shown in the second screen shot on the right. Our database is freely available; the tab delimited flat file for all versions of PROCOGNATE for each different domain definition can be downloaded from http://www.ebi.ac.uk/thornton-srv/databases/procognate/download.html. Currently the website focuses on providing interactive access and facilitating querying the database backend providing cognate-ligand assignments for structures of enzymes in the PDB. We aim to expand the functionality of the website to offer a prediction of ligand binding for both user-submitted sequences and structures based on similarity to the known domains in our database and their ligand-binding profiles.
</content>
</document>
