<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <id>2238898</id>
  <title>The Gypsy Database (GyDB) of mobile genetic elements
</title>
  <abstract>
 In this article, we introduce the Gypsy Database (GyDB) of mobile genetic elements, an in-progress database devoted to the non-redundant analysis and evolutionary-based classification of mobile genetic elements. In this first version, we contemplate eukaryotic Ty3/Gypsy and Retroviridae long terminal repeats (LTR) retroelements. Phylogenetic analyses based on the gag-pro-pol internal region commonly presented by these two groups strongly support a certain number of previously described Ty3/Gypsy lineages originally reported from reverse-transcriptase (RT) analyses. Vertebrate retroviruses (Retroviridae) are also constituted in several monophyletic groups consistent with genera proposed by the ICTV nomenclature, as well as with the current tendency to classify both endogenous and exogenous retroviruses by three major classes (I, II and III). Our inference indicates that all protein domains codified by the gag-pro-pol internal region of these two groups agree in a collective presentation of a particular evolutionary history, which may be used as a main criterion to differentiate their molecular diversity in a comprehensive collection of phylogenies and non-redundant molecular profiles useful in the identification of new Ty3/Gypsy and Retroviridae species. The GyDB project is available at http://gydb.uv.es.
</abstract>
  <content>
 Since the existence of mobile DNA was first suggested by McClintock (1), mobile genetic elements have been an important object of study in multiple areas of biological research (2). Mobile genetic elements are self-contained genomic units capable of proliferating within their host genomes. Nearly all fit into three major functional categories: Class I are all reverse-transcriptase (RT) dependent retroelements (3) that mediate their transposition life cycle through an RNA&#x2013;DNA reverse transcription process; Class II are DNA-based transposons that move directly from one position to another in host genomes (1,4,5) and Class III are the miniature inverted-repeats transposable elements (MITEs) (6,7). With continuous efforts in sequencing and annotation, the field of genomics has been dramatically expanded in the attempt to understand the gene organization of genomes, as well as the bioinformatic and empirical characterization of open reading frames (ORFs). Most of these efforts have revealed mobile genetic elements to be more widely distributed in the genomes of eukaryotes than previously thought; it is thus, commonly accepted that they may have played an important role in the evolution of life and the origin of eukaryotic complexity (8). With the aim of furthering knowledge in this field, we have built the GyDB, a research project in which we analyze and classify non-redundant mobile genetic elements based on their evolutionary profiles. Due to their impressive molecular diversity, the GyDB is a long-term project that has been arranged in a database in continuous progress and must be achieved in stages. In this article, we introduce the database and its background focusing on Ty3/Gypsy and Retroviridae long terminal repeats (LTR) retroelements (LTR retrotransposons and retroviruses). The database also focuses on certain non-viral protein families related to these two groups. (a) Genomic structure of a basal retrovirus, and logos to graphically represent the consensus for both the PBS and the PPT motifs. (b) Screenshot of the GyDB websites specific to families and protein domains. (a) Genomic structure of a basal retrovirus, and logos to graphically represent the consensus for both the PBS and the PPT motifs. (b) Screenshot of the GyDB websites specific to families and protein domains. MRC tree inferred for Ty3/Gypsy and Retroviridae LTR retroelements using the parsimony method and based on a concatenated gag-pro-pol multiple alignment. Host organisms and monophyletic clusters are detailed at left. MRC trees usually consist of all groups that occur more than 50% of the time, we take consensus values higher than 55 as an equivalent-bootstrapping reference. MRC tree inferred for Ty3/Gypsy and Retroviridae LTR retroelements using the parsimony method and based on a concatenated gag-pro-pol multiple alignment. Host organisms and monophyletic clusters are detailed at left. MRC trees usually consist of all groups that occur more than 50% of the time, we take consensus values higher than 55 as an equivalent-bootstrapping reference. The Gypsy database. Accessory genes and complex retroviruses The Gypsy database. Accessory genes and complex retroviruses It is well known that several protein domains encoded by retroelements in general are related to certain families of non-viral proteins present in the genomes of eukaryotes and prokaryotes. It is thus commonly accepted that these kinds of proteins have an ancient relationship with retroelements. The origin of mobile genetic elements, as well as their role in the evolution of eukaryotic complexity, is thus a fascinating subject of discussion and controversy. We are particularly interested in this topic and have considered in this first version or our database the following three non-viral protein families related to LTR retroelements: chromodomains (50), GIN-1 integrases (51) and clan AA of aspartic peptidases (52). Each of these has its own website and phylogeny within the GyDB. One of the most important goals of our project is to provide a set of competent services to facilitate the identification and taxonomical classification of new retroelement species. In an attempt to support further sequence&#x2013;sequence identification, we have implemented a BLAST search (53) that allows the typical comparisons to the following databases: LTR, GENOME and CORES. These databases respectively contain the LTR nucleotide sequences, the complete element genome and the core of each detectable protein domain encoded by the LTR retroelements we currently classify. Results are reported in the conventional BLAST output. However, similarities detected by an unknown query are identified by the name of the element to which the detected sequence belongs, and provide a link to the sequence's Genbank accession. The GyDB BLAST databases are non-redundant, and specific. This facilitates the analysis of pairwise similarities among both closely and distantly related sequences with the same known function. On the other hand, Hidden Markov Model (HMM) profiles are statistical models that capture position-specific information on the degree of conservation in the DNA or protein domain architecture of an alignment and model the primary structure consensus of a family of protein or DNA sequences. Taking this into account we have also constructed, using HMMER Version 2.3.2 (54), a collection of HMM profiles considering for each protein domain a certain number of local multiple alignments extrapolated from the monophyletic clusters reported by the gag-pol-tree summarized in Figure 2. Our HMM profiles are part of the GyDB collection, which consists of a set of non-redundant multiple alignments, HMM profiles and MRC sequences, available to Biotech Vana registered users only (Biotech Vana Bioinformatics, in preparation). However, we implement a publicly available HMM server that, via HMMER, permits a user to search the entire HMM profile database with an unknown query or to search the CORES database using an HMM profile as a query. Outputs are generated in the usual style of HMMER, and allow users to easily identify the clade and/or genus to which a protein query taxonomically belongs. By way of this server users can access a database with citations specific to Ty3/Gypsy and Retroviridae LTR retroelements. The typical filters of year, journal, author and title may be applied in searches. Each displayed citation links to the PubMed Central digital archive at NCBI. Database arrangement and navigation. Database arrangement and navigation. Hits for protein family classification of the env polyprotein of PyERV Hits for protein family classification of the gag-pro-pol internal region of PyERV (a) Pairwise alignment between the ORFX MRC sequence and the PyERV&#x2013;ORF X. (b) Multiple alignment. (a) Pairwise alignment between the ORFX MRC sequence and the PyERV&#x2013;ORF X. (b) Multiple alignment. The GyDB project pursues the fascinating goal of analyzing and classifying the non-redundant diversity of mobile genetic elements in the context of the Tree of Life, and based on their evolutionary profiles. Due to their impressive molecular diversity, the GyDB is a long-term project that has been arranged in a database in continuous progress, and must be achieved in stages. In this first version, we contemplate the eukaryotic Ty3/Gypsy and Retroviridae LTR retroelements and demonstrate that the entire molecular diversity inherent to these two groups of LTR retroelements may be used as a main criterion of classification to generate a comprehensive collection of molecular profiles and phylogenies. We pay special attention to non-redundant elements displaying the full-length genome available and a certain degree of distance, as well as to how their entire coding product may be collectively aligned or related in terms of protein domain architecture with other lineages and elements. This is an effort worth making, as we have been able to infer the evolutionary perspectives of the elements we classify based on the complete internal region they commonly display. The GyDB is thus a small but highly informative database established within a phylogenetic context of classification, useful in viral taxonomy and capable of facilitating further identification and analysis of new LTR retroelement species. However, the most captivating aspect of our project is that we dedicate a share of our efforts to the interpretation of our analyses. In Llorens and Moya (manuscript submitted for publication, PLoS ONE) we differentiate the entire clan AA in monophyletic groups of homodomain peptidases in order to reconstruct the ancestral state for each monophyletic group and a consensus template that approximates the molecular phenotype of an ancestor from which the entire clan AA evolves. In another forthcoming study (in preparation) we phylogenetically and comparatively explore the evolutionary meaning of gag-pro-pol diversity. Following from our results, we introduce a guiding principle&#x2014;the Three Kings Hypothesis&#x2014;with which we suggest that the early origins of the Retroviridae diversity might be more ancient than previously thought, and polyphyletic. We will incorporate in the next GyDB version new non-redundant elements belonging to other LTR retroelement lineages. We think all these incorporations will allow the GyDB to enable exciting insights, leading to a better understanding of the taxonomy and evolutionary history of LTR retroelements. However, as the annotation of new Ty3/Gypsy and Retroviridae lineages (25,62&#x2013;64) is constantly growing and we may have not considered in this version, sequences phylogenetically relevant to the database background, the Ty3/Gypsy and Retroviridae scenario is always open for further evidence. The GyDB project is freely available at http://gydb.uv.es.
</content>
</document>
