<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <id>2238935</id>
  <title>OPTIC: orthologous and paralogous transcripts in clades
</title>
  <abstract>
 The genome sequences of a large number of metazoan species are now known. As multiple closely related genomes are sequenced, comparative studies that previously focussed on only pairs of genomes can now be extended over whole clades. The orthologous and paralogous transcripts in clades (OPTIC) database currently provides sets of gene predictions and orthology assignments for three clades: (i) amniotes, including human, dog, mouse, opossum, platypus and chicken (17 443 orthologous groups); (ii) a Drosophila clade of 12 species (12 889 orthologous groups) and (iii) a nematode clade of four species (13 626 orthologous groups). Gene predictions, multiple alignments and phylogenetic trees are freely available to browse and download from http://genserv.anat.ox.ac.uk/clades. Further genomes and clades will be added in the future.
</abstract>
  <content>
 Gene sets and orthology assignments in three clades Gene sets marked with an asterisk (*) were obtained from ENSEMBL, whereas all others have been predicted by the pipeline. Orphans represent genes that have no ortholog in any of the other genomes in the clade. These will represent results of heuristic failures in our ortholog prediction pipeline or in gene predictions, as well as true gene losses. Gene sets marked with an asterisk (*) were obtained from ENSEMBL, whereas all others have been predicted by the pipeline. Orphans represent genes that have no ortholog in any of the other genomes in the clade. These will represent results of heuristic failures in our ortholog prediction pipeline or in gene predictions, as well as true gene losses. The pipeline predicts orthology for both orthologous groups and simple 1:1 ortholog sets. Here, orthologous groups contain orthologs and in-paralogs but exclude out-paralogs (1), those duplicated genes that were each present in the last common ancestor of a clade. Simple 1:1 ortholog sets are derived from orthologous groups by examining the gene tree and extracting sub-trees that contain exactly one gene per species. To enable inferences of gene duplication or loss, or positive selection on individual codons, we supply amino acid or nucleotide multiple sequence alignments, and phylogenetic trees, for each orthologous group. All data may be searched or downloaded freely from http://genserv.anat.ox.ac.uk/download/clades. Gene prediction by homology from a transcript set using Exonerate (3). BlastP (4) all-against-all alignments of all translated transcripts and PhyOP (5) tree-based orthology assignment of genes. PhyOP (5) tree-based orthology assignment of genes. Graph-based grouping of genes from all species into clusters. Multiple alignment of translated exons using MUSCLE (6). Estimation of phylogenetic tree topology using NJTree (7). Decomposition of clusters into orthologous groups. Branch length estimation using codeml from the PAML package (8). Computation of simple 1:1 ortholog sets. Computation of simple 1:1 ortholog sets. Data are stored in a relational database and gene predictions are displayed within a GMOD genome browser (http://www.gmod.org). Software is open source and available without charge on request to the authors. For the current release, we have applied our pipeline to three metazoan clades (Table 1) each containing between 4 and 12 species. Genes were predicted for Drosophila and Caenorhabditis species&#x2019; genome assemblies using D. melanogaster (9) and C. elegans (10) protein-coding transcripts as templates. Mammalian and chicken gene sets were from ENSEMBL release 42 (2). The web server provides an up-to-date list of genome assemblies for the current release. We find 12 889 orthologous groups in the Drosophila clade, 17 443 groups in the amniotic clade and 13 626 groups in the four Caenorhabditis species. Of these, 10 563 orthologous groups in the Drosophila clade, 9675 groups in the amniotic clade and 6545 groups in the Caenorhabditis clade contain the full species complements. The numbers of simple 1:1 ortholog sets are smaller (5241, 7587, and 5987 for the three clades, respectively) owing to gene duplications and absences from incomplete assemblies. For each orthologous group, we provide: Transcript predictions: Predicted transcripts are available as exonic genomic coordinates, and as peptide and coding sequences. Orthologs: Orthologous groups and simple 1:1 ortholog sets. Multiple alignments: Multiple alignments of transcripts and genes within an orthologous group are provided both as aligned nucleic acid sequences and as aligned peptide sequences. Frameshift insertions or deletions in pseudogenes have been removed, and stop-codons have been masked in order to facilitate downstream analyses. Genes have been aligned by concatenating exons of all transcripts while maintaining frame. Phylogenetic trees: For each orthologous group, we provide a phylogenetic tree. The topology of the tree has been calculated from NJTree, while branch lengths (nucleotide substitutions per site) have been assigned using PAML. Browsing the orthology database. A sample session starts with a query for all simple 1:1 ortholog sets (bottom left). It continues with a list of all simple 1:1 ortholog sets containing all six species from the amniotic clade, then by a selection of one particular ortholog set (number 114), and finally with a viewing of the gene-based multiple sequence alignment. Browsing the orthology database. A sample session starts with a query for all simple 1:1 ortholog sets (bottom left). It continues with a list of all simple 1:1 ortholog sets containing all six species from the amniotic clade, then by a selection of one particular ortholog set (number 114), and finally with a viewing of the gene-based multiple sequence alignment. In queries for simple 1:1 ortholog sets, &#x2018;1&#x2019; indicates that exactly one copy of this gene is present and &#x2018;&#x2013;&#x2019; indicates that this particular species should not be considered. Thus, the profile &#x2018;111&#x2013;&#x2013;&#x2013;&#x2019; applied to simple 1:1 ortholog sets yields 13 788 simple 1:1 ortholog sets that contain exactly one gene in human, dog and mouse, and any number of homologs in opossum, platypus or chicken. For each orthologous group and simple 1:1 ortholog set, multiple alignments and a phylogenetic tree may be displayed. A synteny viewer also allows an assessment of whether orthologs occur in regions of conserved synteny. Genes of particular interest can be located either by identifier or by genomic location. Computational biologists interested in performing large-scale analyses can download complete datasets from the download area. OPTIC is designed to provide precalculated phylogenetic datasets that are of benefit to clade genomic analyses. Our approach complements other existing projects (2,7,12, 12) in four respects: (i) we apply the pipeline to diverse, and not just experimental model, organisms; (ii) we define clades with respect to phylogenetic distances that are amenable to evolutionary rate analysis (roughly, where the number of synonymous substitutions per synonymous site is &lt;2.0 (5)); (iii) our orthology relationships are inferred by considering all species equally, in a phylogenetic approach and (4) we use all exons across all alternative transcripts as opposed to the longest transcripts only. A particularly useful feature of OPTIC is its provision of multiple alignments either for genes as concatenated exons, or for alternative transcripts. We plan to update gene predictions and orthology assignments and add more genomes and clades when they become available.
</content>
</document>
