<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <id>2238881</id>
  <title>ChemBank: a small-molecule screening and cheminformatics resource database
</title>
  <abstract>
 ChemBank (http://chembank.broad.harvard.edu/) is a public, web-based informatics environment developed through a collaboration between the Chemical Biology Program and Platform at the Broad Institute of Harvard and MIT. This knowledge environment includes freely available data derived from small molecules and small-molecule screens and resources for studying these data. ChemBank is unique among small-molecule databases in its dedication to the storage of raw screening data, its rigorous definition of screening experiments in terms of statistical hypothesis testing, and its metadata-based organization of screening experiments into projects involving collections of related assays. ChemBank stores an increasingly varied set of measurements derived from cells and other biological assay systems treated with small molecules. Analysis tools are available and are continuously being developed that allow the relationships between small molecules, cell measurements, and cell states to be studied. Currently, ChemBank stores information on hundreds of thousands of small molecules and hundreds of biomedically relevant assays that have been performed at the Broad Institute by collaborators from the worldwide research community. The goal of ChemBank is to provide life scientists unfettered access to biomedically relevant data and tools heretofore available primarily in the private sector.
</abstract>
  <content>
 ChemBank v1.0 was initiated as a National Cancer Institute (NCI)-sponsored activity within the Initiative for Chemical Genetics (ICG), originally at Harvard's Institute of Chemistry and Cell Biology. The evolving interest of the NCI in sponsoring chemical-genetic research has been reported (1), as has the evolution of ICG as a public research effort dedicated to accelerating the discovery of cancer-relevant small-molecule probes (2). At present, ChemBank v2.0 (hereafter referred to as ChemBank) represents an evolving collaboration between the Chemical Biology Program and Chemical Biology Platform at the Broad Institute of Harvard and MIT, including interactions with academic synthetic chemists and biologists interested in high-throughput, small-molecule screening approaches. ChemBank houses chemical structures and names, calculated molecular descriptors, human-curated biological information regarding small molecule activities, raw experimental results from high-throughput biological assays, and extensive metadata describing screening experiments. While there are many other publicly available small-molecule and drug databases [ChEBI (3), DrugBank (4), PubChem (5) and ZINC (6), among others], ChemBank is unique in three important ways: (i) its dedication to the storage of raw screening data; (ii) its rigorous definition of screening experiments in terms of statistical hypothesis testing; and (iii) its hierarchical metadata-based organization of related assays into screening projects. Moreover, the ChemBank website is more than a simple data repository; it contains tools for visualization and analysis of small-molecule results, including raw and normalized high-throughput screening (HTS) data and chemical-genetic profiles. Data sets may be manipulated within ChemBank or downloaded for use with external analysis tools. ChemBank is a powerful knowledge repository and analysis environment for chemists and biologists alike. Conceptual summary of ChemBank schema. Logical illustration of ChemBank data model, in which 95 tables are organized into groups representing components of the chemical biology research enterprise. Each box represents several actual database tables, as indicated, and pseudocardinality relationships between boxes are meant to convey conceptual relationships, rather than the more complex cardinality relationships that relate the actual tables. Conceptual summary of ChemBank schema. Logical illustration of ChemBank data model, in which 95 tables are organized into groups representing components of the chemical biology research enterprise. Each box represents several actual database tables, as indicated, and pseudocardinality relationships between boxes are meant to convey conceptual relationships, rather than the more complex cardinality relationships that relate the actual tables. Anyone with Internet access can use ChemBank, without registering with a username and password, using the &#x2018;Enter as a Guest&#x2019; button. However, registration is highly encouraged of all users, as guest users are not permitted to export data from ChemBank. Registered users of ChemBank may download data directly from their search results using the &#x2018;[export &#x2026;]&#x2019; hyperlinks on several ChemBank webpages. Downloadable result files are exported in tab-delimited text format for maximum flexibility of use in other applications. Simple Object Access Protocol (SOAP) web-service access is provided for much of the data in ChemBank. Service calls exist to list all projects and assays within ChemBank, as well as assay plates and well measurements. There are also molecule services allowing similarity and substructure searches of molecules within ChemBank. The Web-service Definition Language (WSDL) files for these services can be found on the ChemBank website (http://chembank.broad.harvard.edu/webServices.htm). As a repository of primary data from HTS experiments, ChemBank employs a data-embargo strategy to protect newly generated data for a specified period, and accordingly, ChemBank comprises two separate websites containing overlapping datasets. Public ChemBank (http://chembank.broad.harvard.edu/) contains small-molecule assay data that are more than one year old as well as molecular descriptors and published bioactivity annotation for registered small molecules. Data-Sharing-Agreement (DSA)-ChemBank contains all of the data content of Public ChemBank as well as small-molecule assay data that are less than one year old. Use of the latter database is restricted to scientists who have deposited compounds or performed screening experiments at the Broad Institute of Harvard and MIT and who have signed a DSA (http://www.broad.harvard.edu/chembio/sci/screen/facil/DataSharingAgreement.pdf). The DSA stipulates conditions of participation, such as shared authorship, intellectual property and expectations for sharing follow-up data. All scientists who have signed the agreement may browse the entire contents of DSA-ChemBank and renew their agreements annually for continued access to this resource. Registration for this version of ChemBank is required, and usernames and passwords are assigned by the ChemBank team upon receipt of the signed agreement. DSA-ChemBank users log in using their assigned username and password at a different URL (http://chembank-dsa.broad.harvard.edu/). ChemBank offers multiple routes to find chemical information. Search tools allowing structure drawing (28) for substructure or similarity searches (a), selection of calculated molecular descriptors (b) and selection of term-based bioactivity annotations (c), each provide avenues to find individual molecules or sets of molecules in ChemBank. The ChemBank &#x2018;Molecule Display&#x2019; webpage (background) provides detailed information about each molecule, including structure, names, molecular descriptors, biological annotations, sample information and screening instances. ChemBank offers multiple routes to find chemical information. Search tools allowing structure drawing (28) for substructure or similarity searches (a), selection of calculated molecular descriptors (b) and selection of term-based bioactivity annotations (c), each provide avenues to find individual molecules or sets of molecules in ChemBank. The ChemBank &#x2018;Molecule Display&#x2019; webpage (background) provides detailed information about each molecule, including structure, names, molecular descriptors, biological annotations, sample information and screening instances. Relationship of ChemBank &#x2018;View Project&#x2019; and &#x2018;View Assay&#x2019; webpages. Screenshots of representative screening project and assay (inset) webpages. Emphasis (red boxes, arrow) has been added to highlight key information, including project description and motivation (a), individual assays within project (b), detailed description (shared by both webpages) of assay protocol (c) and individual screening plates within assay (d). Relationship of ChemBank &#x2018;View Project&#x2019; and &#x2018;View Assay&#x2019; webpages. Screenshots of representative screening project and assay (inset) webpages. Emphasis (red boxes, arrow) has been added to highlight key information, including project description and motivation (a), individual assays within project (b), detailed description (shared by both webpages) of assay protocol (c) and individual screening plates within assay (d). Simple queries can be combined to generate complex, multi-criterion searches. ChemBank has an extensive multi-criterion search interface, which allows searches to be constructed interactively. This interface supports modification of prior search criteria or addition of new criteria, and can be used even after initial search results are returned. Additionally, data analysis on a single or combination of screens housed within ChemBank can be performed and visualized as detailed in the following section. More information on conducting ChemBank searches and webpages can be found in the Help section (http://chembank.broad.harvard.edu/details.htm?tag=Help). ChemBank houses both raw and normalized experimental results from many HTS and small-molecule microarray (SMM) (7) projects. These datasets are the foundation for a data-analysis model specifically equipped to accumulate rich profiles of small-molecule performance across multiple, diverse biological assays. One of the primary requirements of this approach is a data-analysis strategy for small-molecule performance that affords normalized values independent of both the screening technology platform and the specific biological question under investigation. ChemBank users are not restricted to this standard analysis paradigm; rather, each of the ChemBank data-visualization tools affords access to multiple data types along the analysis process, including raw data, background-subtracted data and replicate-handled data. ChemBank seeks to provide cross-sectional analysis and multi-assay performance profiles (8&#x2013;14). Therefore, we supplemented ChemBank raw screening data with normalized data using an error model with several salient features. First, it renders the results of multiple parallel assays formally comparable, regardless of the original signal amplitudes or units of measurement. Second, it introduces no assumptions about the strength of signal required to call screening positives. This condition rules out the use of arbitrary thresholds such as 2-fold induction or 50% inhibition (15,16). Third, it does not rely on global assumptions about the compound collection, particularly the assumption that most compounds will be inert in any given assay (17,18). These three conditions suggested the use of only mock-treatment wells as a basis for well-to-well, plate-to-plate and experiment-to-experiment normalization. We reasoned that in any miniaturized assay of small-molecule performance, we can always define a mock-treatment condition that mirrors compound treatment in every way except for the presence of the compound. For example, in a typical HTS experiment, this condition is represented by the treatment of otherwise identical assay-well contents with the delivery vehicle, usually dimethylsulfoxide. We conceptualize our scoring method in terms of a formal hypothesis test comparing a compound-treatment with its associated mock-treatment distribution, and thus seek the most reliable estimates of the statistical parameters associated with this test. In an ideal world, one would simply make many measurements of a compound's performance in a particular assay system, and many measurements of the corresponding vehicle mock-treatment condition in that assay system. In such a case, our primary score for a compound would be similar to the Z' statistic for evaluating HTS methods during assay development (15,19). Since making a statistically meaningful number of measurements of each compound's performance is not practical, we estimate the parameters of the compound-treatment distribution from the parameters of the mock-treatment distribution. At present, ChemBank uses a constant-error assumption for plate-reader assays, and a variable error assumption for small-molecule microarrays (see subsequent paragraph). ChemBank standard data-analysis model for high-throughput small-molecule screens. All raw small-molecule assay results in ChemBank are further processed by comparing each measurement with the collection of mock-treatment well measurements performed in the same screening experiment. Median values from mock-treatment wells on the same plate are used in an initial zero-centering step (a), after which the distribution of mock-treatment measurements for the entire experiment is trimmed to eliminate systematic artifacts (b). Trimmed mock-treatment measurements are used to normalize assay performance by first subtracting the mean of trimmed mock-treatment measurements on the same plate to give &#x2018;background-subtracted values&#x2019; (c), then dividing by twice the standard deviation of trimmed mock-treatment measurements for the entire experiment to give &#x2018;dimensionless Z-score values&#x2019; (d). Replicate handling is performed by cosine correlation of the replicate pair (for screens done in duplicate) of &#x2018;dimensionless Z-score values&#x2019; for each compound with a simple prior model of &#x2018;perfect reproducibility&#x2019;, to yield a &#x2018;Composite Z-score value&#x2019; (e) that represents the final primary screening result. The ChemBank web interface provides access to raw and processed data types appropriate for each of its visualization tools (f). ChemBank standard data-analysis model for high-throughput small-molecule screens. All raw small-molecule assay results in ChemBank are further processed by comparing each measurement with the collection of mock-treatment well measurements performed in the same screening experiment. Median values from mock-treatment wells on the same plate are used in an initial zero-centering step (a), after which the distribution of mock-treatment measurements for the entire experiment is trimmed to eliminate systematic artifacts (b). Trimmed mock-treatment measurements are used to normalize assay performance by first subtracting the mean of trimmed mock-treatment measurements on the same plate to give &#x2018;background-subtracted values&#x2019; (c), then dividing by twice the standard deviation of trimmed mock-treatment measurements for the entire experiment to give &#x2018;dimensionless Z-score values&#x2019; (d). Replicate handling is performed by cosine correlation of the replicate pair (for screens done in duplicate) of &#x2018;dimensionless Z-score values&#x2019; for each compound with a simple prior model of &#x2018;perfect reproducibility&#x2019;, to yield a &#x2018;Composite Z-score value&#x2019; (e) that represents the final primary screening result. The ChemBank web interface provides access to raw and processed data types appropriate for each of its visualization tools (f). Illustration of ChemBank visualizations and linking activities with chemical information. Screening data, including raw measurements, in ChemBank are addressable by exact plate and well position in assay plates (a), and statistical data representing outcomes (b) can be reviewed at the level of raw or normalized data. A multi-assay analysis capability takes advantage of the standard analysis procedure (Figure 4) to display the performance of such similar compounds in multiple assays to which each has been exposed (c). Each of these capabilities can be combined with structure and annotation-based search capabilities to provide cheminformatic analysis of molecules scoring as &#x2018;hits&#x2019; in biological assays (d). Illustration of ChemBank visualizations and linking activities with chemical information. Screening data, including raw measurements, in ChemBank are addressable by exact plate and well position in assay plates (a), and statistical data representing outcomes (b) can be reviewed at the level of raw or normalized data. A multi-assay analysis capability takes advantage of the standard analysis procedure (Figure 4) to display the performance of such similar compounds in multiple assays to which each has been exposed (c). Each of these capabilities can be combined with structure and annotation-based search capabilities to provide cheminformatic analysis of molecules scoring as &#x2018;hits&#x2019; in biological assays (d). Data curation activities for ChemBank fall into two general categories: 1) annotation of information regarding small molecules, and 2) annotation of information regarding small-molecule assays. Annotations regarding small-molecule effects on biological systems are generated from the primary literature. Hyperlinks to other databases such as Entrez Gene (24), GO (25), MeSH (http://www.nlm.nih.gov/mesh/meshhome.html) and PubMed (5), are collected manually during curation activities. Small molecules and clinically used drugs often have multiple names; some drugs have dozens of different brand and generic names. ChemBank names are curated from multiple sources including public databases, the United States Pharmacopeia (USP) Dictionary, the World Health Organization (WHO) International Non-proprietary Name database (http://mednet.who.int/public/default.aspx?c=1f216b1a-c080-46a1-9a39-c33717387926), and chemical vendor websites to provide an exhaustive list of names and synonyms for molecules. For a subset of the bioactive small molecules in ChemBank, activity annotations from the biological literature have been added. Bioactivity annotations (see also Figure 2) are divided into four categories: (i) Biochemical Interactions, which indicate protein molecular targets or GO molecular functions (25) affected by the small molecule; (ii) Therapeutic Indications, which specify what diseases (i.e. MeSH terms) a small molecule is used to treat or manage; (iii) Therapeutic Uses, terms from an internally derived vocabulary that indicates what type of clinical or biological activity a small molecule possesses; and (iv) Biological Processes, which indicate GO biological processes affected by the small molecule. PubMed IDs (5) corresponding to these citations have been captured, but are not yet exposed to the user and GO terms (Biochemical Interactions and Biological Processes) describing the effect(s) of the small molecule (e.g. &#x2018;increases apoptosis&#x2019;) are displayed but do not currently connect directly to the GO website (http://amigo.geneontology.org). Annotation surrounding biological assays is collected as field-based metadata using internal controlled vocabularies, and is used to describe screening projects, experiments, and assay plates. Metadata associated with a screening project express the biological motivation and are displayed on the &#x2018;View Project&#x2019; webpage; metadata associated with the details of a particular assay (instantiated as a screening &#x2018;experiment&#x2019;; see above) are displayed on the &#x2018;View Assay&#x2019; webpage (see also Figure 3). For many of the most frequently screened small molecules in ChemBank, annotation of autofluorescence activity is available to reduce false positives by providing automated filtering in addition to detailed information about the optical properties of the compounds. Annotation includes a binary filter of autofluorescence, a plot of the range of wavelengths above a signal threshold, a plot of the shape of the spectra and a contour plot showing the autofluorescence over a range that includes wavelengths of common filter pairs. Additional details about autofluorescence detection and data-analysis methods are available on the ChemBank website (http://chembank.broad.harvard.edu/details.htm?tag=Help#autoFluorMethodology). ChemBank is a unique knowledge and analysis environment for small molecules and high-throughput small-molecule assays. It provides calculated molecular descriptors, experimental assay measurements, and literature-based annotation for small molecules, allowing integration of both new and established information in a single, public resource. Other public small-molecule databases exist, and the following examples are meant to be illustrative, not comprehensive. BindingDB (26) curates small-molecule binding affinities for protein targets from the literature. KEGG LIGAND (27) and its associated entry points seek to catalog and integrate chemical structures, biochemical reactions, and biological information into a single database. ZINC (6) is a database of three-dimensional compound structures intended for virtual screening applications. These products and the many other examples available serve to illustrate that each project has a different focus, and each is designed accordingly. Content and feature comparison between ChemBank v2.0 and PubChem Content and feature comparison between ChemBank v2.0 and PubChem By committing itself to storing raw screening data, defining screening experiments in a rigorous manner, and organizing screening experiments hierarchically using metadata, ChemBank provides a unique opportunity to the scientific community, even beyond computational scientists. ChemBank provides access to large volumes of data annotating chemical entities with measured outcomes, and the commitment to storage of raw data ensures that these measurements are available for data-mining activities. In this sense, ChemBank is an important social experiment in science, in that it permits an analysis of whether the interpretation of screening data by the investigators performing small-molecule screens indeed reveal all the value in their performance. Alternatively, cross-sectional analysis of results deposited by multiple independent investigators may reveal outcomes not apparent to participants in any individual screening project. To that end, ChemBank allows customization of options for viewing chemical-genetic profiles for the resulting molecules using any associated assay data, and as such, allows users to exploit this assembled information to support discovery and experimentation in chemical biology research. The open, standardized data-sharing environment of ChemBank is geared toward rapid discovery of novel therapeutic candidates and a deep understanding of biological systems.
</content>
</document>
