<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <id>2238977</id>
  <title>CTCFBSDB: a CTCF-binding site database for characterization of vertebrate genomic insulators
</title>
  <abstract>
 Recent studies on transcriptional control of gene expression have pinpointed the importance of long-range interactions and three-dimensional organization of chromatins within the nucleus. Distal regulatory elements such as enhancers may activate transcription over long distances; hence, their action must be restricted within appropriate boundaries to prevent illegitimate activation of non-target genes. Insulators are DNA elements with enhancer-blocking and/or chromatin-bordering functions. In vertebrates, the versatile transcription regulator CCCTC-binding factor (CTCF) is the only identified trans-acting factor that confers enhancer-blocking insulator activity. CTCF-binding sites were found to be commonly distributed along the vertebrate genomes. We have constructed a CTCF-binding site database (CTCFBSDB) to characterize experimentally identified and computationally predicted CTCF-binding sties. Biological knowledge and data from multiple resources have been integrated into the database, including sequence data, genetic polymorphisms, function annotations, histone methylation profiles, gene expression profiles and comparative genomic information. A web-based user interface was implemented for data retrieval, analysis and visualization. In silico prediction of CTCF-binding motifs is provided to facilitate the identification of candidate insulators in the query sequences submitted by users. The database can be accessed at http://insulatordb.utmem.edu/
</abstract>
  <content>
 CCCTC-binding factor (CTCF) is a versatile transcription regulator that is evolutionarily conserved from fruit fly to human (1). CTCF binds to different DNA sequences by combinatorial use of 11-zinc fingers and plays a key role in many chromatin insulation events [reviewed in (2)]. In eukaryotic genomes, chromatins are organized into distinct domains. The chromatin domain architecture is critical for transcription control. Insulators are the key DNA sequence elements that establish and maintain such domain boundaries (2&#x2013;12). They represent a class of diverged DNA sequences capable of shielding genes from inappropriate cis-regulatory signals from the genomic neighborhood. There are two types of insulators&#x2014;enhancer-blocking insulators that block enhancer&#x2013;promoter communication and barrier insulators that protect against heterochromatin-mediated silencing (13). Many recent studies have been devoted to the identification and characterization of insulators. CTCF-binding site is of particular interest because CTCF is the only protein identified so far in vertebrate that binds to enhancer-blocking insulators and shows enhancer-blocking activity. Recent studies also linked the CTCF-binding site to epigenetic processes, such as imprinting (14&#x2013;16), X-chromosome inactivation (17,18) and interchromosomal colocalization (19). Despite their obvious importance, to our knowledge, there is no public database categorizing this type of regulatory elements. In addition to dozens of well-characterized CTCF-binding sites with validated insulation functions that are scattered in the biomedical literature, several recent high-throughput ChIP-chip analyses and comparative genomic studies (20&#x2013;23) have identified tens of thousands of potential CTCF-binding sites in human and mouse genomes. Here we report our effort in creating a CTCF-binding site database, a collection of experimentally identified and computationally predicted CTCF-binding sites. Biological knowledge and data from multiple resources were integrated to annotate the CTCF-binding sites. The database is designed to facilitate the studies on insulators and their roles in regulating gene expression and demarcating functional genomic domains. Experimentally identified and computationally predicted CTCF-binding sites are processed separately. First, 34 417 experimentally identified CTCF-binding sites are collected from four sources: (i) 110 manually curated CTCF-binding sites from biomedical literature, denoted by identifiers starting with &#x2018;INSUL_MAN&#x2019;, (ii) 244 mouse CTCF-binding sites identified by Ohlsson and coworkers using ChIP-chip assay (21), denoted by identifiers starting with &#x2018;INSUL_OHL&#x2019;, (iii) 13 801 human CTCF-binding sites identified by Ren and coworkers using ChIP-chip assay (20), denoted by identifiers starting with &#x2018;INSUL_REN&#x2019; and (iv) 20 262 human CTCF-binding sites identified by Zhao and coworkers using massive direct sequencing of ChIP DNA (23), denoted by identifiers starting with &#x2018;INSUL_ZHAO&#x2019;. Second, we collected the conserved CTCF-specific sequence motifs (&#x223C;20 bp) in the human and mouse genomes that were predicted using motif scan (20,22). We excluded those (&#x223C;40%) overlapped with any of the experimentally determined CTCF-binding sites. The resulting 18 905 entries include 7736 human and 5504 mouse CTCF-binding sites predicted in (20) and 5665 human CTCF-binding sites predicted in (22). The computationally predicted CTCF-binding sites have identifiers beginning with &#x2018;INSUL_PRE&#x2019;. Description of the fields aA mandatory field. aA mandatory field. The sequences of CTCF-binding sites in the database vary from 20 bp to several hundred bp. There are two reasons for this length heterogeneity. First, different experimental methods may have different basepair resolutions for locating CTCF-binding sites. Second, different laboratories often have different research goals when they publish the original sequences. Some researchers may stop at a 500-bp region encapsulating the CTCF-binding sites while others may further narrow down to the sequences covered by the CTCF protein physically. Most CTCF-binding sites were found to share a 20-bp motif (20), which is highlighted using consecutive arrows. The direction of the arrows shows the genomic orientation of the motif. We also highlighted all the single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNP) in the dbSNP database (26) that are located in a CTCF-binding site using vertical indicators. Mutations that disrupt CTCF-binding sites may lead to abnormal gene expression and cause diseases. Indeed, a recent study showed that inherited mutations that abolish CTCF-binding sites in the human H19 differentially methylated region (DMR) can cause Beckwith&#x2013;Wiedemann syndrome (27,28). Thus, the naturally occurring mutations in CTCF-binding sites may represent new types of genetic variations that underlie phenotypes including disease status. To get more information about any of the SNPs, the user can click the SNP indicator to browse the corresponding dbSNP webpage (26). The genomic context of a few CTCF-binding sites. The CTCF-binding sites reside at the boundary between the two histone methylation domains (H3K4me3 and H3K27me3). The genomic context of a few CTCF-binding sites. The CTCF-binding sites reside at the boundary between the two histone methylation domains (H3K4me3 and H3K27me3). A CTCF-binding site (INSUL_MAN0004) webpage displays the flanking gene expression profiles and links to tracks of SNPs, genomic context and orthologous regions. A CTCF-binding site (INSUL_MAN0004) webpage displays the flanking gene expression profiles and links to tracks of SNPs, genomic context and orthologous regions. Comparative genomic studies on human, mouse and rat may provide insights into the evolution of CTCF-binding sites. To this end, we created a track of mammalian orthologous regions. For any of the three genomes, the regions containing CTCF-binding sites and flanking genes were used to query orthologous regions in the other two genomes from the UCSC precomputed block chains (31,32). Only the DNA blocks with the maximal alignment score against the query region were retained as orthologous regions. The aligned orthologous sequences in up to 16 vertebrate genomes can be displayed by clicking the &#x2018;view alignment&#x2019; button (Figure 2). CTCF uses different combinations of its zinc fingers to recognize divergent DNA sequences. Recent studies have identified core motifs for CTCFBS sequences (20,22). The motifs are represented by position weight matrices (PWM). Altogether, four closely related PWM have been derived to accommodate the sequence divergences in CTCF-binding sites (20,22). The database provides a simple web tool to search for the core CTCF-binding motifs in a query sequence. It uses the STORM program (33) to scan for each of the four PWM in the query sequences and reports the best hits. First, a web interface was developed for browsing the experimentally identified and computationally predicted CTCF-binding sites. Users can focus on entries of interest using four selection controls&#x2014;Species, Validation Method, In Situ Function and Description. The in situ function of most known CTCF-binding sites is to act as boundary element. However, in some biological contexts, CTCF-binding sites may also function as elements for transcription activation/repression [reviewed in (34)]. Second, a text search interface was developed for querying the database. Users can search for CTCF-binding sites by element name or by the PubMed identifier of the original literature. A useful approach is to retrieve the CTCF-binding sites contiguous to a gene of interest by entering an official gene symbol or words used in the gene description. Third, the database provides sequence similarity search (35) for the comparison between query sequences and CTCF-binding sequences. Finally, an option of genomic range search is provided. Users can specify a genomic interval and retrieve all the CTCF-binding sites in the interval. To maintain an up-to-date resource, we encourage researchers to submit newly identified CTCFBS sequences to the database. Data can be submitted directly through a web interface. The submissions will be manually checked before being added to the database. The database is an integrative platform for storing, retrieving and characterizing vertebrate genomic insulators. We envision that with more and more experimentally validated CTCFBS sequences available in the database, a comprehensive analysis of these sequences may facilitate the extraction of meaningful sequence signals, uncover the functional basis of insulators, and ultimately enable the mapping of every distinct transcription domain along the genomes.
</content>
</document>
