<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <id>2238986</id>
  <title>ProtozoaDB: dynamic visualization and exploration of protozoan genomes
</title>
  <abstract>
 ProtozoaDB (http://www.biowebdb.org/protozoadb) is being developed to initially host both genomics and post-genomics data from Plasmodium falciparum, Entamoeba histolytica, Trypanosoma brucei, T. cruzi and Leishmania major, but will hopefully host other protozoan species as more genomes are sequenced. It is based on the Genomics Unified Schema and offers a modern Web-based interface for user-friendly data visualization and exploration. This database is not intended to duplicate other similar efforts such as GeneDB, PlasmoDB, TcruziDB or even TDRtargets, but to be complementary by providing further analyses with emphasis on distant similarities (HMM-based) and phylogeny-based annotations including orthology analysis. ProtozoaDB will be progressively linked to the above-mentioned databases, focusing in performing a multi-source dynamic combination of information through advanced interoperable Web tools such as Web services. Also, to provide Web services will allow third-party software to retrieve and use data from ProtozoaDB in automated pipelines (workflows) or other interoperable Web technologies, promoting better information reuse and integration. We also expect ProtozoaDB to catalyze the development of local and regional bioinformatics capabilities (research and training), and therefore promote/enhance scientific advancement in developing countries.
</abstract>
  <content>
 Among the most important protozoan parasitic species causing diseases in humans, five had their genomes recently sequenced. Three of them are pathogenic members of the Order Kinetoplastida, Family Trypanosomatidae, that cause Sleeping sickness (caused by pathogenic subspecies of Trypanosoma brucei), Chagas disease (T. cruzi) or leishmaniasis (Leishmania major) representing the major human diseases caused by kinetoplastids (1&#x2013;3). The fourth pathogenic species in question is Plasmodium falciparum, a member of the Phylum Apicomplexa and the causative agent of the most important human malaria (4). The last is Entamoeba histolytica, member of the Subphylum Sarcodina, the causative agent of amebiasis that infects approximately 50 million people over the globe, mainly on neotropical developing countries (5). The availability of pathogenic protozoan genome sequences allows for comparative analyses to be performed in a systematic and straightforward way, towards a better understanding of biological, genetic and evolutionary aspects. Also, such analyses allow the identification of genes related to pathogenesis and/or species-specific genes, useful for diagnostic markers as well as genes involved in crucial metabolic pathways that may lead to drug or vaccine development. Identification of homolog genes, particularly orthologs, became an important task to transfer annotation from experimentally or better characterized genes, allowing annotation and re-annotation of genes and genomes. Considering the existing genomic data from important human protozoan parasites as well as ongoing sequencing efforts of several other relevant pathogenic species such as P. vivax, Toxoplasma gondii, Cryptosporidium parvum, T. rangeli, L. braziliensis and L. chagasi [GOLD (6)], ProtozoaDB is being developed to initially host genomics and post-genomics data from P. falciparum, E. histolytica, T. brucei, T. cruzi and L. major (5-protozoa), with added-value obtained from similarity- and phylogeny-based analyses performed as part of the system pipeline, but considering the adding/linking of more pathogenic species database in a near future. Number of nucleotide sequences from each parasitic protozoan species retrieved from the GenBank, Refseq and EST databasesa aDatabase search executed in July 2007. aDatabase search executed in July 2007. Redundancy of sequence proteins was treated in the following way: (i) the cd-hit (7) software was ran on all proteins of each five species, providing information on proteins with 100% identity, and (ii) redundancy mapped to already existing GUS tables, then users will be able to query and retrieve non-redundant datasets. External database IDs (from TcruziDB and PlasmoDB) mappings were incorporated into GUS, so that users can query and retrieve ProtozoaDB data using GenBank, TcruziDB or PlasmoDB IDs. Visitors can also click on any of the mapped external database IDs to be re-directed to PlasmoDB, TcruziDB, GeneDB or Superfamily databases, then look on extra annotations. Orthologous groups of the 5-protozoa are being identified using the OrthoMCL package (8). Similarity analyses were performed using all the proteins coded by the GenBank and RefSeq entries listed in Table 1, consisting of BlastP against the UniRef90 database (release 11) of the UniProt consortium (http://www.pir.uniprot.org/database/nref.shtml). Further similarity analyses using the Conserved Domain Database (9) and InterPro (10) are being progressively added to the database. Features of the Search Sequences tool in ProtozoaDB. (A) searching E. histolytica subset, (B) choosing U20322 entry, (C) details of U20322 entry that can be tracked with RSS, Google or Netvibes and (D) CDS of U20322 entry and associated abstracts published in PubMed. Features of the Search Sequences tool in ProtozoaDB. (A) searching E. histolytica subset, (B) choosing U20322 entry, (C) details of U20322 entry that can be tracked with RSS, Google or Netvibes and (D) CDS of U20322 entry and associated abstracts published in PubMed. ProtozoaDB also contains a collection of ESTs from different life cycle stages of the distinct species, allowing the user to perform queries on genes related to metacyclogenesis and/or to compare genes expressed in different parasite species or stages. Due to their particular biological and medical importance, a collection of ESTs from epimastigote, promastigote and amastigote forms of T. cruzi and L. major is available. Moreover, ESTs from gametocytes, schizont and asexual stages of P. falciparum are also available for comparison. An extensive documentation is being incorporated progressively, then users can benefit from the HowTo (user manual), FAQ (Frequently Asked Questions), GUS-Postgres-Wiki (details on the installation, configuration and debugging of GUS for Postgres) and ProtozoaDB roadmap (features to be added) in the left-side menu of the main page. Features of the ProtozoaDB Phylo search tool. (A) searching Mobile Genetics Elements (MGE) phylogenetic trees, (B) MGE genes trees, (C) Ribonuclease H available data, (D) trypanosomatid taxons and (E) phylogenetic tree of Ribonuclease H. Features of the ProtozoaDB Phylo search tool. (A) searching Mobile Genetics Elements (MGE) phylogenetic trees, (B) MGE genes trees, (C) Ribonuclease H available data, (D) trypanosomatid taxons and (E) phylogenetic tree of Ribonuclease H. ProtozoaDB system is publicly available at http://www.biowebdb.org/protozoadb and offers modern Web interfaces, based on concepts inspired by what has been called the Web2.0 (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Web_2) and REST-based Web services (http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Representational_State_Transfer). Those design principles can enhance e-scientists experiment perception, by improving the Web applications&#x2019; look-and-feel, facilitating collaboration and sharing of resources, and, most of all, facilitating services interoperability. ProtozoaDB offers more flexibility than traditional (Perl) scripts while being more flexible and efficient than Web services technology. Yet, it remains compatible with Web services protocols as well as with scripts, turning the system extremely customizable. ProtozoaDB system heavily relies on Web technology. We currently use the developed REST-based Web services as content providers for quick dynamic responses to user actions through the system interface, as well as to enable content and functionality sharing between ProtozoaDB and third-party websites. In general, ProtozoaDB interoperates in three distinct categories: (i) Use of third-party Web services for dynamic integration of information: an example of the use of lightweight services is provided through a ProtozoaDB user interface, where we merge information obtained from ProtozoaDB and NCBI's Entrez Programming Utilities (e-Utils: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/entrez/query/static/eutils_help.html). In this specific example, we search Pubmed dynamically, providing links to literature whenever an article cites sequences stored in ProtozoaDB; (ii) Provision of Web services for third-party reuse: a collection of services are offered to facilitate data retrieval in ProtozoaDB, intended to be used by automated third-party pipelines (workflows) or external user interfaces interested in interoperating with ProtozoaDB; (ii) Tools for direct community involvement: ProtozoaDB interface encourages users involvement by offering them the option of entering their amendments or full annotations to any sequence in the form of &#x2018;tags&#x2019;&#x2014;a concept successfully used in content-sharing websites such as Flickr (http://flickr.com/tour/) and Delicious (http://del.icio.us/), and more recently, NCBI Entrez with the introduction of GeneRIFs (Gene Reference Into Function: http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/projects/GeneRIF/). Additionally, an RSS feed option is available for user subscription, allowing him/her to receive notification of any updates on a given sequence of interest. RSS feeds are widely supported by current Web technology, such as e-mail clients (e.g. Mozilla Thunderbird), browsers (e.g. Mozilla Firefox), iGoogle (Google Customized Homepage) and Netvibes (http://www.netvibes.com). General overview of the ProtozoaDB Architecture. General overview of the ProtozoaDB Architecture. In addition to Web services access, the ProtozoaDB database is available through a user interface, where a series of pre-defined database queries is offered to the users in order to ease the analysis task. Finally, the eUtils (Entrez Programming Utilities) module, provided by NCBI, which does not currently integrate the ProtozoaDB architecture, was included in Figure 3 to illustrate the system ability to provide services composition with third-party database sites. Our plans include: (i) design and incorporation of another new subschema into GUS 3.5 for protein structure experiments, including &#x2018;druggability&#x2019; inferences; (ii) link/interactions with TcruziDB (12), ApiDB (13), GeneDB (http://www.genedb.org) and TDRtargets (http://www.tdrtargets.org) databases; (iii) inclusion of sequences from more protozoan species whose genome/transcriptome/proteome data generation are currently under way; (iv) the addition of post-genomics data from microarrays, proteomics and 3D structures experiments; (v) at least a yearly release cycle for ProtozoaDB and (vi) the inclusion of a non-restrictive Creative Commons license. In step with the emergence of the Semantic Web, an envisioned third generation of the Web, our database was partially mapped to a set of ontologies. Providing accessibility to our repository through Semantic Web-based technologies, we offer Web access to formal relationships that can be explored both by humans and machines, towards a Relationship Web (14).
</content>
</document>
