<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <id>2241854</id>
  <title>The dual control of TFIIB recruitment by NC2 is gene specific
</title>
  <abstract>
 Negative co-factor 2 (NC2) is a conserved eukaryotic complex composed of two subunits, NC2&#x3B1; (Drap1) and NC2&#x3B2; (Dr1) that associate through a histone-fold motif. In this work, we generated mutants of NC2, characterized target genes for these mutants and studied the assembly of NC2 and general transcription factors on target promoters. We determined that the two NC2 subunits mostly function together to be recruited to DNA and regulate gene expression. We found that NC2 strongly controls promoter association of TFIIB, both negatively and positively. We could attribute the gene-specific repressor effect of NC2 on TFIIB to the C-terminal domain of NC2&#x3B2;, and define that it requires ORF sequences of the target gene. In contrast, the positive function of NC2 on TFIIB targets is more general and requires adequate levels of the NC2 histone-fold heterodimer on promoters. Finally, we determined that NC2 becomes limiting for TATA-binding protein (TBP) association with a heat inducible promoter under heat stress. This study demonstrates an important positive role of NC2 for formation of the pre-initiation complex on promoters, under normal conditions through control of TFIIB, or upon activation by stress via control of TBP.
</abstract>
  <content>
 Transcription by RNA polymerase II is critically dependent upon general transcription factors (GTFs) that allow the specific association of the polymerase with promoter regions. Amongst these, the TATA-binding protein (TBP) binds to promoters and plays a critical role in the nucleation of the pre-initiation complex (PIC) (1). It allows the recruitment of both TFIIA and TFIIB, followed by the other GTFs. Several factors that control transcription initiation, interact with TBP and either modify the association of TBP with DNA, or prevent the association of subsequent GTFs. One such factor is negative cofactor 2 (NC2), bearing two subunits (NC2&#x3B1; or Drap1 and NC2&#x3B2; or Dr1), which forms a stable complex with TBP on promoters (2). Biochemical and genetic data have suggested that the association of NC2 with DNA-bound TBP competes with the association of TFIIA and TFIIB, and thus inhibits transcription initiation (3&#x2013;8). NC2 is conserved in eukaryotes, and a crystal structure of a human NC2&#x2013;TBP&#x2013;DNA complex has been resolved (8). NC2 dimerizes through histone-fold domains (HFD) of the H2A/H2B type, and the NC2 histone-fold is localized underneath the DNA surface to which TBP binds. Originally it was suggested that the carboxy terminal extension of NC2&#x3B2; might sterically hinder the association of TFIIB with TBP, whilst regions of NC2&#x3B1; missing in the structure, C-terminal to the HFD, might be responsible for sterically affecting the association of TFIIA with TBP. In contrast to the mutually exclusive binding to TBP proposed for both TFIIA and NC2, a more recent superposition of structures has suggested that TFIIA and NC2 could be bound to TBP simultaneously, albeit with lower affinity than for either molecule alone (9). In addition to this simple and quite well-defined model for transcriptional repression by NC2, many studies have revealed that NC2 function is complex. Indeed, NC2 has been demonstrated not only to repress, but also to activate transcription, in vitro and in vivo (6,10&#x2013;13). The mechanism by which NC2 promotes transcription has not been studied much, and remains unclear. The C-terminal domain of Drosophila NC2&#x3B2;, essential for repression by NC2, is not required for activation by NC2 (11). This observation would suggest the existence of different functional domains within NC2. A different study has suggested that different functional forms of NC2 might exist. Indeed, purification of NC2&#x3B1; and NC2&#x3B2; subunits from Saccharomyces cerevisiae revealed that the two NC2 subunits could not be co-purified from yeast cells growing exponentially, whilst they could be co-purified after glucose depletion (14). Furthermore, relative cross-linking of the NC2 subunits to a same promoter was different before and after glucose depletion suggesting that different forms of NC2 complexes might be able to associate with promoter DNA. What these different forms are remains unknown. In human, evidence has been provided to suggest that NC2&#x3B1; and NC2&#x3B2; can associate with different proteins, since it was demonstrated that BTAF1, the human homolog of yeast Mot1p, interacts with NC2&#x3B1; but not NC2&#x3B2; or the NC2 heterodimer (15). With regard to the mechanism by which NC2 might associate with DNA, it has been documented that NC2 associates with DNA-bound TBP, and this has been studied in vitro using TATA-containing DNA, but efficient binding of NC2&#x2013;TBP to DNA that lacks a canonical TATA box has also recently been demonstrated (16). This observation may be related to former experiments showing that in yeast, NC2 was required for transcription from the TATA-less promoter of HIS3 but repressed transcription from the HIS3 TATA promoter (13). Finally, while the activity of NC2 has generally been thought to be related to TBP function, it was recently demonstrated in vitro that recombinant human NC2, like other histone-fold complexes, could facilitate nucleosome assembly by ACF, independently of a direct interaction with ACF (17). Furthermore, Drosophila NC2&#x3B2; has been described as a partner of the HFD protein TAF11 in two hybrid experiments (18). In this work, using mutants of NC2, we have been able to define NC2 target genes, and determine how NC2 controls the assembly of the PIC on target genes in vivo. We demonstrate that in cells growing exponentially, NC2 regulates the association of TFIIB to promoters in different ways depending upon the gene. Furthermore, our study defines a role for NC2 in the stable recruitment of TBP to heat inducible genes upon heat stress. Taken together, our results reveal an important role for the NC2 heterodimer in the efficient assembly of GTFs to promoters. Strain list Strain list Wild-type (wt) and mutant cells were grown exponentially at 30&#xB0;C in YPD (2% glucose) during 24 h until an OD600 of &#x223C;0.8. Cells were harvested and total RNA extracted by the acid phenol method. The quality of total cellular RNA was tested on a RNA 6000 Nano Chip (Agilent). Total cellular RNA was next purified with RNeasy Mini Handbook kit (QIAGEN). Then, the synthesis of cDNA, cRNA, the hybridization and the scan of the chip were performed according to the technical manual of Affimetrix (GeneChip Expression Analysis). Briefly, oligo dT was added to 15 &#x3BC;g of purified total RNA. After 10 min. of incubation at 70&#xB0;C in first strand buffer with DTT (10 mM), dNTP (500 &#x3BC;M each) and reverse transcriptase (SuperScript II from Invitrogen at 200 U/&#x3BC;l) were added for the first strand cDNA synthesis (1 h at 42&#xB0;C). For the second strand synthesis, dNTP (200 &#x3BC;M each), Escherichia coli DNA ligase (10 U), E. coli DNA polymerase I (40 U) and E. coli RNaseH (2 U) were added to the second strand buffer and incubated for 2 h at 16&#xB0;C. Finally, T4 DNA polymerase (10 U) was added to the reaction. The cDNA was purified and after ethanol precipitation, 15 &#x3BC;g of purified cDNA were incubated during 5 h at 37&#xB0;C with HY buffer (Enzo), biotine-coupled ribonucleotides, DTT, an RNase inhibitor mix and T7 RNA polymerase. The cRNA was then purified in the same way as total RNA and 20 &#x3BC;g of cRNA were fragmented in 5&#xD7; hybridization buffer (200 mM Tris&#x2013;acetate pH 8.1, 500 mM KOAc, 150 mM MgOAc) and incubated during 35 min at 95&#xB0;C. Fifteen micrograms of cRNA were hybridized to the Yeast Genome S98 chip, during 16 h at 45&#xB0;C with 1&#xD7; hybridization buffer (100 mM MES; 1 M [Na+]; 20 mM EDTA; 0.01 Tween-20), oligonucleotide B2 (50 pM), eukaryotic hybridization controls (20&#xD7;), herring sperm DNA (0.1 mg/ml) and acetylated BSA (0.5 mg/ml). The chip was washed in the Fluidics station, first with buffer A (6&#xD7; SSPE, 0.01% Tween-20) then with buffer B (100 mM MES, 0.1 M [Na+], 0.01% Tween-20). Antibodies were added next (Normal Goat IgG 0.1 mg/ml; biotinylated antibodies 0.5 mg/ml; acetylated BSA 2 mg/ml; 100 mM MES; 1 M [Na+]; 0.05% Tween-20) followed by the SAPE solution (Streptavidine&#x2013;Phycoerythrine 10 &#x3BC;g/ml; acetylated BSA 2 mg/ml; 100 mM MES; 1 M [Na+]; 0.05% Tween-20). Finally, the chip was scanned and the scan was analyzed by Affymetrix software (MicroArraySuite, MicroDB, and DataMiningTool) and Iobion software (Array Assist). The stringent analysis consisted of using (p0.05 DE1.0) to obtain significant target genes for each mutant compared to the wt by all three proposed methods of analysis (RMA, GCRMA and CHP). Only genes defined as genes significantly de-regulated in the mutant relative to the wt by all three analyses were considered. For comparison, a less-stringent analysis consisted of using the Affymetrix software, and looking for genes de-regulated in 100% of the comparisons (each mutant duplicate compared to each wt duplicate), without introducing an additional minimal fold increase or decrease. Once target genes for each mutant were defined by the Array Assist software, for each target gene we determined whether in each duplicate for each mutant it was expressed at higher levels than for either duplicate of the wt (Supplementary Table 1). ChIP experiments were performed as described in (14). Briefly, wt and mutant cells were grown exponentially at 30&#xB0;C in YPD (2% glucose) during 24 h until an OD600 of &#x223C;0.8. The cells were fixed with 1% formaldehyde during 20 min. at RT, and glycine was added to a final concentration of 125 mM to stop the reaction. The cells were washed twice (20 mM Tris&#x2013;HCl pH 7.5; 200 mM NaCl) and broken in lysis buffer (50 mM HEPES&#x2013;KOH pH 7.5; 140 mM NaCl; 1 mM EDTA pH 8; 1% Triton; 0.1% sodium deoxycholate; 1 mM PMSF) during 30 min and sonicated. The size of fragmented chromatin was verified on a gel to be between 200 and 400 bp, then a fraction of the extracts (input) was incubated over night at 4&#xB0;C with specific antibodies and protein G-Sepharose. The Sepharose beads were collected and washed with TSE 150 (20 mM Tris&#x2013;HCl pH 8; 2 mM EDTA pH 8; 1% Triton; 0.1% sodium deoxycholate; 150 mM NaCl), followed by TSE 500 (20 mM Tris&#x2013;HCl pH 8; 2 mM EDTA pH 8; 1% Triton; 0.1% sodium deoxycholate; 300 mM NaCl), then Buffer III (10 mM Tris&#x2013;HCl pH 8; 1 mM EDTA pH 8; 250 mM LiCl; 1% Igepal, 0.1% sodium deoxycholate) and finally 2 &#xD7; TE. Immunoprecipitated chromatin was eluted in 1% SDS; 50 mM Tris&#x2013;HCl pH 7.5; 10 mM EDTA pH 8. Then 10 mg/ml of proteinase K was added to the precipitates and to a fraction of the input during 5 h at 65&#xB0;C to reverse cross-links. DNA was extracted and precipitated. Specific promoter DNA in the input and precipitates was measured by real-time PCR using SYBR Green (Eurogentec). The sequences of specific oligonucleotides are available upon request. 9E10 monoclonal anti-MYC antibodies were purchased from Covance, and mouse monoclonal anti-Rpb3p and anti-Rpb4p antibodies from Neoclone. The ChIP experiments were performed three times and the results are the fold (increase or decrease) change of the mutant versus the average wt value. Cultures were grown exponentially to an OD600 of 0.8. The equivalent of 50 OD600 of cells were harvested by centrifugation for 1 min at 13 000 r.p.m. After washing in water, cell pellets were frozen at &#x2212;80&#xB0;C, thawed and resuspended in 600 &#x3BC;l of buffer B (40 mM HEPES&#x2013;KOH pH 7.5, 150 mM KOAc, 100 mM KCl, 20% glycerol, 1&#xD7; protease inhibitor cocktail and 1 mM PMSF). Cells were broken by the addition of 300 &#x3BC;l of glass beads and vortexing vigorously for 15 min. Whole-cell extracts (WCE) were clarified by centrifugation for 15 min. at 13 000 r.p.m. and at 4&#xB0;C. The protein concentration was determined by the Bradford assay. For co-immunoprecipitation experiments, 1 &#x3BC;l of anti-NC2&#x3B1; antibody was mixed with 1 mg of cell extract and 20 &#x3BC;l of protein G-Sepharose beads over night at 4&#xB0;C in a total volume of 250 &#x3BC;l. The beads were washed three times with 40 mM HEPES&#x2013;KOH pH 7.5, 150 mM KOAc, 100 mM KCl, 20% glycerol before elution with boiling in loading buffer. Total cellular RNA extraction and S1 analyses were performed as described previously (14). The sequences of the oligonucleotides used are available upon request. Analysis of bur6-5 and ncb2-2 growth and definition of target genes by microarray experiments. (A) The indicated strains were streaked on glucose-rich medium and placed at the indicated temperatures for 3&#x2013;7 days. (B) Venn diagrams indicating the number of genes that were defined as induced or repressed in bur6-5 or ncb2-2 using the Array Assist software. The overlap between the two mutants was defined by determining for each of the target genes of one mutant whether each duplicate of the other mutant was different from each duplicate of the wild-type, with an average of 2-fold difference (data provided in Supplementary Table 1). Analysis of bur6-5 and ncb2-2 growth and definition of target genes by microarray experiments. (A) The indicated strains were streaked on glucose-rich medium and placed at the indicated temperatures for 3&#x2013;7 days. (B) Venn diagrams indicating the number of genes that were defined as induced or repressed in bur6-5 or ncb2-2 using the Array Assist software. The overlap between the two mutants was defined by determining for each of the target genes of one mutant whether each duplicate of the other mutant was different from each duplicate of the wild-type, with an average of 2-fold difference (data provided in Supplementary Table 1). mRNA analysis to confirm the target genes found by the microarrays. Cells were grown up to an O.D.600 of 0.8, and 50 &#x3BC;g of total cellular RNA was analyzed by S1 digestion for the levels of the indicated transcripts: (A) BUR6, (B) HSP12, (C) HSP26 (D) MUC1, (E) DAN1, (F) RPS14b (G) ADH1 and (H) PHO4. DED1 were measured in each reaction as an internal control, since the microarray experiments indicated that it was not affected by the bur6-5 or ncb2-2 mutations. mRNA analysis to confirm the target genes found by the microarrays. Cells were grown up to an O.D.600 of 0.8, and 50 &#x3BC;g of total cellular RNA was analyzed by S1 digestion for the levels of the indicated transcripts: (A) BUR6, (B) HSP12, (C) HSP26 (D) MUC1, (E) DAN1, (F) RPS14b (G) ADH1 and (H) PHO4. DED1 were measured in each reaction as an internal control, since the microarray experiments indicated that it was not affected by the bur6-5 or ncb2-2 mutations. Association of NC2 subunits with DNA in the bur6-5 and ncb2-2 mutants. (A) Wild-type or mutant cells as indicated were grown in high glucose for 24 h, cross-linked and cell extracts were incubated with antibodies against NC2&#x3B1; or NC2&#x3B2;. After immunoprecipitation and purification of nucleic acids in the immunoprecipitates, the amount of the indicated promoters (HSP12, BUR6 or RPS14b) in the precipitates was evaluated by real-time PCR, and referred to the input extract. The experiments were performed three times independently and the results are presented as the fold-change in the mutant over the average wild-type. (B) Exponentially growing cells from the strains indicated above the panels were lyzed for total protein extract (TE) preparation. The extracts were incubated with antibodies against NC2&#x3B1; (IP NC2&#x3B1;) or N2&#x3B2; (IP NC2&#x3B2;) followed by protein G Sepharose, and the total extract or immunoprecipitates were analyzed by western blot with polyclonal NC2&#x3B1; (upper panel) or NC2&#x3B2; (lower panel) antibodies as indicated. All samples tested with one antibody were run on the same gel and exposed together for the same length of time. The position of the proteins encoded by bur6-5 and ncb2-2, as well as the proteins encoded by the wild-type genes are indicated on the right of the panels, and on the left, asterisk indicates a band cross-reacting with NC2&#x3B1; antibodies and which co-migrates with one form of NC2&#x3B1;. Association of NC2 subunits with DNA in the bur6-5 and ncb2-2 mutants. (A) Wild-type or mutant cells as indicated were grown in high glucose for 24 h, cross-linked and cell extracts were incubated with antibodies against NC2&#x3B1; or NC2&#x3B2;. After immunoprecipitation and purification of nucleic acids in the immunoprecipitates, the amount of the indicated promoters (HSP12, BUR6 or RPS14b) in the precipitates was evaluated by real-time PCR, and referred to the input extract. The experiments were performed three times independently and the results are presented as the fold-change in the mutant over the average wild-type. (B) Exponentially growing cells from the strains indicated above the panels were lyzed for total protein extract (TE) preparation. The extracts were incubated with antibodies against NC2&#x3B1; (IP NC2&#x3B1;) or N2&#x3B2; (IP NC2&#x3B2;) followed by protein G Sepharose, and the total extract or immunoprecipitates were analyzed by western blot with polyclonal NC2&#x3B1; (upper panel) or NC2&#x3B2; (lower panel) antibodies as indicated. All samples tested with one antibody were run on the same gel and exposed together for the same length of time. The position of the proteins encoded by bur6-5 and ncb2-2, as well as the proteins encoded by the wild-type genes are indicated on the right of the panels, and on the left, asterisk indicates a band cross-reacting with NC2&#x3B1; antibodies and which co-migrates with one form of NC2&#x3B1;. Since differences in cross-linking of both NC2 subunits to DNA in both mutant strains were observed, we next analyzed the expression and interaction of the NC2 subunits in wt cells and in cells expressing the mutant forms of the NC2 subunits (Figure 3B). In bur6-5, wt levels of NC2&#x3B1; could be immunoprecipitated with NC2&#x3B1; antibodies (lane 5, upper panel), despite lower levels of the protein in the total extract of mutant cells compared to wt cells (compare lanes 1 and 2, upper panel), but no detectable NC2&#x3B2; was co-immunoprecipitated (lane 5, lower panel), although NC2&#x3B2; was expressed at wt levels in this strain (compare lanes 1 and 2, lower panel). Furthermore, high levels of NC2&#x3B2; could be immunoprecipitated with NC2&#x3B2; antibodies in this strain (lane 8, lower panel), but only very low levels of NC2&#x3B1; co-immunoprecipitated (lane 8, upper panel). In ncb2-2, NC2&#x3B2; is expressed at only very low levels (lane 3, lower panel), and thus whether NC2&#x3B1; or NC2&#x3B2; is immunoprecipitated (lane 6, upper panel; or lane 9, lower panel), only very low levels of the other subunit is detectable in the immunoprecipitate (lane 9, upper panel and lane 6, lower panel). These results demonstrate that in both mutant strains, there are only low levels of the NC2 heterodimer, which correlates nicely with reduced cross-linking of both subunits to DNA in both strains, in contrast to wt expression of NC2&#x3B2; in bur6-5 and NC2&#x3B1; in ncb2-2. Analysis of PIC recruitment in wt, bur6-5 and ncb2-2 cells by ChIP. (A) Wild-type or mutant cells as indicated were grown in high glucose for 24 h, cross-linked and cell extracts were incubated with antibodies against TBP. After immunoprecipitation, and purification of nucleic acids in the immunoprecipitates, the amount of the indicated promoters (HSP12, BUR6 or RPS14b) in the precipitates was evaluated by real-time PCR and referred to the input extract. The experiments were performed three times independently and the results are expressed as in Figure 3A. (B) The same procedure was used to follow TFIIA recruitment with polyclonal antibodies, against Toa1p or with monoclonal antibodies against MYC to follow (C) TFIIB using wild-type or mutant strains expressing MYC-tagged Sua7p, (D) TFIIE using wild-type or mutant strains expressing MYC-tagged Tfa1p, (E) or TFIIH using wild-type or mutant strains expressing MYC-tagged Tfb3p and finally (F) monoclonal antibodies directed against the CTD to follow RNA polymerase II. Analysis of PIC recruitment in wt, bur6-5 and ncb2-2 cells by ChIP. (A) Wild-type or mutant cells as indicated were grown in high glucose for 24 h, cross-linked and cell extracts were incubated with antibodies against TBP. After immunoprecipitation, and purification of nucleic acids in the immunoprecipitates, the amount of the indicated promoters (HSP12, BUR6 or RPS14b) in the precipitates was evaluated by real-time PCR and referred to the input extract. The experiments were performed three times independently and the results are expressed as in Figure 3A. (B) The same procedure was used to follow TFIIA recruitment with polyclonal antibodies, against Toa1p or with monoclonal antibodies against MYC to follow (C) TFIIB using wild-type or mutant strains expressing MYC-tagged Sua7p, (D) TFIIE using wild-type or mutant strains expressing MYC-tagged Tfa1p, (E) or TFIIH using wild-type or mutant strains expressing MYC-tagged Tfb3p and finally (F) monoclonal antibodies directed against the CTD to follow RNA polymerase II. In vitro, the NC2 complex has been shown to block the association of the basal transcription factors TFIIA and TFIIB from associating with DNA-bound TBP, resulting in non-productive TBP&#x2013;TATA complexes (3). Thus, we next investigated TFIIA recruitment to NC2 target genes in the wt and mutant cells. For this, we used antibodies directed against the large subunit of TFIIA called Toa1p. We found no significant change in Toa1p recruitment in either mutant compared to the wt, suggesting that NC2 does not strongly inhibit the recruitment of TFIIA in vivo, as previously described in vitro (Figure 4B). To next follow TFIIB presence on promoters, we created strains expressing a MYC-tagged form of TFIIB (Table 1). We observed a very strong increase in TFIIB recruitment to HSP12 in the ncb2-2 mutant (about a 7- to 8-fold increase compared to the wt) that correlated well with upregulation of the HSP12 mRNA in this mutant, but no change in TFIIB association with the HSP12 promoter was detected in bur6-5. For the BUR6 promoter, no significant variations in TFIIB association in the three strains were observed despite the increased levels of BUR6 mRNA in both mutants. On the RPS14b promoter in contrast, a significant decrease of TFIIB association was observed in both mutants (Figure 4C), demonstrating a correlation, for this gene, between the loss of NC2, the loss of TFIIB on the promoter and the decrease of RPS14b mRNA, in the mutants. Next, we investigated the presence of TFIIE and TFIIH by creating strains expressing MYC-tagged versions of the Tfa1p and Tfb3p subunits of TFIIE and TFIIH, respectively (Table 1). No significant change in the presence of either factor was measured between NC2 mutants and the wt, on either HSP12 or BUR6, but a drastic decrease of both factors on RPS14b was observed in the mutants compared to the wt (Figure 4D and E). Finally, to determine how the described changes in association of GTFs might affect transcription, we investigated the presence of RNA polymerase II (Pol II) on the three genes by using antibodies against its carboxy terminal heptad repeat (CTD). There was no significant change in the presence of Pol II on either HSP12 or BUR6 in the mutants compared to the wt, but in contrast a clear reduction of Pol II on RPS14b in both mutants was observed (Figure 4F). Changes in Pol II and TFIIB recruitment in the ncb2-2 mutant are gene-specific. (A) ChIP experiments were performed to follow TFIIB using wild-type or ncb2-2 cells expressing MYC-tagged Sua7p. The promoters MUC1, DAN1, HSP26 RPS8A and ADH1, were tested and the experiments were performed three times independently and the results expressed as in Figure 4. (B) ChIP experiments were performed to follow Pol II using antibodies directed against the Rpb3p or Rpb4p subunits. The HSP12, MUC1, HSP26, DAN1 and RPS14b promoters were tested and referred to the input. The results of one experiment are presented. (C) ChIP experiments were performed to follow TFIIB recruitment on the HSP12 or RPS14b promoters when the ORFs of these genes had been replaced by the TRP1 ORF at the endogenous loci of HSP12 and RPS14b. The experiments were performed three times independently and the results expressed as in Figure 4. Changes in Pol II and TFIIB recruitment in the ncb2-2 mutant are gene-specific. (A) ChIP experiments were performed to follow TFIIB using wild-type or ncb2-2 cells expressing MYC-tagged Sua7p. The promoters MUC1, DAN1, HSP26 RPS8A and ADH1, were tested and the experiments were performed three times independently and the results expressed as in Figure 4. (B) ChIP experiments were performed to follow Pol II using antibodies directed against the Rpb3p or Rpb4p subunits. The HSP12, MUC1, HSP26, DAN1 and RPS14b promoters were tested and referred to the input. The results of one experiment are presented. (C) ChIP experiments were performed to follow TFIIB recruitment on the HSP12 or RPS14b promoters when the ORFs of these genes had been replaced by the TRP1 ORF at the endogenous loci of HSP12 and RPS14b. The experiments were performed three times independently and the results expressed as in Figure 4. We next re-examined the recruitment of Pol II, by investigating several NC2 target genes and using antibodies directed against the Rpb3p and Rpb4p subunits of the polymerase. Increases of both Pol II subunits were measured on HSP12 and to a lesser extent on MUC1 (Figure 5B), whereas in contrast decreases were measured on HSP26, DAN1 and dramatically on RPS14b, in the mutant (Figure 5B). Thus, changes in Pol II association with promoters correlate quite well with changes in TFIIB recruitment in ncb2-2, but only partially with changes in gene expression. Indeed, for some genes such as DAN1 and HSP26, changes in association of TFIIB and Pol II are surprisingly opposite to changes in expression. Finally, to determine the elements driving the differential effects observed on TFIIB recruitment in NC2 mutants depending upon the gene, we generated strains in which the HSP12 or RPS14B ORFs were substituted with an unrelated ORF (see Materials and Methods section). Interestingly, we found that recruitment of TFIIB to the promoter of HSP12 was similar in wt and ncb2-2 mutant cells under these conditions (Figure 5C). Thus, the HSP12 ORF is required to observe NC2 regulation of TFIIB association with its promoter. In contrast, regulation of the presence of TFIIB on the RPS14b promoter by NC2 was observed independently upon the ORF immediately downstream (Figure 5C). NC2 is massively recruited to the HSP12 promoter upon heat shock. (A) Wild-type cells were grown to exponential phase, and then shifted to 38.5&#xB0;C for the indicated times. Total cellular RNA was extracted and analyzed by S1 digestion for the levels of HSP12, BUR6 and DED1 as indicated. (B) The same cells were cross-linked with formaldehyde prior to total extract preparation for TBP, NC2&#x3B1; and NC2&#x3B2; immunoprecipitation. The presence of the HSP12 promoter in the immunoprecipitates was evaluated by real-time PCR and expressed relative to input DNA. The results of three independent experiments are presented. NC2 is massively recruited to the HSP12 promoter upon heat shock. (A) Wild-type cells were grown to exponential phase, and then shifted to 38.5&#xB0;C for the indicated times. Total cellular RNA was extracted and analyzed by S1 digestion for the levels of HSP12, BUR6 and DED1 as indicated. (B) The same cells were cross-linked with formaldehyde prior to total extract preparation for TBP, NC2&#x3B1; and NC2&#x3B2; immunoprecipitation. The presence of the HSP12 promoter in the immunoprecipitates was evaluated by real-time PCR and expressed relative to input DNA. The results of three independent experiments are presented. Mutation of either NC2 subunit leads to non-optimal HSP12 induction upon heat shock. (A) Wild-type and mutant cells were grown to exponential phase, and then shifted or not to 38.5&#xB0;C as indicated for 10 min. Total cellular RNA was extracted and analyzed for the levels of HSP12 and DED1 as indicated. Quantification of the blot reveals an induction of more than 850-fold of HSP12 relative to DED1 upon heat shock for the wild-type, more than 300-fold for bur6-5 and 10-fold for ncb2-2. (B) Wild-type or mutant cells as indicated were grown to exponential phase, and then shifted or not to 38.5&#xB0;C as indicated for 10 min, cross-linked and ChIP were performed with antibodies against histone H3. (C) Wild-type or mutant cells as indicated were grown to exponential phase, and then shifted or not to 38.5&#xB0;C as indicated for 10 min, cross-linked and ChIP experiments were performed to follow TBP and the CTD with the same antibodies used in the experiments presented in Figure 4. Mutation of either NC2 subunit leads to non-optimal HSP12 induction upon heat shock. (A) Wild-type and mutant cells were grown to exponential phase, and then shifted or not to 38.5&#xB0;C as indicated for 10 min. Total cellular RNA was extracted and analyzed for the levels of HSP12 and DED1 as indicated. Quantification of the blot reveals an induction of more than 850-fold of HSP12 relative to DED1 upon heat shock for the wild-type, more than 300-fold for bur6-5 and 10-fold for ncb2-2. (B) Wild-type or mutant cells as indicated were grown to exponential phase, and then shifted or not to 38.5&#xB0;C as indicated for 10 min, cross-linked and ChIP were performed with antibodies against histone H3. (C) Wild-type or mutant cells as indicated were grown to exponential phase, and then shifted or not to 38.5&#xB0;C as indicated for 10 min, cross-linked and ChIP experiments were performed to follow TBP and the CTD with the same antibodies used in the experiments presented in Figure 4. In this work, to further our understanding of the NC2 transcriptional co-factor, we studied S. cerevisiae cells expressing C-terminally truncated forms of either NC2 subunit. A rather small number of genes, including both BUR6 (Figure 2) and NCB2 (data not shown), are affected in these mutants during normal growth, suggesting that NC2 auto-regulates its expression. We find that the two subunits act mostly together in exponential phase. Several results strongly support this hypothesis. First, our microarray results show a significant overlap between genes affected in either NC2 subunit mutant. Second, ChIP experiments show that altering one subunit strongly impairs the recruitment of the second subunit to all DNA sequences tested. This finding contrasts with our conclusion in a recent report suggesting that NC2&#x3B1; and &#x3B2; might act independently of each other because they do not co-purify (14). Our present results do not exclude the possibility of independent functions for the NC2 subunits, since there are genes deregulated in one mutant and not in the other. However, they also reveal that the NC2 heterodimer is not limiting in cells growing exponentially since bur6-5 cells are wt for growth despite very much reduced DNA-bound heterodimeric NC2. In the previous study, we used cells expressing tagged versions of the NC2 subunits that express reduced levels of the NC2 heterodimer, which escaped detection, but supported wt growth (our unpublished data). Interestingly, ncb2-2 cells express similar low levels of the NC2 heterodimer as bur6-5 cells, but in contrast to bur6-5 cells, they display a slow growth phenotype. Thus, normal cell growth in high glucose does seem to require the C-terminal domain of NC2&#x3B2;, at least under limiting amounts of the NC2 heterodimer. We addressed the role of the domains C-terminal to the histone-fold motif (HFM) of both NC2&#x3B1; and NC2&#x3B2; in PIC assembly on target promoters in vivo. Indeed, structural studies suggest that the C-terminal region of NC2&#x3B2; inhibits TFIIB recruitment to TBP (8), whereas other studies have shown that the C-terminal region of human NC2&#x3B1; supports TBP binding to DNA (16) and interacts with BTAF1 (15). In yeast, sequences besides the HFM of NC2&#x3B1; are dispensable for growth (21). A functional importance for regions besides the HFM have been demonstrated in several proteins, such as the mammalian NF-Y trimeric transcription factor, where stretches at the N- and C-termini of the HFM influence DNA binding (22) and Taf11p, where the region N-terminal to the HFM contributes to interaction with TFIIA (23). In our study, we observe that the primary consequence of deleting the C-terminal regions of either NC2 subunit is a reduction of the NC2 heterodimer. Thus, mutant phenotypes common to both NC2 mutants reveal roles of the NC2 heterodimer, whereas roles for the C-terminal domains can be inferred from mutant phenotypes specific to one of the NC2 mutants only. Obviously, there may be additional roles of NC2 that have not been revealed in our study of these two specific mutants. First, concerning TBP, we observed a modest decrease of TBP binding to promoters such as BUR6 or RPS14b for the NC2&#x3B1; mutant only. From this, we conclude that NC2 is not generally contributing to, or limiting for, the association of TBP to promoters. However, the C-terminal domain of NC2&#x3B1; might provide some support for TBP binding to certain promoters, at least under limiting NC2 levels. For the early recruited factor TFIIA, no significant changes in either mutant on any promoter studied, was identified. Thus, NC2 is not limiting, and no role for the C-terminal regions of both subunits was found, either to support TFIIA association or to counteract TFIIA association, with promoters. This finding surprisingly does not support a previous model suggesting that the essential function of NC2 is to counteract TFIIA (7). The analysis of another early factor in PIC formation, TFIIB, revealed unexpectedly, that for many genes tested, mutation of either NC2 subunit led to its reduction on promoters. In contrast, out of all the genes tested, only two displayed an increase of TFIIB on their promoter, namely HSP12 and MUC1, and this only in the ncb2-2 mutant. This result does not support the model provided by in vitro studies and the crystal structure that NC2 and the C-terminal region of NC2&#x3B2; in particular, act as a global repressor of transcription by inhibiting recruitment of TFIIB. Rather, it appears that NC2 regulates TFIIB association with promoters in a highly gene-specific and dual manner. A positive role of NC2 on PIC formation is supported by previous biochemical studies with both drosophila NC2 (11) and yeast NC2 (6). The dominant role of NC2 on TFIIB in vivo appears to be a positive role, and this seems to be determined by the promoters of the target genes, as we determined for one such gene, RPS14b. In particular, TFIIB association with all strongly expressed genes that we looked at requires NC2, in accordance with recent reports suggesting that NC2 is generally activating ribosomal protein (RP) genes (24), but NC2 also has a positive effect on TFIIB recruitment to some lowly expressed genes such as HSP26 or DAN1. Factors which assemble after TFIIB in the PIC, namely TFIIE, TFIIH as well as RNA polymerase II, generally also decrease in NC2 mutants. However, mRNA levels do not always correlate with these effects, since some mRNAs decrease consistently, such as RPS14b, some do not change such as ADH1 and some even increase, such as DAN1 or HSP26. One possibility is that GTFs are limiting for RPS14b, but not limiting for genes such as ADH1, DAN1 or HSP26. The latter two mRNAs might additionally be indirectly increased by some post-transcriptional mechanism. This might also be the case for BUR6, for which we found no changes in the transcription machinery at the promoter that could correlate with the increased levels of the mRNA in the NC2 mutants. In contrast, the identified negative role of NC2, and in particular of the C-terminal domain of NC2&#x3B2;, on TFIIB association with promoters is very restricted. Indeed, HSP12 was the only target for such an effect identified on the entire chromosome VI by ChIP-on-ChIP experiments (data not shown). The HSP12 ORF, unique in the genome, is required for this regulation, explaining why the effect is so restricted. Surprisingly, the increased association of TFIIB with HSP12 in the ncb2-2 mutant correlates with a weak increase of Pol II, but not with any increase of either TFIIE or TFIIH. Thus, TFIIB on this promoter might be promoting transcription mostly at a step subsequent to polymerase binding in the mutant, leading for instance, to more productive elongation from a stalled or inefficient polymerase, taking as a model the block to elongation that has been described for mammalian or Drosophila heat-shock genes (25). Alternatively, the increased presence of TFIIB might accelerate re-initiation, play some role in efficient mRNA export or even not play an active role, but reflect the disappearance of an antisense transcript that prevents accumulation of a sense transcript in wt cells. This latter hypothesis integrates our observation that this regulation requires the HSP12 ORF, and a previous study revealing the presence of an antisense transcript for HSP12 (26). Furthermore, such a model could extend to other genes whose expression increases in NC2 mutants, such as DAN1, HSP26 and BUR6 for which we found no increase of tested components of the PIC at the promoter. Our study suggests that NC2 is bound in excess on many promoters in cells growing exponentially. It appears however, that for genes such as HSP12, this might be important in order to allow activation to high levels in response to the appropriate stimulus. This is consistent with a previous study that has suggested an important role of NC2 in the stress response (12) and our finding that the association of both NC2 subunits to the HSP12 promoter is transiently increased together with TBP, in response to heat shock. Furthermore, efficient recruitment of TBP and transcriptional activation upon heat shock requires the presence of sufficient NC2, and the NC2 mutants that have reduced NC2 heterodimer are temperature sensitive. It has been shown that NC2 can play a role in nucleosome sliding and assembly (17), and it is known that histones are depleted from heat-shock promoters upon heat shock (27). However, we found that histone H3 is correctly depleted from HSP12 upon heat shock in the NC2 mutants, suggesting that the effect of NC2 on TBP is not indirectly due to an effect on histone depletion. Taken together, our results suggest that NC2 plays a positive role on genes that are highly expressed, but through different GTFs in unstressed (TFIIB) or stressed (TBP) cells. In this regard, it is interesting to note that NC2 and Mot1p, another regulator of TBP, have been described to have common target genes (28), were identified in at least two similar genetic screens for transcriptional repressors (21), and that Mot1p, like NC2, is transiently recruited to heat-shock genes upon heat shock (29). However, whereas mutation of NC2 reduces activation of heat-shock genes in response to heat shock, mutation of MOT1 leads to increased expression of heat-shock mRNA levels (29) and to an increased presence of NC2 at promoters (28). Therefore an inter-play between NC2 and Mot1p might determine the importance of NC2 for the association of TBP with DNA, particularly upon heat shock. Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online.
</content>
</document>
