<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <id>2241874</id>
  <title>ATR-dependent pathways control hEXO1 stability in response to stalled forks
</title>
  <abstract>
 Nucleases play important roles in DNA synthesis, recombination and repair. We have previously shown that human exonuclease 1 (hEXO1) is phosphorylated in response to agents stalling DNA replication and that hEXO1 consequently undergoes ubiquitination and degradation in a proteasome-dependent manner. In the present study, we have addressed the identity of the pathway transducing stalled-replication signals to hEXO1. Using chemical inhibitors, RNA interference, ATM- and ATR-deficient cell lines we have concluded that hEXO1 phosphorylation is ATR-dependent. By means of mass spectrometry, we have identified the sites of phosphorylation in hEXO1 in undamaged cells and in cells treated with hydroxyurea (HU). hEXO1 is phosphorylated at nine basal sites and three additional sites are induced by HU treatment. Analysis of single- and multiple-point mutants revealed that mutation to Ala of the three HU-induced sites of phosphorylation partially rescued HU-dependent degradation of hEXO1 and additionally stabilized the protein in non-treated cells. We have raised an antibody to pS714, an HU-induced site of the S/T-Q type, and we provide evidence that S714 is phosphorylated upon HU but not IR treatment. The antibody may be a useful tool to monitor signal transduction events triggered by stalled DNA replication.
</abstract>
  <content>
 Exonuclease 1 is a DNA repair nuclease of the Rad2 family originally identified in the fission yeast Schizosaccharomyces pombe (1). The activity of S. pombe Exo1 gene product is induced about 5-fold just prior to meiosis, which led to the suggestion that Exo1 might be involved in meiotic homologous recombination (1). Transcriptional induction of the Saccharomyces cerevisiae and the Drosophila melanogaster EXO1 gene during meiosis has also been reported (2,3). Mouse Exo1 was found predominantly expressed in testis and the spleen, consistent with roles in processes specific to germ cell maturation and hematopoiesis (4). The human homolog EXO1 gene encodes a protein bearing only 27% identity to its yeast counterpart (5,6). Nonetheless, human exonuclease 1 (hEXO1) was shown to be functionally similar to the yeast protein by its ability to complement S. cerevisiae Exo1 and the mutator phenotype of the yeast rad27 mutant (5,7). In humans, two isoforms (hEXO1a and hEXO1b) have been described to arise from alternative splicing (5,8), though no functional differences between the two isoforms have been reported. The expression of hEXO1 reflects the pattern reported for the mouse, with high levels in testis, thymus and colon and slightly lower expression in small intestine, placenta, spleen and ovary (5). EXO1 catalyzes the removal of mononucleotides from the 5&#x2032; end of the DNA duplex, showing a strong preference for blunt-ended, 5&#x2032; recessed termini and DNA nicks. It can also degrade exonucleolytically single-stranded DNA, although less efficiently than double-stranded DNA (9,10). Moreover, hEXO1 displays a 5&#x2032; ssDNA-flap-specific endonuclease activity but does not possess endonuclease activity at bubble-like structures (10). In S. cerevisiae, EXO1 was shown to participate in meiotic crossing over as well as in the processing of double-strand breaks (DSB) ends (2). An additional role in mutation avoidance and mismatch correction was described for S. pombe Exo1 (11). Mismatch repair (MMR) is a mechanism reducing the rate of somatic microsatellite polymorphism and it is disabled in a number of human cancers (12). The involvement of Exo1 in MMR was confirmed by studies demonstrating physical and genetic interaction between yeast Exo1 and the MMR proteins Msh2 (6) and Mlh1 (13). Furthermore, an independent study confirmed the structural role of yeast Exo1 in the stabilization of the multiprotein complex containing MMR proteins (14). Studies conducted with human recombinant proteins or HeLa cells extracts confirmed the interaction between hEXO1 and the MMR proteins hMSH2 (15) and hMLH1/hPMS2 (16). The functional role of hEXO1 in MMR was addressed in complementation assays (5) as well as in reconstituted systems (17&#x2013;20). Taken together, the evidence provided by these studies pointed to hEXO1 as the most likely candidate for the excision step during MMR in mammals. In addition to MMR, yeast Exo1 was shown to participate to mitotic (21) and meiotic recombination (2) and to end-resection at telomeres (22). The physical interaction observed in human cells between hEXO1 and the Werner Syndrome helicase WRN (23) and RECQ1 (24) further pointed to a role for hEXO1 in the resolution of DNA intermediates that are formed during recombination (25). In ectopic expression studies, hEXO1 was shown to interact with PCNA via its C-terminal region and the two proteins co-localized at DNA replication foci (26). Proper nuclear localization of hEXO was shown to depend on the sequence K418RPR421, which exhibits strong homology to other monopartite nuclear localization sequences (NLS) (27). The importance of exonuclease 1 is underscored by the phenotype of Exo1&#x2212;/&#x2212; mice that displayed reduced survival, sterility and increased susceptibility to the development of lymphomas (28). Analysis of Exo1&#x2212;/&#x2212; cells revealed specific defects in MMR leading to elevated microsatellite instability, increased mutation rate at the Hprt locus and abnormal spindle structures in metaphase cells (28). Moreover, Exo1 mutant mice displayed altered somatic hypermutation and reduced class switch recombination (29). Consistent with its proposed role at sites of DNA replication (30,31), we have previously shown that the hEXO1 protein is selectively destabilized in response to fork arrest. We reported the rapid degradation of hEXO1 to depend on ubiquitin-mediated proteasome pathways and to be facilitated by phosphorylation (32). In the present study, we have examined the pathway transducing the fork-arrest signal to hEXO1 and we have identified ATR as the responsible kinase. Moreover, we have localized the sites of phosphorylation in hEXO1 and assessed their role in the stability of the protein. Finally, we have generated and characterized an antibody to one of the fork arrest-induced sites of phosphorylation in hEXO1 that would represent a useful tool in studies addressing DNA replication fork stalling. The polyclonal antibody F-15 to the N-terminus of hEXO1 was previously described (32). A monoclonal antibody to full-length EXO1 (Ab-4, clone 266) was purchased from NeoMarkers (Fremont, CA, USA). Antibodies to CHK1-pS345, CHK2-pT68 and p53-pS15 were from Cell Signaling Technology (Beverly, MA, USA). The antibody to ATM-pS1981 was from Rockland (Gilbertsville, PA, USA). Antibodies to ATM and ATR were from Gentex (San Antonio, TX, USA) and Calbiochem (San Diego, CA, USA), respectively. Antibodies to TFIIH (sc-293) and MSH6 (clone 44, G70220) were from Santa Cruz Biotechnology (Santa Cruz, CA, USA) and BD Transduction Laboratories (San Jose, CA, USA), respectively. The Omni-probe antibody (sc-499) used to detect Omni-tagged hEXO1 was from Santa Cruz Biotechnology. HRP-conjugated anti-mouse and anti-rabbit secondary antibodies were obtained from Amersham-Biosciences/GE-Healthcare (Otelfingen, Switzerland), whereas the secondary anti-goat was obtained from Santa Cruz Biotechnology. The antibody to phosphorylated S714 in hEXO1 was raised using the peptide CNIKLLDpSQSDQT, where pS represents phospho-Serine (Eurogentec, Seraing, Belgium). The HPLC purified peptide was coupled to Keyhole Limpet Hemocyanin (KLH) and used to immunize two rabbits. The resulting sera were affinity purified by two consecutive chromatography steps over phosphopeptide and non-phosphopeptide columns. The phospho-specific antibody was eluted with 0.1 M glycine&#x2013;HCl pH 2.5 and neutralized with 1 M Tris&#x2013;HCl pH 8.0. Hydroxyurea (HU) and caffeine were obtained from Sigma (St. Louis, MO, USA) and dissolved in water. KU-55933 was kindly provided by Kudos Pharmaceuticals (Cambridge, UK) and dissolved in DMSO. MG132 was purchased from Calbiochem and dissolved in DMSO. The protein referred as hEXO1 throughout this study is the isoform b. An expression vector for wt-hEXO1 was created by subcloning full-length hEXO1 in pcDNA3.1-His&#xA9; (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) 3&#x2032; to a His-tag that is specifically recognized by the Omni-probe antibody. Single- and multiple-hEXO1 mutants of the sites of phosphorylation (Ser/Thr &gt; Ala) were generated with the QuikChange site-directed mutagenesis kit (Stratagene, La Jolla, CA, USA) using wt-hEXO1 as template. The overlapping oligonucleotides employed were the following: S454 &gt; A forward: 5&#x2032;-GCAATAAATCATTGGCCTTTTCTGAAGTG-3&#x2032; S454 &gt; A reverse: 5&#x2032;-CACTTCAGAAAAGCCCAATGATTTATTGC-3&#x2032; T621 &gt; A forward: 5&#x2032;-GAGATTTTTCAAGAGCGCCGAGCCCCTCTCC-3&#x2032; T621 &gt; A reverse: 5&#x2032;-GGAGAGGGGCTCGGCGCTCTTGAAAAATCTC-3&#x2032; S714 &gt; forward: 5&#x2032;-GCAATATTAAGTTACTTGACGATCAAAGTGACCAGACC-3&#x2032; S714 &gt; reverse: 5&#x2032;-CGTTATAATTCAATGAACTGCTAGTTTCACTGGTCTGG-3&#x2032; S674 &gt; A forward: 5&#x2032;-GGCATGTTCTGCACAGTCCCAGGAAAG-3&#x2032; S674 &gt; A reverse: 5&#x2032;-CTTTCCTGGGACTGTGCAGAACATGCC-3&#x2032; S676 &gt; A forward: 5&#x2032;-GTTCTGCACAGGCCCAGGAAAGTGG-3&#x2032; S676 &gt; A reverse: 5&#x2032;-CCACTTTCCTGGGCCTGTGAAGAAC-3&#x2032; S693 &gt; A forward: 5&#x2032;-GCATCAAAGCTTGCTCAGTGCTCTAG-3&#x2032; S693 &gt; A reverse: 5&#x2032;-CTAGAGCACTGAGCAAGCTTTGATGC-3&#x2032; All single and multiple mutations were verified by DNA sequencing. HEK-293, HEK-293T, HeLa, U2OS, mouse embryonal fibroblast (MEF) and NIH3T3 cells were maintained in DMEM (OmniLab, Mettmenstetten, Switzerland) supplemented with 10% fetal calf serum (FCS) (Life technologies, Rockville, MD, USA), penicillin (100 U/ml) and streptomycin (100 &#x3BC;g/ml). The ATM-deficient (AT) fibroblasts AT22IJE-T and the matched line complemented with an ATM minigene (AT + ATM) were kindly provided by Y. Shiloh (Tel Aviv University, Israel) and were maintained as described (33). ATR-Seckel cells were kindly provided by M. O&#x2019;Driscoll and P. Jeggo (University of Sussex, UK) and were maintained in RPMI (OmniLab, Mettmenstetten, Switzerland) supplemented with 15% FCS, penicillin (100 units/ml) and streptomycin (100 &#x3BC;g/ml). Transient transfections were performed in 6 cm cell culture dishes using 0.5 &#x3BC;g expression vector for wt-EXO1 or Ala-point mutants and the FuGENE-6&#xAE; transfection reagent (Roche, Basel, Switzerland). Eight hours upon transfection cells were either left untreated or treated with HU for 24 h and harvested 32 h post-transfection. To create stable cell lines expressing shRNA for ATM or ATR, the constructs described in Ref. (34) were used. HEK-293T cells were transfected either with empty vector (EV) or with shRNA specific to ATM or ATR. Cells underwent selection with 10 &#x3BC;g/ml puromycin for 3 weeks. Downregulation of specific target genes was monitored by western blot analysis. Irradiation of cell was performed using a Faxitron&#xAE; Cabinet X-ray system, model 43855D (Faxitron X-ray Corp., Wheeling, IL, USA). Cellular proteins were extracted using ice-cold lysis buffer (50 mM Tris&#x2013;HCl pH 7.5, 120 mM NaCl, 20 mM NaF, 1 mM EDTA, 6 mM EGTA, 15 mM Na-pyrophosphate, 0.5 mM Na-orthovanadate, 1 mM benzamidine, 0.1 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride and 1% nonidet P-40). Protein concentration was determined using the Bio-Rad Protein Assay Reagent (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA, USA). Detection of proteins by western blot analysis was performed following separation of whole cell extracts (50 &#x3BC;g) on 8% SDS&#x2013;PAGE. To detect ATM or ATR in whole cell extracts, 6% SDS&#x2013;PAGE was used. Proteins were transferred to polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) (Amersham Biosciences GE-Healthcare, Otelfingen, Switzerland), probed with appropriate antibodies and immune complexes were revealed using the enhanced chemiluminescence system (Amersham Biosciences GE-Healthcare, Otelfingen, Switzerland). Immunoprecipitation of hEXO1 was carried out with polyclonal antibody F-15, as previously described (32), using HEK-293 (2 mg), HEK-293T (2 mg), HeLa (5 mg), U2OS (7 mg), MEF (6 mg) or NIH3T3 (9 mg) total cell extracts. The immunoprecipitated proteins were revealed by western blot using monoclonal Ab-4 antibody. HEK-293 cells were transfected with an expression vector for wt-hEXO1 using Metafectene&#xAE; (Biontex, Planegg, Germany) as transfection reagent. Twenty-four hours upon transfection, cells were either left untreated or treated with HU for 24 h and were harvested 48 h post-transfection. Using the Omni-probe antibody, hEXO1 was immunoprecipitated from 12 mg of cell extracts, for 3 h at 4&#xB0;C. The antibody was captured on protein G-agarose beads that were subsequently washed twice with TNET buffer (50 mM Tris&#x2013;HCl pH 7.5, 140 mM NaCl, 5 mM EDTA and 1% Triton X-100) and twice with TNE buffer (50 mM Tris&#x2013;HCl pH 7.5, 140 mM NaCl and 5 mM EDTA) before boiling in an equal volume of 2&#xD7; Laemmli-SDS sample buffer. Samples were alkylated with iodoacetamide (55 mM) for 45 min in the dark. Proteins were subjected to electrophoresis on 8% SDS&#x2013;PAGE and stained with Coomasie Brilliant Blue. Bands corresponding to Omni-hEXO1 were excised and digested with 1 &#x3BC;g trypsin (Promega, Madison, WI, USA) in 50 mM ammonium bicarbonate (pH 8.0) at 37&#xB0;C for 16 h (35). The resulting peptides were analyzed by capillary liquid chromatography-tandem mass spectrometry (LC&#x2013;MS/MS) using a Magic C18 100 &#x3BC;m &#xD7; 10 cm HPLC column (Spectronex, Basel, Switzerland) connected online to an ion-trap Finnigan DecaXP (ThermoFinnigan, San Jose, CA, USA). A linear gradient from 5 to 50% solvent B (0.1% formic acid and 80% (v/v) acetonitrile in water) in solvent A (0.1% formic acid and 2% acetonitrile in water) was delivered in 60 min with a Rheos 2000 HPLC system (Flux, Basel, Switzerland) at 100 &#x3BC;l/min flow rate. A pre-column flow-splitter reduced the flow to &#x223C;300 nl/min and the peptides were manually loaded with a 10 &#x3BC;l Hamilton syringe on a peptide cap-trap cartridge (Michrom BioResources, Auburn, CA, USA) mounted in the injection loop of the MS. The eluting peptides were ionized by electrospray ionization, detected and the peptide ions were automatically selected and fragmented by collision-induced dissociation (MS/MS) in the ion trap. Individual MS/MS spectra were compared against the known protein sequence using TurboSequest software (36). Phosphorylated peptides were sequenced more than once. ATR-dependent control of hEXO1 stability in response to stalled replication. (A) HEK-293, U2OS, HeLa and MEF cells were grown in the presence or the absence of 2 mM HU for 24 h. Whole cell extracts were immunoprecipitated with the rabbit polyclonal antibody F-15 and resolved on a 8% SDS&#x2013;PAGE. Human and mouse EXO1 were visualized with the monoclonal antibody Ab-4. MSH6 and IgG(H) were used as controls for the input and the quality of the immunoprecipitation, respectively. (B) Upper panels: immunoprecipitation of hEXO1 from HEK-293T cells left untreated (lane 1) or treated for 8 h with either 10 &#x3BC;M KU-55933 (lane 2), 4 mM caffeine (lane 3), 2 mM HU (lane 4), 4 mM caffeine followed by 2 mM HU (lane 5) or 10 &#x3BC;M KU-55933 followed by 2 mM HU (lane 6). hEXO1 was detected as described above. The signal given by IgG(H) was used as control for the quality of the immunoprecipitation. Lower panels: western blot analysis of phosphorylated CHK1 in whole cell extracts was used as read-out for the cellular response to HU. TFIIH was used as loading control. (C) HEK-293T cells were stably transfected with EV, ATR or ATM shRNA constructs. hEXO1 was immunoprecipitated from cells left untreated or treated with HU for 16 h. The signal given by IgG(H) was used as control for the quality of the immunoprecipitation. ATR and ATM expression was monitored to assess the extent of downregulation by shRNA. TFIIH served as loading control. The data shown represent one of three independent experiments. (D) ATR-Seckel cells at early or late passages were either left untreated or treated with HU for 16 h. hEXO1 was immunoprecipitated as described above. TFIIH and IgG(H) were used as controls for the input and the quality of the immunoprecipitation, respectively. The expression of ATR was examined by western blot analysis. (E) AT or AT + ATM fibroblasts were treated in the presence or the absence of HU and the expression of hEXO1 was assessed following immunoprecipitation as described above. TFIIH and IgG(H) were used as controls for input and quality of the immunoprecipitation, respectively. ATR-dependent control of hEXO1 stability in response to stalled replication. (A) HEK-293, U2OS, HeLa and MEF cells were grown in the presence or the absence of 2 mM HU for 24 h. Whole cell extracts were immunoprecipitated with the rabbit polyclonal antibody F-15 and resolved on a 8% SDS&#x2013;PAGE. Human and mouse EXO1 were visualized with the monoclonal antibody Ab-4. MSH6 and IgG(H) were used as controls for the input and the quality of the immunoprecipitation, respectively. (B) Upper panels: immunoprecipitation of hEXO1 from HEK-293T cells left untreated (lane 1) or treated for 8 h with either 10 &#x3BC;M KU-55933 (lane 2), 4 mM caffeine (lane 3), 2 mM HU (lane 4), 4 mM caffeine followed by 2 mM HU (lane 5) or 10 &#x3BC;M KU-55933 followed by 2 mM HU (lane 6). hEXO1 was detected as described above. The signal given by IgG(H) was used as control for the quality of the immunoprecipitation. Lower panels: western blot analysis of phosphorylated CHK1 in whole cell extracts was used as read-out for the cellular response to HU. TFIIH was used as loading control. (C) HEK-293T cells were stably transfected with EV, ATR or ATM shRNA constructs. hEXO1 was immunoprecipitated from cells left untreated or treated with HU for 16 h. The signal given by IgG(H) was used as control for the quality of the immunoprecipitation. ATR and ATM expression was monitored to assess the extent of downregulation by shRNA. TFIIH served as loading control. The data shown represent one of three independent experiments. (D) ATR-Seckel cells at early or late passages were either left untreated or treated with HU for 16 h. hEXO1 was immunoprecipitated as described above. TFIIH and IgG(H) were used as controls for the input and the quality of the immunoprecipitation, respectively. The expression of ATR was examined by western blot analysis. (E) AT or AT + ATM fibroblasts were treated in the presence or the absence of HU and the expression of hEXO1 was assessed following immunoprecipitation as described above. TFIIH and IgG(H) were used as controls for input and quality of the immunoprecipitation, respectively. To finally confirm the lack of involvement of ATM in signaling to hEXO1, we examined the response of fibroblast derived from an AT-patient (33). Both in ATM-deficient and -proficient fibroblasts, hEXO1 displayed a similar pattern of degradation in response to HU treatment (Figure 1E), thus ruling out a role for ATM in this process. Taken together, these data show that the stalled-fork signal was relayed to hEXO1 through an ATR-dependent pathway. Identification of the sites of phosphorylation in hEXO1. (A) HEK-293 cells were transfected with EV (lane 3) or an expression vector encoding Omni-hEXO1 (lanes 4&#x2013;7). Cells were left untreated (lanes 4 and 5) or treated with 2 mM HU for 24 h (lanes 6 and 7). hEXO1 was immmunoprecipitated with the Omni-probe antibody. Samples were subjected to 8% SDS&#x2013;PAGE electrophoresis and the gel was stained with Coomassie Brilliant Blue. Molecular weight protein markers (lane 1) and 500 ng BSA (lane 2) were loaded to estimate the amount of immunoprecipitated hEXO1. The protein bands corresponding to hEXO1 were excised from the gel and underwent LC-MS/MS analysis. (B) Schematic representation of hEXO1 and localization of the sites of phosphorylation identified by LC-MS/MS. N-terminal (N) and internal (I) catalytic domains are indicated. Dots, basal sites; stars, HU-induced sites. Sites of phosphorylation that were identified in hEXO1 phosphopeptides present among the peptides detected in LC&#x2013;MS/MS analysis Sites of phosphorylation that were identified in hEXO1 phosphopeptides present among the peptides detected in LC&#x2013;MS/MS analysis Characterization of the hEXO1-pS714 antibody. (A) HeLa cells were transfected with EV (lane 1) or Omni-hEXO1 expression vector (lanes 2 and 3). Cells were left untreated or treated with HU for 24 h. Whole cell extracts were subjected to 8% SDS&#x2013;PAGE electrophoresis, followed by western blot analysis using antibody pS714 to detect phosphorylated hEXO1 (upper panel) or mouse monoclonal antibody Ab-4 to visualize the entire pool of hEXO1 (middle panel). TFIIH served as control for equal loading. (B) HEK-293T cells were transfected with EV (lane 1), expression vector for wild-type Omni-hEXO1 (lanes 2 and 3) or for the non-phosphorylatable mutant Omni-hEXO1-A714 (lane 4). Cells were treated with HU as indicated. Western blot analysis of total cell extracts was performed using antibody pS714. (C) Immunoprecipitation of endogenous hEXO1 from HEK-293T cells using either pS714 antibody (upper panel) or rabbit polyclonal antibody F-15 (lower panel) followed by western blot analysis with mouse monoclonal antibody Ab-4. (D) HEK-293T cells were transfected with an expression vector for wild-type Omni-hEXO1 (lanes 1&#x2013;3). Cells were left untreated or treated with IR (10 Gy) or HU (2 mM), as indicated, and hEXO1 was immunoprecipitated using rabbit polyclonal antibody F-15 (upper panels). The signal given by IgG(H) was used as control for the quality of the immunoprecipitation. The phosphorylation status of hEXO1 and CHK2 was monitored by western blot analysis using phospho-specific antibodies (lower panels). TFIIH was used as loading control. Characterization of the hEXO1-pS714 antibody. (A) HeLa cells were transfected with EV (lane 1) or Omni-hEXO1 expression vector (lanes 2 and 3). Cells were left untreated or treated with HU for 24 h. Whole cell extracts were subjected to 8% SDS&#x2013;PAGE electrophoresis, followed by western blot analysis using antibody pS714 to detect phosphorylated hEXO1 (upper panel) or mouse monoclonal antibody Ab-4 to visualize the entire pool of hEXO1 (middle panel). TFIIH served as control for equal loading. (B) HEK-293T cells were transfected with EV (lane 1), expression vector for wild-type Omni-hEXO1 (lanes 2 and 3) or for the non-phosphorylatable mutant Omni-hEXO1-A714 (lane 4). Cells were treated with HU as indicated. Western blot analysis of total cell extracts was performed using antibody pS714. (C) Immunoprecipitation of endogenous hEXO1 from HEK-293T cells using either pS714 antibody (upper panel) or rabbit polyclonal antibody F-15 (lower panel) followed by western blot analysis with mouse monoclonal antibody Ab-4. (D) HEK-293T cells were transfected with an expression vector for wild-type Omni-hEXO1 (lanes 1&#x2013;3). Cells were left untreated or treated with IR (10 Gy) or HU (2 mM), as indicated, and hEXO1 was immunoprecipitated using rabbit polyclonal antibody F-15 (upper panels). The signal given by IgG(H) was used as control for the quality of the immunoprecipitation. The phosphorylation status of hEXO1 and CHK2 was monitored by western blot analysis using phospho-specific antibodies (lower panels). TFIIH was used as loading control. To definitely assess whether the epitope recognized by the antibody was phospho-S714, we ectopically expressed wt-hEXO1 or the point mutant A714-hEXO1 in HEK293 cells that were either left untreated or treated with HU. The results obtained show that the pS714 antibody could detect the HU-induced increase in hEXO1 phosphorylation only in the case of wt-hEXO1 (Figure 3B, lane 3) but not in the A714 point mutant (Figure 3B, lane 4). This allowed us concluding that the pS714 antibody specifically reacted with hEXO1 phosphorylated at S714. Next, we examined the ability of the pS714 antibody to detect endogenous hEXO1. To this end, immunoprecipitation experiments were performed on total extracts of HEK-293T cells using either the pS714 antibody (Figure 3C, upper panel) or antibody F15 (Figure 3C, lower panel). The data show that antibody pS714 was able to precipitate the phosphorylated form of the endogenous hEXO1 protein and this occurred only in the case of HU-treated cells (Figure 3C, lanes 2 and 3). The fact that a higher amount of phosphorylated hEXO1 was precipitated from MG-132 treated cells in comparison to untreated cells (Figure 3C, upper panel, lane 3 versus lane 2), confirmed our early finding that hEXO1 degradation is phosphorylation-dependent (32). Antibody pS714 was also suitable for the detection of phosphorylated hEXO1 by western blot analysis upon immunoprecipitation of the endogenous protein. A weak but clear signal was observed upon treatment with HU and the proteasome inhibitor MG-132 to prevent hEXO1 degradation (Supplementary Figure 4). Finally, considering that S714 belongs to the S/T-Q type of DNA damage sites, we asked whether S714 is specifically phosphorylated upon replication fork stalling or if it is also targeted in response to other types of DNA damage. To this end, we treated HEK-293T cells ectopically expressing Omni-tagged hEXO1 with either IR or HU. Detection of hEXO1 with the pS714 antibody indicated that HU potently induced phosphorylation at this site (Figure 3D, lane 3), whereas the IR treatment was only minimally affecting phosphorylation at S714 (Figure 3D, lane 2). Taken together, these results show that the pS714 antibody is able to specifically recognize the phosphorylated S714 epitope in hEXO1 and that S714 is a site selectively targeted in response to stalled replication. The pS714 antibody may be potentially employed to monitor the flow of signal transduction events in studies on stalled DNA replication. A second foreseeable application for this tool is the identification of hEXO1 interacting proteins by means of combined immunoprecipitation/mass spectrometry under conditions of stalled DNA replication, when hEXO1 is phosphorylated at S714. Effect of HU on non-phosphorylatable hEXO1 mutants. (A) HeLa cells were transfected with an expression vector for wild-type Omni-hEXO1 or the single Ala point mutants indicated in the panel. Cells were left untreated or treated with HU for 24 h. Total cell extracts were analyzed by western blot using the Omni-probe antibody to detect the tagged hEXO1 protein. Data were quantified using ImageQuant 5.2 software (Amersham-Biosciences/GE-Healthcare). Percent degradation was calculated as the ratio between the amount of protein present in HU treated over untreated lanes. TFIIH was used for normalization. (B) Analysis of multiple hEXO1-Ala point mutants was performed as indicated above. The data shown in panels A and B represent one of three independent experiments. Effect of HU on non-phosphorylatable hEXO1 mutants. (A) HeLa cells were transfected with an expression vector for wild-type Omni-hEXO1 or the single Ala point mutants indicated in the panel. Cells were left untreated or treated with HU for 24 h. Total cell extracts were analyzed by western blot using the Omni-probe antibody to detect the tagged hEXO1 protein. Data were quantified using ImageQuant 5.2 software (Amersham-Biosciences/GE-Healthcare). Percent degradation was calculated as the ratio between the amount of protein present in HU treated over untreated lanes. TFIIH was used for normalization. (B) Analysis of multiple hEXO1-Ala point mutants was performed as indicated above. The data shown in panels A and B represent one of three independent experiments. Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online.
</content>
</document>
