<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <id>2241876</id>
  <title>Epstein&#x2013;Barr virus-encoded microRNA miR-BART2 down-regulates the viral DNA polymerase BALF5
</title>
  <abstract>
 MicroRNAs (miRNAs) have been implicated in sequence-specific cleavage, translational repression or deadenylation of specific target mRNAs resulting in post-transcriptional gene silencing. Epstein&#x2013;Barr virus (EBV) encodes 23 miRNAs of unknown function. Here we show that the EBV-encoded miRNA miR-BART2 down-regulates the viral DNA polymerase BALF5. MiR-BART2 guides cleavage within the 3&#x2032;-untranslated region (3&#x2032;UTR) of BALF5 by virtue of its complete complementarity to its target. Induction of the lytic viral replication cycle results in a reduction of the level of miR-BART2 with a strong concomitant decrease of cleavage of the BALF5 3&#x2032;UTR. Expression of miR-BART2 down-regulates the activity of a luciferase reporter gene containing the BALF5 3&#x2032;UTR. Forced expression of miR-BART2 during lytic replication resulted in a 40&#x2013;50% reduction of the level of BALF5 protein and a 20% reduction of the amount of virus released from EBV-infected cells. Our results are compatible with the notion that EBV-miR-BART2 inhibits transition from latent to lytic viral replication.
</abstract>
  <content>
 MicroRNAs (miRNAs) are non-coding RNAs of about 19&#x2013;24 nt that usually bind to partially complementary sites in the 3&#x2032;-untranslated region (3&#x2032;UTR) of mRNA targets (1,2) and either repress translation, induce degradation or deadenylation of their targets (3). MiRNA-encoding genes are transcribed by RNA polymerases II and III and are processed by the RNase III Drosha to precursors (4&#x2013;6) which are converted to mature miRNAs in the cytoplasm by the RNase III Dicer (7,8). Some but not all miRNAs with complete complementarity to their mRNAs employ the RNase Ago2 to direct the cleavage of their targets (9,10). Presumably, miRNAs regulate multiple targets and have been implicated in a variety of cellular processes as well as diseases including cancer (11&#x2013;13). (A) Genomic localization of the EBV miRNAs. The top row of the schematic shows the location of the genes expressed in latently infected B-cells. The position of the three clusters of the miRNAs within the genome is shown in greater detail in the bottom. The deletion within the B95.8 virus isolate is indicated. For the exact location of the EBV-miRNAs, refer to references 15&#x2013;17. (B) Schematic representation of luciferase reporters containing the 3&#x2032; untranslated region (Luc-BALF5-3&#x2032;UTR) of the EBV BALF5 DNA polymerase gene. The 3&#x2032;UTR of BALF5 extends in leftward orientation on the EBV genome from nucleotides 153228 to 152188. The potential binding site of EBV miR-BART2 (encoded on the opposite strand) extends from 152768 to 152746 and was deleted by PCR in the reporter Luc-BALF5 3&#x2032;UTR-mut. Numbering refers to gene bank accession number AJ507799. Note that the drawing is not to scale. (A) Genomic localization of the EBV miRNAs. The top row of the schematic shows the location of the genes expressed in latently infected B-cells. The position of the three clusters of the miRNAs within the genome is shown in greater detail in the bottom. The deletion within the B95.8 virus isolate is indicated. For the exact location of the EBV-miRNAs, refer to references 15&#x2013;17. (B) Schematic representation of luciferase reporters containing the 3&#x2032; untranslated region (Luc-BALF5-3&#x2032;UTR) of the EBV BALF5 DNA polymerase gene. The 3&#x2032;UTR of BALF5 extends in leftward orientation on the EBV genome from nucleotides 153228 to 152188. The potential binding site of EBV miR-BART2 (encoded on the opposite strand) extends from 152768 to 152746 and was deleted by PCR in the reporter Luc-BALF5 3&#x2032;UTR-mut. Numbering refers to gene bank accession number AJ507799. Note that the drawing is not to scale. Adherent HeLa and 293-T cells were grown in DMEM supplemented with 10% FCS and antibiotics (100 U penicillin ml&#x2212;1 and 100 &#xB5;g streptomycin ml&#x2212;1) as described (19). H.-J- Delecluse, DKFZ, Heidelberg, kindly supplied 293-EBV cells (2089) (20) which were cultivated in RPMI supplemented with 10% FCS, antibiotics and Hygromycin (100 &#xB5;g/ml). The non-adherent EBV-infected B-cell lines B95.8, M-ABA, Raji and Jijoye were cultured as described in RPMI 1640 supplemented with 10% FCS and antibiotics (21&#x2013;23). BL41 is an EBV-negative Burkitt's lymphoma line; BL41-B95.8 is infected with the standard B95.8 strain (24). For lytic cycle induction, cells were incubated for 48 h with 20 ng/ml TPA (12-O-tetradecanoyl-phorbol-13-acetate; Sigma, M&#xFC;nchen, Germany). Monoclonal antibody BZ-1 directed against BZLF1 was kindly provided by Martin Rowe, Birmingham, UK; anti-&#xDF;-actin mAb was purchased from Sigma (M&#xFC;nchen, Germany). An internal peptide (G66KGMWWRQRAQEGTARPEADT87) of the DNA polymerase BALF5 of EBV was synthesized and coupled to KLH or OVA (PSL, Heidelberg, Germany). Rats were immunized with 50 &#xB5;g peptide-KLH using CPG 2006 and IFA as adjuvant. Generation of monoclonal antibodies was carried out as described (21). Supernatants were tested in a differential ELISA using the BALF5-peptide-OVA and an irrelevant peptide-OVA conjugate as negative control. BALF5-specific clone 4C12 (IgG2a) subclass was established which recognized the EBV polymerase in western blot, immunoprecipitation and immunofluorescence assays. Rat monoclonal antibodies against Ago2 were generated by immunization with a bacterially expressed GST-fusion protein encompassing the N-terminal aa MGVLSAIPALAPPAPPPPIQGYAFKPPRPDFGTSGRTIKLQANFFEMD of Ago2 in the vector pGEX6P1 (9); screening by ELISA was carried out using the Ago2-GST-fusion protein and an irrelevant GST-fusion protein as a control. A clone designated 3C7 (IgG1) that reacted with Ago2 in immunoprecipitation and western blot analysis was established for further experiments. Using Nanofectin&#xAE; (PAA, C&#xF6;lbe, Austria), 2 &#xD7; 106 293-T cells were transfected with HA-tagged Ago2 expression vector (9). After 48 h, cells were pelleted and lysed with a buffer containing 10 mM Tris&#x2013;HCl, pH 8.0, 150 mM NaCl, 0.5 mM EDTA, 0.5% NP-40 (Igepal, Sigma, M&#xFC;nchen, Germany) supplemented with protease inhibitor cocktail (Roche). After 20 min on ice, the extract was centrifuged in a tabletop centrifuge and &#x223C;900 &#xB5;g of protein extract was incubated over night at 4&#xB0;C with antibody immobilized on 50 &#xB5;l of settled protein G Sepharose (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech, Uppsala, Sweden). The beads were collected, washed repeatedly in lysis buffer with a final concentration of 0.5 M NaCl. The immune complexes were dissolved in SDS&#x2013;gelbuffer, separated by 10% polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis and transferred to nitrocellulose membrane. The membrane was incubated with Ago2-specific 3C7 (1:1000) in PBS/5% non-fat dried milk. Bound antibody was visualized by the ECL&#xAE; method (Amersham Pharmacia Biotech) using peroxidase-coupled goat-anti-rat as secondary antibody (19). For immunoprecipitation of BALF5, extract of TPA-treated Raji cells was incubated either with BALF5-specific antibody 4C12 or irrelevant isotype control. Immune complexes were collected using protein G sepharose (Amersham-Pharmacia) and washed as described above. The precipitated BALF5 protein was analysed in a western blot using 4C12 as primary antibody; bound antibody was visualized by the ECL method. DNA manipulations were carried out according to standard procedures. To express miR-BART2, which maps to position 152747&#x2013;152768 of the EBV genome (Gene bank accession number AJ507799), the nucleotides 152663&#x2013;152902 of EBV were PCR-amplified from M-ABA DNA using primers BART2-pSG5 Eco 5&#x2032;-GTC GAA TTC GGG TGG TGT CTG CAG CAA AAG-3&#x2032; and BART2-pSG5 EcoBgl 5&#x2032;-TCT GAA TTC AGA TCT GCT TCA GAC AGC CGC GGT TG-3&#x2032;, inserted into pSG5 (Stratagene) to yield pSG5-miR-BART2. The nucleotides 162&#x2013;391 of the human BIC-mRNA (gene bank accession number AF402776) that encompass miR-155 were PCR amplified with primers 5&#x2032;Eco miR155 5&#x2032;-CGC GAA TTC CAG GAA GGG GAA ATC TGT-3&#x2032; and 3&#x2032;Bgl miR155 5&#x2032;-CGC GAA TTC AGA TCT GTT TAT CCA GCA GGG TGA CTC-3&#x2032; from human genomic DNA and inserted into pSG5 to generate pSG5-miR-155. To yield the luciferase reporter plasmid Luc BALF5 3&#x2032;UTR the nucleotides 152128 to 153228 of the EBV genome including the putative binding site for miR-BART2 (nucleotides 152747 to 152768) were PCR-amplified using the primers BALF5-3&#x2032;UTR-for 5&#x2032;-GCT CTA GAT CTG GGG GCC TGA GAC TGG ACC C-3&#x2032; and BALF5-3&#x2032;UTR-rev 5&#x2032;-GC TCT AGA GGA GTA CCA GAC AAA ACA CGC CC-3&#x2032; and XbaI digested and ligated into the vector pGL3-promoter (Promega, Mannheim, Germany) (note that the BALF5 gene is transcribed in 3&#x2032; to 5&#x2032; orientation from the viral genome). To delete the binding site for miR-BART2, the fragments directly adjacent to the binding sites were amplified using the primer pairs 5&#x2032;-EcoNhe 5&#x2032;-GAC GAA TTC GCT AGC TCT GGG GGC CTG AGA CTG GAC CC-3&#x2032; and 3&#x2032;-Eco 5&#x2032;-CGA GAA TTC TGG AAG TCC ACC AGG CAG GGA GG-3&#x2032; for the 5&#x2032;-side and the primers 5&#x2032;-Eco 5&#x2032;-TCG GAA TTC GTG TCC ATT GTT GCA AGG AGC G-3&#x2032; and 3&#x2032;-Nhe 5&#x2032;-GCG CTA GCT CTG GGG GCC TGA GAC TGG ACC C-3&#x2032;. The resulting NheI&#x2013;(EcoRI)&#x2013;NheI fragment was ligated into the XbaI-digested pGL3-promoter. The luciferase reporter plasmid Luc LMP2A 3&#x2032;UTR was generated by PCR-amplification using the primers 5&#x2032;LMP2A Xba 5&#x2032;-GCT CTA GAT CTT GGT TCT CCT GAT TTG CTC TTC-3&#x2032; and 3&#x2032;LMP2A Xba 5&#x2032;-GCT CTA GAC ACT CTC CGT GCC CAA GTG TTC ACC-3&#x2032;. The XbaI-digested PCR product was ligated into the vector pGL3-promoter (Promega, Mannheim, Germany). The BZLF1 expression plasmid p509 (25) was kindly provided by H.-J- Delecluse, DKFZ, Heidelberg. Hela cells cultivated in 10-cm dishes were transfected with 8 &#xB5;g pSG5-miR-BART2 or pSG5-miR-155 using Nanofectin&#xAE; transfection reagent (PAA) as recommended by the manufacturer to examine expression of miRNAs in northern blots. Using Metafectene&#xAE; (Biontex), according to manufacturers specifications, 293-EBV cells were transfected in six-well plates with 1 &#xB5;g plasmid DNA and 0.5 &#xB5;g p509, respectively. Cultivated in 24-well plates, 293-T cells were transfected with 0.2 &#xB5;g pEGFP (Clontech), 0.2 &#xB5;g reporter plasmid and 0.8 &#xB5;g miRNA expressing plasmid using Nanofectin. Transfection efficiency was determined in a FACScan analyser. Luciferase assays were performed as described previously, 48 h after transfection (20). Total RNA was extracted from cells using TriFast Reagent (peQLab) following the vendor's recommendations. Total RNA measuring 100 &#x3BC;g was routinely electrophoresed through 12% urea-polyacrylamide gel and then electroblot-transferred to nylon membrane Hybond XL (Amersham) for 1 h at 2 mA/cm2. The membrane was crosslinked with UV-Stratalinker (Stratagene) at 120 mJ/cm2 and then baked at 80&#xB0;C for 1 h. Blots were hybridized with radioactive labelled antisense probe overnight and then washed twice for 15 min with 5&#xD7; SSC, 1% SDS and twice for 15 min with 1&#xD7; SSC, 1% SDS. As radioactive probes, we used RNA probes labelled with miRVana Probe construction kit (Ambion) according to the manufacturer's instructions. The following antisense probes were used: miR-BART1: 5&#x2032;-gca agg gcg aug aga aaa ua-3&#x2032;, miR-BART2: 5&#x2032;-gca agg gcg aau gca gaa aau a-3&#x2032;, miR-155: 5&#x2032;-ccc cua uca cga uua gca uua a-3&#x2032;. Cleavage substrates that were perfectly complementary to BART2 or miR-19b were in vitro transcribed and 32P-cap labelled as described previously (9). Ago2-containing complexes were immunoprecipitated using anti-Ago2 antibodies coupled to protein G Sepharose and beads were incubated with 5 nM substrate RNA, 1 mM ATP, 0.2 mM GTP, 10 U/ml RNasin (Promega), 100 mM KCl, 1.5 mM MgCl2 and 0.5 mM DTT for 1.5 h at 30&#xB0;C in a total volume of 25 &#xB5;l. RNA was extracted by proteinase K digestion followed by phenol/chloroform treatment and analysed by 8% denaturing RNA&#x2013;PAGE. Radioactive signals were detected by autoradiography. To determine the amount of virus released from 293-EBV cells, supernatants were collected between 24 and 72 h after transfection, DNA was extracted using the QIAmp DNA Blood Mini Kit (Qiagen) according to the manufacturers&#x2019; instructions. Quantitative EBV&#x2013;PCR was performed as hot-start real-time PCR using LightCycler (Roche) as described (26). miR-BART2 down-regulates the BALF5 3&#x2032;UTR. (A) Northern blot detection of ectopically expressed miR-BART2 and miR-155 using the indicated probes. RNA extracted from HeLa cells 48 h after transfection with the vector pSG5-miR-BART2 (lane designated &#x2018;HeLa+miR-BART2&#x2019;) was analysed in parallel with RNA from BL41 and B95.8 cells (EBV-negative and -positive, respectively). Total RNA of HeLa cells either transfected or untransfected with pSG5-mir-155 was analysed by northern blotting for the expression of miR-155. The positions of the precursor and the mature miRNA are indicated. (B) Effect of miR-BART2 on the BALF5 3&#x2032;UTR. miR-BART2 and the Luc-BALF5-3&#x2032;UTR reporter were co-expressed in the indicated combinations. The activity obtained with the reporter alone was set to 100%. Graph B represents the mean values of six independent experiments carried out in duplicate (&#xB1;SEM). (C) miR-BART2 and a luciferase reporter containing the BALF5 3&#x2032;UTR with a deletion of the BART2-recognition site were co-expressed in the indicated combinations and analysed as in (B). (D) Effect of miR-BART2 on the parental (empty) vector pGL3-promoter (&#x2018;Luc&#x2019;). MiR-BART2 and the pGL3-reporter were co-expressed in the indicated combinations. The activity obtained with the reporter alone was set to 100%. The statistical analysis showed an insignificant effect (P = 0.257). (E) miR-BART2 and a luciferase reporter containing the LMP2A 3&#x2032;UTR were co-expressed in the indicated combinations and analysed as in (B). The activity obtained with the reporter alone was set to 100%. (F) Effect of miR-155 on the pGL3-BALF5 3&#x2032;-UTR reporter; the reporter alone was set to 100%. The statistical analysis showed an insignificant effect (P = 0.092). Graphs C, D, E and F represent the mean values of four independent experiments carried out in duplicate (&#xB1;SEM). miR-BART2 down-regulates the BALF5 3&#x2032;UTR. (A) Northern blot detection of ectopically expressed miR-BART2 and miR-155 using the indicated probes. RNA extracted from HeLa cells 48 h after transfection with the vector pSG5-miR-BART2 (lane designated &#x2018;HeLa+miR-BART2&#x2019;) was analysed in parallel with RNA from BL41 and B95.8 cells (EBV-negative and -positive, respectively). Total RNA of HeLa cells either transfected or untransfected with pSG5-mir-155 was analysed by northern blotting for the expression of miR-155. The positions of the precursor and the mature miRNA are indicated. (B) Effect of miR-BART2 on the BALF5 3&#x2032;UTR. miR-BART2 and the Luc-BALF5-3&#x2032;UTR reporter were co-expressed in the indicated combinations. The activity obtained with the reporter alone was set to 100%. Graph B represents the mean values of six independent experiments carried out in duplicate (&#xB1;SEM). (C) miR-BART2 and a luciferase reporter containing the BALF5 3&#x2032;UTR with a deletion of the BART2-recognition site were co-expressed in the indicated combinations and analysed as in (B). (D) Effect of miR-BART2 on the parental (empty) vector pGL3-promoter (&#x2018;Luc&#x2019;). MiR-BART2 and the pGL3-reporter were co-expressed in the indicated combinations. The activity obtained with the reporter alone was set to 100%. The statistical analysis showed an insignificant effect (P = 0.257). (E) miR-BART2 and a luciferase reporter containing the LMP2A 3&#x2032;UTR were co-expressed in the indicated combinations and analysed as in (B). The activity obtained with the reporter alone was set to 100%. (F) Effect of miR-155 on the pGL3-BALF5 3&#x2032;-UTR reporter; the reporter alone was set to 100%. The statistical analysis showed an insignificant effect (P = 0.092). Graphs C, D, E and F represent the mean values of four independent experiments carried out in duplicate (&#xB1;SEM). miR-BART2-directed cleavage of BALF5 mRNA is reduced during lytic replication. (A) Immunoprecipitation analysis of Ago2 using monoclonal antibody 3C7. Extracts of 293-T cells expressing HA-tagged Ago2 were subjected to precipitation using the Ago2-specific rat monoclonal antibody 3C7 (IgG1) or isotype control antibody. Whole-cell extract containing HA-Ago2 was co-electrophoresed in the adjacent lane designated &#x2018;input&#x2019;. After transfer to nitrocellulose membrane, the precipitated Ago2 was visualized using 3C7. The position of rat immunoglobulin heavy and light chains are indicated. Molecular mass marker proteins (&#xD7;10&#x2212;3 kDa) were, in descending order: phosphorylase B, bovine serum albumin, ovalbumin, carboanhydrase. (B) Ago2-mediated cleavage of RNA. Cytoplasmic extracts generated from the indicated cell lines with or without previous TPA treatment were subjected to immunoprecipitation using anti-Ago2 antibodies. Immunoprecipitates were subsequently incubated with 32P-cap-labelled RNAs, which contained perfect complementary sequences to the viral miRNA BART2. The cleaved RNA products were separated by 8% denaturing RNA&#x2013;PAGE. Lanes denoted &#x2018;T1&#x2019; show nuclease T1 digestions of the RNA substrates. (C) Ago-2 mediated cleavage of RNA. Extracts of the indicated cell lines with or without TPA-treatment were compared. The RNA sequences complementary to miR-BART2 or miR-19b are indicated by black bars to both sides. Arrows denote the actual cleavage sites. (D) Detection of miRNA levels during EBV lytic replication. Total RNA from EBV-negative BL41 cells, from type-2 EBV-infected Jijoye cells and from type-1 EBV infected B95.8 cells either treated (+TPA) or not treated (&#x2212;TPA) with tetradecanoylphorbol acetate (TPA), was assayed in a northern blot with the indicated 32P-labelled probes. The loading control (tRNA) is shown below each blot. miR-BART2-directed cleavage of BALF5 mRNA is reduced during lytic replication. (A) Immunoprecipitation analysis of Ago2 using monoclonal antibody 3C7. Extracts of 293-T cells expressing HA-tagged Ago2 were subjected to precipitation using the Ago2-specific rat monoclonal antibody 3C7 (IgG1) or isotype control antibody. Whole-cell extract containing HA-Ago2 was co-electrophoresed in the adjacent lane designated &#x2018;input&#x2019;. After transfer to nitrocellulose membrane, the precipitated Ago2 was visualized using 3C7. The position of rat immunoglobulin heavy and light chains are indicated. Molecular mass marker proteins (&#xD7;10&#x2212;3 kDa) were, in descending order: phosphorylase B, bovine serum albumin, ovalbumin, carboanhydrase. (B) Ago2-mediated cleavage of RNA. Cytoplasmic extracts generated from the indicated cell lines with or without previous TPA treatment were subjected to immunoprecipitation using anti-Ago2 antibodies. Immunoprecipitates were subsequently incubated with 32P-cap-labelled RNAs, which contained perfect complementary sequences to the viral miRNA BART2. The cleaved RNA products were separated by 8% denaturing RNA&#x2013;PAGE. Lanes denoted &#x2018;T1&#x2019; show nuclease T1 digestions of the RNA substrates. (C) Ago-2 mediated cleavage of RNA. Extracts of the indicated cell lines with or without TPA-treatment were compared. The RNA sequences complementary to miR-BART2 or miR-19b are indicated by black bars to both sides. Arrows denote the actual cleavage sites. (D) Detection of miRNA levels during EBV lytic replication. Total RNA from EBV-negative BL41 cells, from type-2 EBV-infected Jijoye cells and from type-1 EBV infected B95.8 cells either treated (+TPA) or not treated (&#x2212;TPA) with tetradecanoylphorbol acetate (TPA), was assayed in a northern blot with the indicated 32P-labelled probes. The loading control (tRNA) is shown below each blot. The reduction in cleavage activity could either be due to inhibition of binding to Ago2 or a reduction in miR-BART2 levels. To test for the latter we analysed miRNA expression by northern blotting. The blot obtained using a 32P-labelled probe for miR-BART2 is shown in Figure 3D, left panel, and was quantified using a PhosphoImager. The amount of the miR-BART2 in Jijoye and B95.8 cells was reduced upon TPA treatment by 33% and 36%, respectively and no miR-BART2 signal was seen in EBV-negative BL41 cells; the induction of the lytic replication was verified by the up-regulation of the BZLF1 protein (Figure 5A). We also observed a reduction for the viral miR-BART1 (27% in Jijoye and 27% in B95.8 cells, Figure 3D, right panel) but an increase for the cellular miR-155 by 75%, in Jijoye, 96%, in B95.8 and 360% in BL41 cells after treatment with TPA (Figure 3D, middle panel). The amount of cellular miR-19b after TPA treatment was separately determined for induced and untreated B95.8 cells and we observed a slight decrease after TPA administration (data not shown). Such a TPA-induced decrease for miR-19b and an increase for miR-155 was described for the EBV-negative myeloid HL60 cells (29). In summary, miR-BART2 associates with Ago2 and guides the sequence-specific cleavage of the BALF5 mRNA. Upon induction of the lytic cycle, miR-BART2 expression is down-regulated resulting in reduced cleavage of BALF5 mRNA. Reduced repression (&#x2018;De-repression&#x2019;) of the BALF5-3&#x2032;UTR during lytic cycle replication. The pGL3 vector containing the BALF5-3&#x2032;UTR (A) or the reporter with the mutated BALF5-3&#x2032;UTR (B) were transfected alone or with the p509 vector encoding the lytic activator BZLF1 into 293-EBV cells. The luciferase activities observed without p509 were set to 100%. Activation of Luc-BALF5-3&#x2032;UTR with p509 was 7.7-fold (P = 0.003); activation for pGL3 with the mutated binding site was 1.6-fold (P = 0.07). Graphs represent the mean value of four (A) or rather eight (B) independent assays carried out in duplicate (&#xB1;SEM). Reduced repression (&#x2018;De-repression&#x2019;) of the BALF5-3&#x2032;UTR during lytic cycle replication. The pGL3 vector containing the BALF5-3&#x2032;UTR (A) or the reporter with the mutated BALF5-3&#x2032;UTR (B) were transfected alone or with the p509 vector encoding the lytic activator BZLF1 into 293-EBV cells. The luciferase activities observed without p509 were set to 100%. Activation of Luc-BALF5-3&#x2032;UTR with p509 was 7.7-fold (P = 0.003); activation for pGL3 with the mutated binding site was 1.6-fold (P = 0.07). Graphs represent the mean value of four (A) or rather eight (B) independent assays carried out in duplicate (&#xB1;SEM). miR-BART2 down-regulates BALF5 polymerase. (A) Identification of BALF5 protein using the monoclonal antibody 4C12. Whole-cell extracts of B95.8 B-cells either treated (+) or untreated (&#x2212;) with TPA were analysed by western blotting as shown in the left panel. The blots were stained with the novel BALF5-specific antibody 4C12, an antibody directed against &#x3B2;-actin as a loading control and BZLF1-specific monoclonal antibody BZ-1 to verify the induction of EBV lytic replication. Detection of BALF5 in EBV-infected 293 cells without (&#x2013;) and after (+) induction of lytic replication by BZLF1 using the vector p509 (18) is shown in the right panel. (B) Immunoprecipitation of BALF5. Extract of TPA-treated Raji cells was incubated either with BALF5-specific antibody 4C12 or irrelevant isotype control as indicated. Immune complexes were collected using protein G Sepharose (Amersham-Pharmacia). The precipitated BALF5 protein was analysed in a western blot using 4C12 as primary antibody; bound antibody was visualized by the ECL method; the lanes designated &#x2018;Raji&#x2019;, shows whole-cell extract prior to precipitation. (C) Reduction of BALF5 protein levels by miR-BART2. 293-EBV cells were transfected with BZLF1 expression vector p509 in combination with miR-BART2 expression vector or pSG5 control. BALF5 protein was stained using the monoclonal antibody 4C12, &#x3B2;-actin served as a loading control (left panel); statistical analysis of the BALF5 protein reduction by miR-BART2. The amount of BALF5 protein with or without BART2 expression from three independent assays as shown in (C) was determined and statistically analysed. The reduction of 30&#x2013;40% after co-expression of miR-BART2 was statistically significant (right panel; P = 0.0037). (D) Reduction in virus load by miR-BART2. Viral replication in 293-EBV cells was induced by expression of BZLF1 using the vector p509. The amount of virus released was determined by quantitative real-time PCR. The value obtained by co-transfection of the empty control vector pSG5 was set to 100%. Co-expression of miR-BART2 resulted in a statistically significant reduction of the virus load by 20% (P = 0.039), co-expression of miR-155 resulted in a non-significant reduction by 5&#x2013;10% (P = 0.155). miR-BART2 down-regulates BALF5 polymerase. (A) Identification of BALF5 protein using the monoclonal antibody 4C12. Whole-cell extracts of B95.8 B-cells either treated (+) or untreated (&#x2212;) with TPA were analysed by western blotting as shown in the left panel. The blots were stained with the novel BALF5-specific antibody 4C12, an antibody directed against &#x3B2;-actin as a loading control and BZLF1-specific monoclonal antibody BZ-1 to verify the induction of EBV lytic replication. Detection of BALF5 in EBV-infected 293 cells without (&#x2013;) and after (+) induction of lytic replication by BZLF1 using the vector p509 (18) is shown in the right panel. (B) Immunoprecipitation of BALF5. Extract of TPA-treated Raji cells was incubated either with BALF5-specific antibody 4C12 or irrelevant isotype control as indicated. Immune complexes were collected using protein G Sepharose (Amersham-Pharmacia). The precipitated BALF5 protein was analysed in a western blot using 4C12 as primary antibody; bound antibody was visualized by the ECL method; the lanes designated &#x2018;Raji&#x2019;, shows whole-cell extract prior to precipitation. (C) Reduction of BALF5 protein levels by miR-BART2. 293-EBV cells were transfected with BZLF1 expression vector p509 in combination with miR-BART2 expression vector or pSG5 control. BALF5 protein was stained using the monoclonal antibody 4C12, &#x3B2;-actin served as a loading control (left panel); statistical analysis of the BALF5 protein reduction by miR-BART2. The amount of BALF5 protein with or without BART2 expression from three independent assays as shown in (C) was determined and statistically analysed. The reduction of 30&#x2013;40% after co-expression of miR-BART2 was statistically significant (right panel; P = 0.0037). (D) Reduction in virus load by miR-BART2. Viral replication in 293-EBV cells was induced by expression of BZLF1 using the vector p509. The amount of virus released was determined by quantitative real-time PCR. The value obtained by co-transfection of the empty control vector pSG5 was set to 100%. Co-expression of miR-BART2 resulted in a statistically significant reduction of the virus load by 20% (P = 0.039), co-expression of miR-155 resulted in a non-significant reduction by 5&#x2013;10% (P = 0.155). A hallmark of the infection of Herpes viruses is the persistence of the viruses in the infected host and it may be speculated that the viral miRNAs function to establish and maintain latency. The HSV-1 miRNA designated miR-LAT is found in latently infected cells and represses the TGF-&#x3B2;-mediated apoptosis after infection (30). In the case of MHV-68, a deletion at the 5&#x2032;-end of the viral genome including the miRNA genes resulted in a reduced capacity for persistent infection (31). However, as the deletion(s) also included protein-encoding genes, it is unclear whether this effect is due to the loss of the miRNA. Marek's disease virus, an oncogenic Herpes virus infecting chicken, encodes eight miRNAs expressed in latently infected, transformed cells. Three of these miRNAs are antisense to the immediate early gene ICP4 and probably down-modulate this gene product to inhibit entry into the lytic cycle (32). The data presented in this report indicate that at least one of the EBV-encoded miRNAs might have a function in the viral life cycle. Our results are compatible with the notion that the miR-BART2 serves as an inhibitor of viral DNA replication through degradation of the mRNA for the viral DNA polymerase BALF5. MiR-BART2 is only expressed at very low levels during latent infection and we therefore assume that this particular miRNA serves to inhibit aberrantly transcribed BALF5 mRNA to ensure that the viral replication is not inadvertently induced. Accordingly, we only observed a modest reduction of virus production upon forced expression of miR-BART2. We also noticed that the reduction of cleavage activity after TPA-induction was much stronger than the reduction in miR-BART2 levels; it might be possible that the virus employs additional factors that interfere with Ago-2-mediated cleavage. In addition to miR-BART2, we found that both the precursor and the mature miR-BART1 were also down-regulated upon lytic cycle induction. In conjunction with a previous report (16), which shows that the mature EBV-encoded miR-BHRF1-1 and -2 are down-regulated upon TPA induction of the two EBV-infected BL cell lines Daudi and Mutu I, we speculate that additional virus-encoded miRNAs may play a role in repression of the lytic replication cycle. We are presently analysing the possibility that the other EBV&#x2013;miRNAs target distinct viral or cellular genes involved in regulation of viral replication.
</content>
</document>
