<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <id>2241864</id>
  <title>Interplay of ion binding and attraction in DNA condensed by multivalent cations
</title>
  <abstract>
 We have measured forces generated by multivalent cation-induced DNA condensation using single-molecule magnetic tweezers. In the presence of cobalt hexammine, spermidine, or spermine, stretched DNA exhibits an abrupt configurational change from extended to condensed. This occurs at a well-defined condensation force that is nearly equal to the condensation free energy per unit length. The multivalent cation concentration dependence for this condensation force gives the apparent number of multivalent cations that bind DNA upon condensation. The measurements show that the lower critical concentration for cobalt hexammine as compared to spermidine is due to a difference in ion binding, not a difference in the electrostatic energy of the condensed state as previously thought. We also show that the resolubilization of condensed DNA can be described using a traditional Manning&#x2013;Oosawa cation adsorption model, provided that cation&#x2013;anion pairing at high electrolyte concentrations is taken into account. Neither overcharging nor significant alterations in the condensed state are required to describe the resolubilization of condensed DNA. The same model also describes the spermidine3+/Na+ phase diagram measured previously.
</abstract>
  <content>
 Interactions between DNA and mobile cations, such as Na+, Mg2+ and spermidine3+, play a critical role in DNA physical properties and biological function. Even in dilute solutions of relatively weakly associating monovalent cations, such as Na+ and K+, approximately three out of four DNA charges are neutralized by a cation that is in some sense &#x2018;bound&#x2019; (1,2). This neutralization facilitates compaction of DNA into the densely packaged genomes of viruses (3) and cells (4) and deformation of DNA by proteins (5). Interactions between DNA and monovalent cations seem to be well described by traditional models for polyelectrolyte&#x2013;counterion interactions, such as Manning&#x2013;Oosawa theory (6) and the Poisson&#x2013;Boltzmann equation (7). These theories ignore the interactions among cations and the discrete nature of DNA and counterion charges. In solutions containing only one type of counterion, both theories predict a nearly concentration-independent fraction of DNA charge neutralized. For competitive binding between multiple cations, the binding of each ionic species can be described by a simple adsorption isotherm characterized by an ion- and electrolyte-dependent equilibrium constant (6). DNA in solutions of tri- and higher-valent cations, such as cobalt hexammine3+ and spermine4+, show a peculiar phase behavior not expected for the traditional theories (8&#x2013;18). DNA initially precipitates at low concentrations of the polyvalent cation and then &#x2018;resolubilizes&#x2019; at high concentration, indicating either decreased neutralization of DNA at elevated concentrations or overcompensation of DNA charge. This deviation from classic adsorption isotherm behavior indicates violations in the basic assumptions in the traditional theories and has been attributed to various causes including correlations between counterions (15,16), increased electrolyte screening (13) and non-ideal polycation&#x2013;anion pairing at elevated electrolyte concentrations (8,19,20). Here, we investigate the interactions between polyvalent cations and DNA using single-molecule magnetic tweezers. The measurements extend the existing, mostly structural, data on condensed DNA (21&#x2013;25) by providing the free energy of condensation across the entire range of condensing conditions. We are able to determine the number of cations associated with DNA by thermodynamic analysis of the electrolyte dependence of condensation free energies. The analysis resolves a subtle increase in the binding of cobalt hexammine3+ to DNA as compared to spermidine3+ that could not be seen in previous bulk measurements (26,27). The observation of increased binding of Co(NH3)63+ to DNA reverses the long-held assumption that Co(NH3)63+ condenses DNA at a lower fractional neutralization than spermidine3+ (28,29). The energetic consequences of these differences in binding are significant and can account for the different phase behavior observed for the two ions. We model the resolubilization of condensed DNA using a traditional Manning&#x2013;Oosawa cation adsorption model (6). We show that, if ion pairing at high electrolyte concentrations is included, this traditional model can describe resolubilization. Neither overcharging nor electrolyte screening is necessary to describe resolubilization. The same model also describes the spermidine3+/Na+ phase diagram previously measured by Raspaud et al. (9). Magnetic tweezing of condensed DNA will be described in more detail in a forthcoming paper (30). Briefly, &#x3BB;-DNA with multiple biotins at 3&#x2032; and 5&#x2032; ends was suspended between a fixed 5 &#x3BC;m streptavidin-coated latex bead and a 2.8 &#x3BC;m streptavidin-coated superparamagnetic bead. The stretching force on the DNA was controlled via a micrometer-positioned magnet placed next to a microscope. Condensation forces were measured by stretching the DNA to forces &gt;10 pN, introducing a condensing agent, and then slowly decreasing the force at 0.1 pN/min until it was less than the attractive force of condensation. Condensation was easily observed from the decrease in the stretched length of the DNA from &gt;14 &#x3BC;m to &lt;1 &#x3BC;m. Condensation forces were insensitive to a 2&#xD7; change in the unloading rate. All measurements were done in solutions containing a background of 10 mM Tris buffer (pH 7.5). We assume throughout an 8 mM monovalent cation concentration, corresponding to &#x223C;80% protonation of Tris. High molecular weight DNA prepared from chicken blood was precipitated with spermidine3+/Co(NH3)63+ mixtures. The DNA samples (&#x223C;200 &#x3BC;g) in screw top Eppendorf tubes were centrifuged at 15 000g for 20 min and the buffer removed. The DNA pellets were removed using a glass capillary and transferred to weighing paper. The condensed DNA was gently blotted with lens paper to remove excess buffer. The pellets were transferred back to Eppendorf tubes and dissolved in 1 ml of 1 M NaCl, 10 mM TrisCl (pH 7.5). The absorbance at 475 nm was used to determine the Co(NH3)63+ concentration from an extinction coefficient of 0.056/cm mM. Samples were diluted by 100-fold into 10 mM Tris&#x2013;Cl (pH 7.5), 1 mM EDTA and the absorbance at 260 nm used to determine the DNA concentration from a standard extinction coefficient of 6.7/cm mM DNA-phosphate. Measuring a condensation force in Co(NH3)6Cl3. A single &#x3BB;-DNA double helix is stretched between an immobilized bead (large bead on the left) and a bead susceptible to a magnetic force pulling to the right. Bathed in a solution containing the multivalent cation, the DNA is initially stretched by a relatively large force, f &gt; &#x2212; &#x394; &#x11C;. The force is decreased at 0.1 pN/min and the distance between the beads, x, is monitored. Prior to condensation, the force-distance dependence is well characterized by the worm-like chain model (dashed line). At the condensation force, f &#x223C; &#x2212; &#x394; &#x11C;, the bead-bead separation abruptly decreases. Within minutes, condensation of DNA reaches completion, f &lt; &#x2212; &#x394; &#x11C;, bringing the magnetic bead nearly into contact with the fixed bead. If the unloading rate was increased to 1&#x2013;7 pN/min (dashed lines, right-hand plot), the condensation force became stochastic and decreased with increasing unloading rate. This indicates the onset of kinetic effects seen previously (18,32&#x2013;34). Measuring a condensation force in Co(NH3)6Cl3. A single &#x3BB;-DNA double helix is stretched between an immobilized bead (large bead on the left) and a bead susceptible to a magnetic force pulling to the right. Bathed in a solution containing the multivalent cation, the DNA is initially stretched by a relatively large force, f &gt; &#x2212; &#x394; &#x11C;. The force is decreased at 0.1 pN/min and the distance between the beads, x, is monitored. Prior to condensation, the force-distance dependence is well characterized by the worm-like chain model (dashed line). At the condensation force, f &#x223C; &#x2212; &#x394; &#x11C;, the bead-bead separation abruptly decreases. Within minutes, condensation of DNA reaches completion, f &lt; &#x2212; &#x394; &#x11C;, bringing the magnetic bead nearly into contact with the fixed bead. If the unloading rate was increased to 1&#x2013;7 pN/min (dashed lines, right-hand plot), the condensation force became stochastic and decreased with increasing unloading rate. This indicates the onset of kinetic effects seen previously (18,32&#x2013;34). At this unloading rate of 0.1 pN/min, the condensation forces were insensitive to a 2&#xD7; increase in unloading rate and condensation of the entire molecule occurred over a narrow, 0.1&#x2013;0.2 pN, range of force (Figure 1, solid line). This rate independence indicates that, at 0.1 pN/min, the condensation process occurs under quasi-static, equilibrium conditions. Increases in the unloading rate to 1&#x2013;7 pN/min (Figure 1, dashed lines), progressively decreased the condensation force and introduced a stochastic character. This is similar to the nonequilibrium effects described previously for unloading rates between 1.5 and 5 pN/min (18,32&#x2013;34). Also similar to previous measurements (18,34), we observed that the reverse process (&#x2018;decondensation&#x2019;) was rate dependent and required rupture forces of &#x223C;10 pN, even at loading rates of 0.1 pN/min. This indicates that the kinetics of decondensation are exceptionally slow and that the equilibrium condition for decondensation has not yet been reached at 0.1 pN/min. All of the forces analyzed here are for the equilibrium condensation process measured at an unloading rate of 0.1 pN/min. Condensation force as a function of multivalent cation concentration for Co(NH3)6Cl3 (a), spermidine trichloride (b) and spermine tetrachloride (c). For each, the condensing force is seen to rise from the critical concentration at low concentration, reaching a peak at intermediate concentration, and then decreasing toward the resolubilization point at high concentration. Where data is available, we have compared our measurement with previous bulk measurements of the critical (filled arrows) and resolubilization concentrations (open arrows). Co(NH3)6Cl3 data taken from Matulis et al., spermidine data from Raspaud et al. and spermine data extrapolated from Raspaud et al. (9,24,29). The zero crossings in our measurements clearly correspond to the borders of the phase diagram measured in the bulk. Condensation force as a function of multivalent cation concentration for Co(NH3)6Cl3 (a), spermidine trichloride (b) and spermine tetrachloride (c). For each, the condensing force is seen to rise from the critical concentration at low concentration, reaching a peak at intermediate concentration, and then decreasing toward the resolubilization point at high concentration. Where data is available, we have compared our measurement with previous bulk measurements of the critical (filled arrows) and resolubilization concentrations (open arrows). Co(NH3)6Cl3 data taken from Matulis et al., spermidine data from Raspaud et al. and spermine data extrapolated from Raspaud et al. (9,24,29). The zero crossings in our measurements clearly correspond to the borders of the phase diagram measured in the bulk. This result was expected because, at sufficiently slow loading rates, the condensation force is nearly equal to the condensation free energy per unit length (31,32). This can be understood by considering that condensation in the presence of a stretching force is governed by a balance between the favorable (negative) condensation free energy gained by compacting the DNA and the unfavorable (positive) work required to translate the bead against the magnetic force. Spontaneous condensation occurs when the sum of these components is just less than zero, i.e. the applied force is just smaller than the condensation free energy per unit length, &#x394; &#x11C; &#x223C; &#x2212; f. At low stretching forces, a bit more accuracy can be achieved by noting that, because the DNA is not completely stretched, the contour length of DNA incorporated into the condensate, L, can be somewhat larger than the distance over which work is done on the bead, &#x394;X. This gives a slight correction to the free energy, &#x394; &#x11C; = &#x2212; &#x394; xf, where &#x394;x = &#x394;X/L can vary between 0 and 1. DNA is &gt;85% stretched for forces &gt;1 pN however, so for most of the forces of interest this contributes a correction of &lt;15%. Nevertheless, we apply this small correction throughout. The sensitivity of the condensation free energy to multivalent cation concentration for Co(NH3)6Cl3 (red) and spermidine trichloride (blue). At low concentrations, where dissociation of the trivalent cation is complete this equals the change in number of bound trivalent cations accompanying condensation. At their respective critical points, Co(NH3)63+ requires binding of 0.01 fewer ion/phosphate than spermidine. Around the critical point, the spermidine curve (blue) is well modeled by Manning&#x2013;Oosawa counterion association for the competition between the +3 ion and the monovalent Tris buffer (dashed line). At higher concentrations, the experimentally measured sensitivities decrease and become negative. This can be understood as the competition between the +3 form of each multivalent cation and its +2, chloride associated form. The solid line is calculated using a previously estimated equilibrium constant of 0.15 M for the spermidine to spermidine&#x2013;chloride association and Manning&#x2013;Oosawa theory. This models contains no free parameters. The sensitivity of the condensation free energy to multivalent cation concentration for Co(NH3)6Cl3 (red) and spermidine trichloride (blue). At low concentrations, where dissociation of the trivalent cation is complete this equals the change in number of bound trivalent cations accompanying condensation. At their respective critical points, Co(NH3)63+ requires binding of 0.01 fewer ion/phosphate than spermidine. Around the critical point, the spermidine curve (blue) is well modeled by Manning&#x2013;Oosawa counterion association for the competition between the +3 ion and the monovalent Tris buffer (dashed line). At higher concentrations, the experimentally measured sensitivities decrease and become negative. This can be understood as the competition between the +3 form of each multivalent cation and its +2, chloride associated form. The solid line is calculated using a previously estimated equilibrium constant of 0.15 M for the spermidine to spermidine&#x2013;chloride association and Manning&#x2013;Oosawa theory. This models contains no free parameters. We will postpone analysis of the higher concentrations until the Discussion section. For now, we restrict ourselves to the trivalent cations, Co(NH3)63+ and spermidine3+, and to the dilute regime near the low concentration critical points. In this case, ions are fully dissociated and the apparent change in bound cations is equal to the change in trivalent cations, &#x394; n = &#x394; n3+ (Appendix A). The number of additional ions that must bind for Co(NH3)63+ to condense DNA (red) is less than for spermidine (blue) (see that red is lower than blue at low concentrations in Figure 3). This occurs despite the lower critical concentration for Co(NH3)63+. The critical concentrations, Ccrit, and change in number of bound ions at the critical point, &#x394;ncrit, are 4.1 &#xD7; 10&#x2212;5 M and 0.028 per phosphate for Co(NH3)63+ and 1.8 &#xD7; 10&#x2212;4 M and 0.038 per phosphate for spermidine. From &#x394;ncrit, Ccrit, and an estimate of the local concentration of trivalent cations bound to DNA, Cb = 0.2 M (1), we can estimate the free energy cost to bind the additional multivalent cations at the critical point,2The free energy costs for Co(NH3)63+ and spermidine are identical within the &#x223C;10% precision for the measured &#x394;ncrit and are equal to &#x223C;0.25 kbT/phosphate. This indicates that the &#x223C;0.01 ion bound per phosphate decrease in &#x394;ncrit for Co(NH3)63+ compensates for the increased energetic cost per ion at the more dilute critical concentration. This subtle but measurable difference in ion binding accounts for the lower critical concentration of Co(NH3)63+ as compared to spermidine. For both Co(NH3)63+ and spermidine, this unfavorable energy required to binding +3 ions is balanced by identical free energies of DNA-DNA interactions and Tris1+ release (30). We sought to quantify the differences in ion binding in terms of binding constants. Because &#x394; n3 + represents a difference between cations bound to the condensed and extended DNA, it is unclear in which phase binding differs between Co(NH3)63+ and spermidine3+. We assume that the condensed phase is neutralized by both spermidine and Co(NH3)63+ and that the difference lies with the fraction bound to the extended phase, &#x3B8; 3 + = (1/3) &#x2212; &#x394; n3 +. This choice is consistent with the insensitivity of osmotic stress curves of counterion condensed DNA to condensing ion concentration (25,30), with small surface potentials measured in electrophoresis of condensed DNA (10,18), and with spectroscopic measurements that we will present below. We extract binding constants from Scatchard plots of the concentration dependence of &#x3B8; 3 + in a manner identical to previous measurements (26,27) and estimated the binding constant uncertainties defined by a 90% confidence interval. The binding constant for Co(NH3)63+ is 3-fold larger than that for spermidine (Kspermidine = 0.6 &#xB1; 0.3 &#x3BC; M &#x2212; 1). Competitive DNA binding between Co(NH3)63+ and spermidine. The Co(NH3)63+ concentration relative to the DNA phosphate concentration, , is measured as a function of the spermidine concentration, Cspermidine. A fit of Equation (4) to the data gives relative binding constants,  (line). Competitive DNA binding between Co(NH3)63+ and spermidine. The Co(NH3)63+ concentration relative to the DNA phosphate concentration, , is measured as a function of the spermidine concentration, Cspermidine. A fit of Equation (4) to the data gives relative binding constants,  (line). Our results highlight the remarkably large effect that small alterations in ion-binding constants can have on DNA condensation. The 0.01 ion/phosphate decrease in Co(NH3)63+ required to condense DNA fully accounts for the &#x223C;4-fold decrease in critical concentration, as compared to spermidine; decreasing the number of neutralizing ions required to condense DNA allows Co(NH3)63+ to condense at a higher cost of mixing entropy per ion. It was previously thought that the more compact charge of Co(NH3)63+ facilitated stronger, more correlated DNA&#x2013;DNA electrostatic interactions (16,29,35). However, recent measurements by magnetic tweezers showed that the free energy of direct DNA&#x2013;DNA interactions for Co(NH3)63+ and spermidine condensed DNA are equal (30). Our measurements explain how Co(NH3)63+ can condense DNA at a lower critical concentration while facilitating the same direct DNA&#x2013;DNA interactions. Comparing our measured DNA association constants for Co(NH3)63+ (red circle) and spermidine (blue triangle) with previous equilibrium dialysis measurements (red triangles for Co(NH3)63+ and blue &#x2018;+&#x2019; for spermidine). The current measurements are consistent with extrapolations from the previous measurements (red and blue lines) within experimental error (shaded regions). Comparing our measured DNA association constants for Co(NH3)63+ (red circle) and spermidine (blue triangle) with previous equilibrium dialysis measurements (red triangles for Co(NH3)63+ and blue &#x2018;+&#x2019; for spermidine). The current measurements are consistent with extrapolations from the previous measurements (red and blue lines) within experimental error (shaded regions). The physical mechanisms responsible for this difference in ion binding are unknown. However, the difference in ion binding that we measure is similar to NMR measurements of a concentration insensitive, 0.02 ion/phosphate population of 59Co(NH3)63+ tightly bound to extended DNA (36,37). This excess is of the right sign and magnitude to account for the difference in our measurements. This fraction was previously correlated to the fraction of stacked guanine&#x2013;guanine pairs in DNA and thought to be related to a hydrogen bonded bridge that Co(NH3)63+ forms between neighboring guanines (36,37). Additionally, at high fractions of bound +3 ions, it should be easier to bind compact Co(NH3)63+ that sterically occludes perhaps one base pair compared with extended spermidine3+ that could span &#x223C;3 base pairs. Whatever the precise mechanism, the consistent interpretation of our results at high cation-binding densities and the equilibrium dialysis measurements at low binding densities highlights the effectiveness of simple binding constants for characterizing DNA&#x2013;cation interactions over a large range of electrolyte conditions. Modeling the electrolyte concentration dependence of the condensation free energy. We assume that the variations in free energy are due solely to the changes in free energy associated with binding counterions upon condensation, neglecting any changes to the condensed state itself. The number of counterions bound to the extended DNA (left side), &#x3B8;i, are calculated using Manning&#x2013;Oosawa counterion association theory. The condensed DNA (right side) is assumed to be completely and exclusively neutralized by the trivalent cation. Modeling the electrolyte concentration dependence of the condensation free energy. We assume that the variations in free energy are due solely to the changes in free energy associated with binding counterions upon condensation, neglecting any changes to the condensed state itself. The number of counterions bound to the extended DNA (left side), &#x3B8;i, are calculated using Manning&#x2013;Oosawa counterion association theory. The condensed DNA (right side) is assumed to be completely and exclusively neutralized by the trivalent cation. We first naively assume that the Co(NH3)6Cl3 and spermidine trichloride salt fully dissociate, so that, the apparent change in number of ions bound, &#x394;n is equal to the change in number of trivalent ions bound &#x394; n3 + (Appendix A). Plotted as the dashed line in Figure 3, &#x394; n3 + overlaps the spermidine data at low concentrations where dissociation of the salt is expected to be complete. At higher concentrations, the model plateaus out, indicating saturation of the +3 ion at &#x3B8; 3 + &#x223C; 0.30. Deviations of DNA condensation data from this classic adsorption isotherm behavior have attracted considerable attention and have been referred to as &#x2018;resolubilization&#x2019; or &#x2018;reentrant transition&#x2019;. This behavior whereby DNA first precipitates at low concentration of multivalent cations and later &#x2018;resolubilizes&#x2019; at higher concentrations (8&#x2013;12,18) is also seen in other polyelectrolyte systems (10,13,39) and is thought to represent a fundamental new physics not captured by the conventional saturating adsorption isotherm (6). This has motivated development of new theories for polyelectrolyte&#x2013;ion interactions (13&#x2013;17). Alternatively, Solis and Olvera de la Cruz (19,20) and, independently, Yang and Rau (8) have noted that resolubilization occurs at concentrations where a significant fraction of 3+ ions associate with anions to form a 2+-valent anion-paired form. From this point-of-view, the DNA condensate falls apart due to increased competition between the 2+ and 3+ forms at high concentrations. The Cl&#x2212; dissociation constant has been measured for Co(NH3)6+3 as 0.02 M (40,41) and has been estimated for spermidine+3 as 0.15 M (8), indicating significant quantities of 2+-valent forms at concentrations approximately &gt;0.01 M. That this sort of ion-pairing occurs should not be surprising given that Co(NH3)6Cl3 is insoluble beyond &#x223C;0.4 M. Typical resolubilization experiments, similar to the current measurements, approach the solubility limit of the multivalent cation where ion behavior is highly nonideal. Ion pairing can be incorporated into our model in a straightforward way. Using the estimated dissociation constant for spermidine&#x2013;Cl+2, for instance, we simply calculate the relative populations of fully dissociated 3+-valent and partially dissociated 2+-valent ions. Based on these concentrations, Manning&#x2013;Oosawa theory is used to calculate the fraction of 3+ and 2+ ions bound to the extended DNA. The apparent change in the number of bound ions now includes contributions from each of these two populations. For this case, the Gibbs&#x2013;Duhem equation gives (Appendix B),5The apparent &#x394;n is now the weighted sum from each ion form produced by addition of the trichloride salt. This behavior, shown as the solid line in Figure 3, gives a reasonable description of the data across the entire range of multivalent cation concentrations with no fitting parameters. The negative slope of the force versus concentration curve indicates replacement of bound 2+-ions with 3+-ions as DNA condenses; ion pairing accounts for the resolubilization observed in the magnetic tweezers data. This peculiar behavior appears to be more likely a consequence of multivalent cation chemistry than new polyelectrolyte physics. Modeling the spermidine3+/Na+ phase diagram, as measured by Raspaud et al. (circles). The same model used to describe the multivalent cation concentration dependence of the condensation free energy in Figure 3 also describes the trivalent/monovalent cation phase boundaries (line). This model contains no free parameters. Modeling the spermidine3+/Na+ phase diagram, as measured by Raspaud et al. (circles). The same model used to describe the multivalent cation concentration dependence of the condensation free energy in Figure 3 also describes the trivalent/monovalent cation phase boundaries (line). This model contains no free parameters. It is remarkable that nowhere in our analysis have we considered alterations in the DNA&#x2013;DNA attractive interactions, taking into account only the changes in free energy associated with binding neutralizing cations. Yet, variations in the free energy with spermidine concentration, and also, the location of phase boundaries are well described without any free parameters. This suggests that, although interhelical interactions between condensed DNA show some dependence on electrolyte concentration (8,24), the energetic consequences of this variation are small compared to the energetic cost of binding neutralizing multivalent cations. Since ion-binding energies dominate the electrolyte dependence of DNA condensation, it would be difficult to use the electrolyte dependence of DNA condensation to elucidate the mechanism of DNA&#x2013;DNA attraction. Any, relatively small, contribution from the electrolyte dependence of DNA&#x2013;DNA attractions could be incorporated as a correction to our model to improve the agreement with experimental data. In contrast to the traditional assumption that DNA condensation produces a change in number of bound counterions that is larger for Co(NH3)63+ than for spermidine3+ (28,29), our measurements show that the change in bound counterions is actually smaller for Co(NH3)63+ than for spermidine. This decrease in the number of ions required to bind upon condensation allows Co(NH3)63+ to affect condensation at a lower critical concentration. The traditional Manning&#x2013;Oosawa counterion adsorption model could describe variations in the condensation force near the critical points in the dilute regime. Variations in condensation force over the entire range of concentrations and the spermidine3+/Na+ phase diagram of Raspaud et al. (9) could be described by the same model, if the counterion&#x2013;anion pairing that occurs at high concentrations was included. In short, provided that counterion chemistry is treated properly, the traditional Manning&#x2013;Oosawa adsorption isotherm appears capable of predicting the counterion concentration dependence for DNA condensation without invoking overcharging or any changes in the condensed state via, for instance, electrolyte screening.
</content>
</document>
