<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <id>2241903</id>
  <title>Mutation adjacent to the active site tyrosine can enhance DNA cleavage and cell killing by the TOPRIM Gly to Ser mutant of bacterial topoisomerase I
</title>
  <abstract>
 The TOPRIM DXDXXG residues of type IA and II topoisomerases are involved in Mg(II) binding and the cleavage-rejoining of DNA. Mutation of the strictly conserved glycine to serine in Yersinia pestis and Escherichia coli topoisomerase I results in bacterial cell killing due to inhibition of DNA religation after DNA cleavage. In this study, all other substitutions at the TOPRIM glycine of Y. pestis topoisomerase I were examined. While the Gly to Ala substitution allowed both DNA cleavage and religation, other mutations abolished DNA cleavage. DNA cleavage activity retained by the Gly to Ser mutant could be significantly enhanced by a second mutation of the methionine residue adjacent to the active site tyrosine. Induction of mutant topoisomerase with both the TOPRIM glycine and active site region methionine mutations resulted in up to 40-fold higher cell killing rate when compared with the single TOPRIM Gly to Ser mutant. Bacterial type IA topoisomerases are potential targets for discovery of novel antibiotics. These results suggest that compounds that interact simultaneously with the TOPRIM motif and the molecular surface around the active site tyrosine could be highly efficient topoisomerase poisons through both enhancement of DNA cleavage and inhibition of DNA rejoining.
</abstract>
  <content>
 DNA topoisomerases can carry out the important functions of DNA supercoiling regulation and DNA untangling because these enzymes can catalyze the interconversion of DNA topological forms by the concerted breaking and rejoining of DNA strands coupled to DNA strand passage through the DNA cleavage sites (1&#x2013;4). A covalent enzyme&#x2013;DNA complex is formed after nucleophilic attack of an active site tyrosine on the DNA phophodiester backbone during the DNA cleavage step. Topoisomerase poisons are compounds that interfere with the DNA cleavage-rejoining equilibrium of topoisomerases and increase the physiological concentration or life-time of the covalent complex intermediates formed between topoisomerases and cleaved DNA, resulting in events that lead to cell death (5,6). Many clinically important antibacterial and anticancer drugs are topoisomerase poisons targeting type IB and type IIA topoisomerases (5&#x2013;10). Both type IA and type IB topoisomerases cut and rejoin a single-strand of DNA during catalysis but type IA topoisomerases are more similar to type IIA topoisomerases in catalytic mechanism of DNA cleavage and rejoining (3). Based on genome sequences and genetic studies, there is at least one type IA topoisomerase activity required to be present in every organism to resolve entanglement of single-stranded DNA during replication or recombination (2,11). Although topoisomerase poison known to target type IA topoisomerase with high specificity is not available currently, it has been demonstrated that trapping of covalent complex intermediate formed by a mutant form of recombinant Yersinia pestis or Escherichia coli topoisomerase I can result in rapid and extensive cell killing in E. coli (12). This cell killing effect from the stabilization of topoisomerase I cleavage complex validates the potential of bacterial type IA topoisomerase as a target for development of novel antibacterial compounds to combat multi-drug resistant bacterial pathogens (12&#x2013;14). The cell killing mutation previously characterized was identified by screening a random recombinant Y. pestis topoisomerase I mutant library for induction of cellular SOS response in E. coli, and involves change of the strictly conserved Gly residue in the TOPRIM motif (DXDXXG) to a Ser residue (12). The understanding of how DNA cleavage-rejoining can be interfered with at the molecular level is important for the elucidation of how the enzyme maintains the DNA cleavage-rejoining equilibrium so that the degree of DNA cleavage is sufficient for the required conversion of DNA topology, but avoids toxic level of cleaved DNA complex being accumulated. Such biochemical investigations could also be useful for the design of novel type IA topoisomerase poisons or modification of hit molecules identified via high through-put screening in the development of antibacterial compounds targeting type IA topoisomerases (13,14). In this study, it is shown that the TOPRIM Gly to Ser mutation in subdomain I is unique in its cell killing capability among all other possible substitutions at the conserved Gly residue because it maintains a sufficient level of DNA cleavage activity while DNA religation is abolished. All other possible amino acid substitutions at the conserved glycine residue of the TOPRIM motif were examined and found not to result in cell killing. Every other substitution except Ala had no detectable DNA cleavage or relaxation activity. Unlike the Gly to Ser substitution, DNA religation was not inhibited by the Gly to Ala substitution. We also demonstrated that in a different subdomain of the enzyme (subdomain III), although the conversion of the highly conserved methionine residue adjacent to the active site tyrosine of Y. pestis topoisomerase I did not inhibit relaxation of DNA or affect cell viability by itself, the mutation enhanced DNA cleavage by the enzyme. When this increase in DNA cleavage was combined with the inhibition of DNA rejoining by the TOPRIM Gly to Ser mutation, the level of DNA cleavage product and degree of cell killing of the double mutant were increased significantly over the TOPRIM Gly to Ser single mutant. This demonstrates that molecular interactions near the active site tyrosine of type IA topoisomerases can also affect the DNA cleavage-religation equilibrium and be synergistic with other molecular perturbations elsewhere in the enzyme that inhibit DNA rejoining to achieve higher degree of DNA cleavage product accumulation and overall bactericidal action. Site-directed mutagenesis was carried out with using Pfu Ultra DNA polymerase (from Stratagene) with procedures based on the Stratagene QuikChange protocol. Oligonucleotide primers coding for the desired amino acid substitutions were synthesized by Sigma Genosys. Random substitution of Y. pestis topoisomerase I (YTOP)2 at Gly122 was achieved with plasmid pYTOP (12) as template and primers 5&#x2032;GACCTTGATCGCGAANNNGAGGCTATTGCCTG 3&#x2032; and 5&#x2032; CAGGCAATAGCCTCNNNTTCGCGATCAAGGTC 3&#x2032;. YTOP mutants with substitutions of Gly122 with Asn, His, Trp and Tyr or Met326 substitution with Val were created by using oligonucleotides specifying these substitutions. Recombinant E. coli topoisomerase I (ETOP) with Val substitution at Met320 were made by introducing the site-directed mutation into plasmid pETOP or pETOP-G116S (12). In the pYTOP and pETOP plasmids, the synthesis of the recombinant topoisomerase I is under the control of the arabinose-inducible BAD promoter. In addition to ampicillin, the plates and media used for isolation, maintenance and overnight growth of the E. coli strains transformed with plasmids pYTOP or pETOP contained 2% glucose to suppress the expression of the potentially lethal mutant topoisomerases from the BAD promoter. Escherichia coli strain JD5 with chromosomal dinD1::lacZ fusion (15) was transformed with plasmid pYTOP derivatives encoding mutant YTOP enzymes. Transformations obtained on LB plates with 2% glucose and 100 &#x3BC;g/ml ampicillin were replicated onto plates with ampicillin, 35 &#x3BC;g/ml X-gal and 0.002% arabinose to identify SOS-inducing mutants that gave rise to blue colonies after overnight incubation at 37&#xB0;C due to induction of the dinD1 promoter (16). The ability of the YTOP mutants with different substitutions at Gly122 to cause bacterial cell death was first evaluated in strain JD5 by inducing their expression with saturating concentration of arabinose (0.2%) for 2 h at early exponential phase (OD600 = 0.4) after dilution of overnight culture in the presence of 2% glucose into fresh LB medium with antibiotics but no glucose. Viable counts were measured by plating of dilutions on LB plates with 2% glucose and ampicillin and compared with viable counts from cultures not induced with arabinose after overnight incubation of the plates at 37&#xB0;C. The cell killing effects of mutant recombinant topoisomerases with the Gly to Ser substitution were also measured at a range of lower arabinose concentrations (0.00006&#x2013;0.002%) in E. coli strain BW27784 (from Yale E. coli Genetic Stock Center). In this strain, the control of the arabinose transporter araE gene by a constitutive promoter (17) allows expression from the BAD promoter to be regulated by increasing arabinose concentration instead of the &#x2018;all-or-none&#x2019; expression pattern found in strain JD5 (12,18). This enabled comparison of the cell killing efficiency with increasing arabinose concentrations. Wild-type and mutant YTOP proteins were induced in E. coli JD5 strain after growth in LB medium with ampicillin to exponential phase with either 0.02 or 0.2% arabinose for 4 h at 37&#xB0;C. The recombinant proteins with thioredoxin N-terminal tag and His6 C-terminal tag were purified with the His SpinTrap column (GE Healthcare) according to manufacturer's protocol. Recombinant ETOP mutant proteins without affinity tags were expressed in E. coli strain GP200 (&#x394;topA) and purified by combination of phosphocellulose, hydroxyapitite and DNA affinity chromatography columns as previously described (19,20). Each assay was carried out at least thrice, and representative results are shown here. Assays of relaxation of negatively supercoiled DNA by topoisomerase I was assayed in the presence of 6 mM MgCl2 as described previously (20). Cleavage of plasmid DNA was assayed in buffer with either no added Mg2+ or with up to 10 mM MgCl2 added as described (12). A 59-base oligonucleotide 5&#x2032;-GCCCTGAAAGATTATGCAATGCGCTTTGGGCAAACCAAGAGAGCTAATCTTTCAGGGC-3&#x2032; with the preferred cleavage site CAAT&#x2193;GC for ETOP (21) was labeled at the 5&#x2032;-end with T4 polynucleotide kinase and [&#x3B3;32P-ATP]. Cleavage and religation of the oligonucleotide by topoisomerase I were assayed as described and analyzed by electrophoresis in a 15% DNA sequencing gel (22). The wild-type topoisomerase I religation reaction is complete after 10 s at 37&#xB0;C so some of the religation reactions were carried out on ice at 0&#xB0;C. Gel shift assay with the same 5&#x2032;-end labeled oligonucleotide was used to compare non-covalent binding affinities of wild-type and mutant ETOP enzymes with the DNA substrate (22). To assess the effect of the mutations on Mg2+-binding affinity of ETOP, measurements of change in intrinsic tryptophan fluorescence of ETOP enzymes from binding of Mg2+ (20,23) were carried out as described previously (12). Non-linear regression curve fitting for two binding sites was carried out using the GraphPad Prism program. Effect of overexpression of recombinant wild-type or mutant Y. pestis topoisomerase I with substitutions at Gly122 on the viability of E. coli JD5 Relative viability (RV) was measured by the ratio of the viable colonies obtained after induction of the BAD promoter directing the expression of recombinant YTOP with 0.2% arabinose for 2&#x2009;h in comparison with viable colonies from the culture not treated with arabinose. The results shown represent the average and standard deviation from at least three measurements. Relative viability (RV) was measured by the ratio of the viable colonies obtained after induction of the BAD promoter directing the expression of recombinant YTOP with 0.2% arabinose for 2&#x2009;h in comparison with viable colonies from the culture not treated with arabinose. The results shown represent the average and standard deviation from at least three measurements. Enzymatic activities of the YTOP-G122A mutant. (A) Relaxation of supercoiled DNA. The indicated amount of wild-type or G122A mutant YTOP protein was incubated in relaxation buffer containing 6 mM MgCl2 at 37&#xB0;C for 30 min. S: supercoiled plasmid DNA. (B) Magnesium dependent formation of cleavage product from oligonucleotide DNA substrate by wild-type YTOP and YTOP-G122A mutant enzyme. 400 ng of enzyme was incubated with 0.5 pmole of 5&#x2032;-end labeled oligonucleotide substrate for 30 min at 37&#xB0;C. The cleavage product was visualized by PhosphorImager after electrophoresis in a 15% sequencing gel. (C) Religation of DNA cleavage product. DNA cleavage reaction between 400 ng of enzyme and 0.5 pmole of oligonucleotide substrate in the presence of 5 mM MgCl2 was allowed to reach cleavage-religation equilibrium and then treated with 1 M NaCl to promote dissociation of the enzyme from the religated DNA. The religation reactions were stopped after the indicated amount of time by the addition of stop solution containing 0.2 M NaOH and 79% formamide. Enzymatic activities of the YTOP-G122A mutant. (A) Relaxation of supercoiled DNA. The indicated amount of wild-type or G122A mutant YTOP protein was incubated in relaxation buffer containing 6 mM MgCl2 at 37&#xB0;C for 30 min. S: supercoiled plasmid DNA. (B) Magnesium dependent formation of cleavage product from oligonucleotide DNA substrate by wild-type YTOP and YTOP-G122A mutant enzyme. 400 ng of enzyme was incubated with 0.5 pmole of 5&#x2032;-end labeled oligonucleotide substrate for 30 min at 37&#xB0;C. The cleavage product was visualized by PhosphorImager after electrophoresis in a 15% sequencing gel. (C) Religation of DNA cleavage product. DNA cleavage reaction between 400 ng of enzyme and 0.5 pmole of oligonucleotide substrate in the presence of 5 mM MgCl2 was allowed to reach cleavage-religation equilibrium and then treated with 1 M NaCl to promote dissociation of the enzyme from the religated DNA. The religation reactions were stopped after the indicated amount of time by the addition of stop solution containing 0.2 M NaOH and 79% formamide. DNA cleavage was not observed for any of the other YTOP G122 substitution mutant protein in the absence of added Mg2+ and the addition of up to 10 mM Mg2+ did not restore the DNA cleavage activity of any of the other Gly122 substitution mutants (data not shown). Due to its more significant effect on viability among the mutants examined, DNA cleavage activity of YTOP-G122C was also examined using 5&#x2032;-end labeled oligonucleotide as substrate. DNA cleavage activity was again not detectable, so the small effect on viability from overexpression of YTOP-G122C was probably unrelated to the effect of the mutation on DNA cleavage-religation. It can be concluded that the Gly to Ser substitution is unique in its cell killing phenotype because it is the only amino acid substitution at this critical position that inhibits DNA religation completely while retaining a high degree of DNA cleavage activity. Effect of arabinose concentration on the viability of E. coli BW27784 expressing different recombinant YTOP proteins under the control of the BAD promoter Relative viability was determined by calculating the ratio of the viable colony counts after 2 h of induction with the indicated arabinose concentration versus the viable colony counts from the non-induced culture. The recombinant YTOP proteins were expressed in low copy number plasmids (pAYTOP and its derivatives). The results shown represent the average and standard deviation of at least four different measurements for the mutant YTOP proteins and three different measurements for wild-type YTOP. Mutant pAYTOP128 had a third A383P substitution in addition to G122S and M326V mutations. Single mutation of A383P or M326V in YTOP did not induce SOS response when induced by arabinose and had no significant effect on viability (12). Relative viability was determined by calculating the ratio of the viable colony counts after 2 h of induction with the indicated arabinose concentration versus the viable colony counts from the non-induced culture. The recombinant YTOP proteins were expressed in low copy number plasmids (pAYTOP and its derivatives). The results shown represent the average and standard deviation of at least four different measurements for the mutant YTOP proteins and three different measurements for wild-type YTOP. Mutant pAYTOP128 had a third A383P substitution in addition to G122S and M326V mutations. Single mutation of A383P or M326V in YTOP did not induce SOS response when induced by arabinose and had no significant effect on viability (12). Effect of the M326V mutation on the relaxation and cleavage activities of YTOP. (A) YTOP-M326V has similar relaxation activity as wild-type YTOP enzyme. S: supercoiled plasmid DNA. (B) YTOP-M326V DNA cleavage activity was magnesium independent, and was enhanced over the wild-type DNA cleavage activity. Formation of oligonucleotide cleavage product was assayed with 400 ng of enzyme, 0.5 pmole of 5&#x2032;-end labeled oligonucleotide substrate after incubation for 30 min at 37&#xB0;C. Effect of the M326V mutation on the relaxation and cleavage activities of YTOP. (A) YTOP-M326V has similar relaxation activity as wild-type YTOP enzyme. S: supercoiled plasmid DNA. (B) YTOP-M326V DNA cleavage activity was magnesium independent, and was enhanced over the wild-type DNA cleavage activity. Formation of oligonucleotide cleavage product was assayed with 400 ng of enzyme, 0.5 pmole of 5&#x2032;-end labeled oligonucleotide substrate after incubation for 30 min at 37&#xB0;C. The M320V mutation enhanced DNA cleavage by ETOP without affecting the relaxation and religation activities significantly. (A) Similar relaxation activity for wild-type ETOP and ETOP-M320V assayed in the presence of 6 mM MgCl2 at 37&#xB0;C for 30 min. S: supercoiled plasmid DNA. (B) Comparison of cleavage of oligonucleotide substrate by wild-type ETOP and ETOP-M320V enzymes. The indicated amount of enzyme was incubated with 0.5 pmole of substrate for 30 min at 37&#xB0;C in the absence of any MgCl2. (C) ETOP-M320V does not require magnesium for DNA cleavage. 400 ng of enzyme was incubated with 0.5 pmole of substrate at 37&#xB0;C for 10 min. (D) DNA religation by ETOP-M320V mutant enzyme. The olignonucleotide substrate was incubated with 400 ng of enzyme for 10 min at 37&#xB0;C in the absence of added MgCl2 before being placed on ice and the addition of 5 mM MgCl2 along with 1 M NaCl to promote DNA religation of the cleavage product and subsequent dissociation of the enzyme from the religated DNA. The reactions were allowed to proceed at 0&#xB0;C for the indicated length of time before being stopped for analysis of the remaining cleavage product by gel electrophoresis. The M320V mutation enhanced DNA cleavage by ETOP without affecting the relaxation and religation activities significantly. (A) Similar relaxation activity for wild-type ETOP and ETOP-M320V assayed in the presence of 6 mM MgCl2 at 37&#xB0;C for 30 min. S: supercoiled plasmid DNA. (B) Comparison of cleavage of oligonucleotide substrate by wild-type ETOP and ETOP-M320V enzymes. The indicated amount of enzyme was incubated with 0.5 pmole of substrate for 30 min at 37&#xB0;C in the absence of any MgCl2. (C) ETOP-M320V does not require magnesium for DNA cleavage. 400 ng of enzyme was incubated with 0.5 pmole of substrate at 37&#xB0;C for 10 min. (D) DNA religation by ETOP-M320V mutant enzyme. The olignonucleotide substrate was incubated with 400 ng of enzyme for 10 min at 37&#xB0;C in the absence of added MgCl2 before being placed on ice and the addition of 5 mM MgCl2 along with 1 M NaCl to promote DNA religation of the cleavage product and subsequent dissociation of the enzyme from the religated DNA. The reactions were allowed to proceed at 0&#xB0;C for the indicated length of time before being stopped for analysis of the remaining cleavage product by gel electrophoresis. Effect of addition of the M320V mutation to the ETOP-G116S mutant enzyme activities. (A) Restoration of a low level of relaxation activity to the ETOP-G116S mutant enzyme by the M320V mutation. The indicated amount of enzyme was incubated with supercoiled plasmid DNA in buffer containing 6 mM MgCl2 at 37&#xB0;C for 30 min. S: supercoiled plasmid DNA. (B) Dependence of magnesium for DNA cleavage. 400 ng of enzyme was incubated with 0.5 pmole of substrate for 30 min at 37&#xB0;C. (C) Quantitation of oligonucleotide (5 pmole) cleavage by ETOP-G116S (filled circles) and ETOP-G116S/M320V (open circles) enzymes in the presence of 5 mM MgCl2. The data plotted represents the average and standard deviation from three different experiments. (D) DNA religation inhibition for the ETOP-G116 and ETOP-G116S/M320V mutants. The oligonucleotide substrate was incubated with 400 ng of enzyme in the presence of 5 mM MgCl2 at 37&#xB0;C for 10 min at 37&#xB0;C before the addition of 1 M NaCl and further incubation at 37&#xB0;C for the indicated length of time. Effect of addition of the M320V mutation to the ETOP-G116S mutant enzyme activities. (A) Restoration of a low level of relaxation activity to the ETOP-G116S mutant enzyme by the M320V mutation. The indicated amount of enzyme was incubated with supercoiled plasmid DNA in buffer containing 6 mM MgCl2 at 37&#xB0;C for 30 min. S: supercoiled plasmid DNA. (B) Dependence of magnesium for DNA cleavage. 400 ng of enzyme was incubated with 0.5 pmole of substrate for 30 min at 37&#xB0;C. (C) Quantitation of oligonucleotide (5 pmole) cleavage by ETOP-G116S (filled circles) and ETOP-G116S/M320V (open circles) enzymes in the presence of 5 mM MgCl2. The data plotted represents the average and standard deviation from three different experiments. (D) DNA religation inhibition for the ETOP-G116 and ETOP-G116S/M320V mutants. The oligonucleotide substrate was incubated with 400 ng of enzyme in the presence of 5 mM MgCl2 at 37&#xB0;C for 10 min at 37&#xB0;C before the addition of 1 M NaCl and further incubation at 37&#xB0;C for the indicated length of time. Magnesium binding measured by intrinsic tryptophan fluorescence of wild-type and mutant ETOP enzymes. Decrease of tryptophan fluorescence signal at 334 nm (excitation at 295 nm) with increasing concentration of MgCl2 was monitored. Fraction of maximal decrease of fluorescence signal was determined and curve fitted for binding of two Mg2+/enzyme molecule with the GraphPad Prism program. The KDs shown in the insert represent the average from two sets of data for ETOP-G116S/M320V and three sets of data for wild-type ETOP and ETOP-G116S. Magnesium binding measured by intrinsic tryptophan fluorescence of wild-type and mutant ETOP enzymes. Decrease of tryptophan fluorescence signal at 334 nm (excitation at 295 nm) with increasing concentration of MgCl2 was monitored. Fraction of maximal decrease of fluorescence signal was determined and curve fitted for binding of two Mg2+/enzyme molecule with the GraphPad Prism program. The KDs shown in the insert represent the average from two sets of data for ETOP-G116S/M320V and three sets of data for wild-type ETOP and ETOP-G116S. Gel shift assay with the labeled oligonucleotide substrate used for the DNA cleavage assay was carried out to determine if the addition of the M320V mutation to the ETOP-G116S mutant enhanced the initial non-covalent interaction with DNA as a possible explanation for the higher amount of DNA cleavage product observed for the double mutant. The results (Supplementary Figure 1) showed that the ETOP-G116S and ETOP-G116S/M320V mutant enzymes had similar non-covalent binding affinity for the oligonucleotide DNA substrate used in the cleavage reaction. Therefore the biochemical effect of the M320V mutation on ETOP activity is likely to be directly on the step of DNA cleavage during the catalytic cycle. In this study, it was determined that the Ser substitution at the strictly conserved Gly residue of the topoisomerase I TOPRIM motif was unique in its consequence of inhibiting DNA religation while retaining DNA cleavage activity, thus accounting for an effect on enzyme activity and cell viability similar to that expected from a topoisomerase poison. Among all amino acids, glycine has the smallest and most flexible side chain. The size of the side chain increases in the order of Gly to Ala to Ser. When the TOPRIM Gly was substituted with Ala, Mg2+-binding affinity was likely to have also been affected, as DNA cleavage became Mg2+ dependent as in the case of the Gly to Ser substitution. However, the Ala substitution might not have altered the positioning of the DNA 3&#x2032;-hydroxyl group formed after DNA cleavage as much as the Ser substitution to have an inhibitory effect on DNA religation. With all the other 17 amino acid substitutions tested here, the steric effect from replacing the strictly conserved Gly side chain with a much larger group probably accounted for the complete loss of DNA cleavage activity, even in the presence of up to 5 mM Mg2+. The strict requirement of Gly for its steric properties probably accounts for its high degree of conservation following the DXD residues in the TOPRIM domain of DNA topoisomerases (26,27). The results from these experiments illustrate how the two events of DNA cleavage and DNA religation in the catalytic cycle, can be differentially affected by molecular perturbations even though the DNA religation is the reverse of DNA cleavage step when considered only for overall chemical changes. Small molecules could potentially bind adjacent to the Gly residue of the topoisomerase IA TOPRIM motif in subdomain I and exert effect selectively on the DNA religation step while allowing the enzyme to cleave DNA and form a covalent complex, similar to the effect of the Ser substitution. Single mutation of the Met residue adjacent to the active site Tyr to Val was found not to have SOS-inducing or cell killing phenotypes in vivo, but nevertheless resulted in increase in DNA cleavage activity in vitro. There have been no mutagenesis results on this residue until this study. The Met to Val is a relatively conservative substitution so it is not surprising that the substitution did not inhibit the relaxation activity. Nevertheless, substitutions between Met and Val in other proteins have been shown to have significant effects on protein folding or catalytic properties (28&#x2013;30). This result demonstrated for the first time that perturbation proximal to the active site tyrosine in subdomain III of topoisomerase I could influence DNA cleavage efficiency. Regions of E. coli topoisomerase I structure important for the control of the DNA cleavage-religation equilibrium. The active site nucleophile Tyr-319 and adjacent Met-320 residues in subdomain III are shown along with the TOPRIM residues Asp-111, Asp-113 and Gly-116 in subdomain I in the structure (Protein Data Bank number 1ECL) of the 67 kDa N-terminal fragment of E. coli topoisomerase I (41). Regions of E. coli topoisomerase I structure important for the control of the DNA cleavage-religation equilibrium. The active site nucleophile Tyr-319 and adjacent Met-320 residues in subdomain III are shown along with the TOPRIM residues Asp-111, Asp-113 and Gly-116 in subdomain I in the structure (Protein Data Bank number 1ECL) of the 67 kDa N-terminal fragment of E. coli topoisomerase I (41). High through-put screening of compound libraries is one approach that is being utilized in the attempt of identifying small molecules that can act as bactericidal poisons and increase the accumulation of covalent complex formed by bacterial type IA topoisomerases and cleaved DNA (14). The identification of various regions of the enzyme structure and associated molecular perturbations that can influence the DNA cleavage-religation equilibrium of topoisomerase I could facilitate a second alternative approach of drug discovery through molecular modeling (35&#x2013;37). For such molecular modeling efforts, it would be extremely useful to have a crystal structure of the covalent complex formed between a type IA topoisomerase and cleaved DNA available. Structure of the covalent complex would also complement the currently available 3-dimensional structures of the non-covalent complexes in different conformational states formed between type IA topoisomerases and DNA (38&#x2013;40) to provide key information on the catalytic mechanism and protein conformational changes that take place during the catalytic cycle. The mutant enzyme molecules that have been identified in our ongoing study as those that could form stabilized covalent intermediate with cleaved DNA might be more amenable to efforts of obtaining a crystal structure of the covalent complex between type IA topoisomerase and cleaved DNA substrate. Supplementary Data are available at NAR Online.
</content>
</document>
