<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <id>2241852</id>
  <title>Overlapping activator sequences determined for two oppositely oriented promoters in halophilic Archaea
</title>
  <abstract>
 Transcription of the genomic region involved in gas vesicle formation in Halobacterium salinarum (p-vac) and Haloferax mediterranei (mc-vac) is driven by two divergent promoters, PA and PD, separated by only 35 nt. Both promoters are activated by the transcription activator GvpE which in the case of PmcA requires a 20-nt sequence (UAS) consisting of two conserved 8-nt sequence portions located upstream of BRE. Here, we determined the two UAS elements in the promoter region of p-vac by scanning mutageneses using constructs containing PpD (without PpA) fused to the bgaH reporter gene encoding an enzyme with &#x3B2;-galactosidase activity, or the dual reporter construct pApD with PpD fused to bgaH and PpA to an altered version of gvpA. The two UAS elements found exhibited a similar extension and distance to BRE as previously determined for the UAS in PmcA. Their distal 8-nt portions almost completely overlapped in the centre of PpD&#x2013;PpA, and mutations in this region negatively affected the GvpE-mediated activation of both promoters. Any alteration of the distance between BRE and UAS resulted in the loss of the GvpE activation, as did a complete substitution of the proximal 8-nt portion, underlining that a close location of UAS and BRE was very important.
</abstract>
  <content>
 The extremely halophilic Halobacterium salinarum and the moderately halophilic Haloferax mediterranei produce gas vesicles depending on environmental factors (1). We are interested in mechanisms of gene regulation in halophilic Archaea and use the gvp gene clusters encoding the proteins required for gas vesicle formation as model system. Gas vesicle formation involves the two gene clusters gvpACNO and gvpDEFGHIJKLM, which are oppositely oriented in the vac region (2). Two different vac regions of H. salinarum PHH1 are known, the plasmid pHH1-encoded p-vac and the chromosomal c-vac region, and in addition the chromosomal mc-vac region of H. mediterranei. The 14 gvp genes found in each of these vac regions encode slightly different variants of the two gas vesicle structural proteins GvpA and GvpC, and of additional Gvp proteins required for the assembly of this structure. GvpD and GvpE regulate the expression, with GvpE serving as transcriptional activator and GvpD being involved in the repression of gas vesicle formation (2&#x2013;5). GvpD and GvpE are able to interact, and the interaction results in the breakdown of GvpE (4,6). Comparison of the three intergenic regions between PA and PD in different vac-regions, and alignment of the 8-nt UAS portions. (A) The vac regions are designated mc (mc-vac), p (p-vac) and c (c-vac). The TATA-box and BRE elements (in italics) are shaded in grey. The sequence determined as GvpE-responsive element (UAS) in PmcA is in bold and underlined, and the two conserved 8-nt portions are labelled 1 and 2. Related sequences in p-vac and c-vac are also underlined. (B) Divergent double-stranded PpA&#x2013;PpD promoter sequence with the two putative UAS underlined. Arrows point to the direction of transcription. (C) Alignment of the 8-nt portions of the putative UAS elements found in the PA and PD promoters. The conserved sequences are shaded in grey. The distal (1) and the proximal (2) 8-nt portions of the UAS are indicated. Comparison of the three intergenic regions between PA and PD in different vac-regions, and alignment of the 8-nt UAS portions. (A) The vac regions are designated mc (mc-vac), p (p-vac) and c (c-vac). The TATA-box and BRE elements (in italics) are shaded in grey. The sequence determined as GvpE-responsive element (UAS) in PmcA is in bold and underlined, and the two conserved 8-nt portions are labelled 1 and 2. Related sequences in p-vac and c-vac are also underlined. (B) Divergent double-stranded PpA&#x2013;PpD promoter sequence with the two putative UAS underlined. Arrows point to the direction of transcription. (C) Alignment of the 8-nt portions of the putative UAS elements found in the PA and PD promoters. The conserved sequences are shaded in grey. The distal (1) and the proximal (2) 8-nt portions of the UAS are indicated. Two scanning mutageneses have been performed to determine the sequence elements required for the basal transcription and for the GvpE-mediated activation in vivo. The first series of 4-nt mutations encompassed a 50-nt region upstream of the transcription start site of p-gvpA, and the results of this study clearly define the TATA-box and BRE in PpA, but also a region around position &#x2013;10 that might serve as additional contact site of TFB (9,14). Mutations close to the 5&#x2032;-end of this 50-nt sequence also affected the GvpE-mediated activation in PpA (most strongly by altering the sequence AACCA upstream of BRE), but the mutations between the TATA-box and the start site of transcription had no effect on the GvpE-mediated activation (9). The PmcA promoter of mc-vac was used for the second 4-nt scanning mutagenesis encompassing the sequences upstream of the PmcA-BRE, and this study defined the 20-nt sequence TGAAACGG-n4-TGAACCAA adjacent to BRE as important for the GvpE-mediated activation (Figure 1A) (13). A significant drop in the GvpE-induced activation is observed when two 8-nt portions of this element (labelled 1 and 2 in Figure 1) are mutated in steps of 4-nt, but a residual activity of 6&#x2013;20% is still observed (BgaH activity quantified by ONPG assay). In silico analysis suggests similar 20-nt elements in all three PA promoters and implies that they might serve as upstream activator sequence (UAS) for the GvpE-mediated activation (Figure 1A). The AACCA sequence mentioned above is part of the proximal 8-nt portion of this element in PpA, and mutations up to CTGG had only a minor effect on the GvpE-induction in p-vac (9). Whether similar 20-nt UAS elements also occur in the GvpE-activated PD promoters is not yet known and topic of the present report. In silico analysis indicated two similar elements in PmcD and PpD (Figure 1C). If a similar 20-nt UAS is found for PD, the two divergent UAS in the PD&#x2013;PA promoter region must overlap considerably in the centre of the 35-nt of intervening sequence as shown for p-vac in Figure 1B. In this report, we analysed the PpD&#x2013;PpA promoter region by 5-nt scanning mutagenesis to determine the respective UAS element required for the GvpE-mediated activation of both promoters in H. volcanii transformants. Using pGvpE, cGvpE or mcGvpE to activate PpD-bgaH again defined cGvpE as strongest activator protein. A 5-nt scanning mutagenesis performed with PpD&#x2013;bgaH clearly yielded an UAS element of similar size as determined in the previous PmcA-study. The effect of mutations was also analysed in the dual reporter construct pApDUGA (containing 3 UGA stop codons in gvpA) by monitoring the activity of both promoters simultaneously. These experiments confirmed the UAS of PpD, but also the hypothesized GvpE&#x2013;UAS of PpA and proved that both UAS elements almost entirely overlap with their distal 8-nt portions in the centre of the PpD&#x2013;PpA region. In addition, variations in the UAS&#x2013;BRE distance, a complete substitution of the entire UAS element, and complete substitutions of either the distal or the proximal region were constructed. The results underlined that the close location of UAS&#x2013;BRE is required for the GvpE-induced promoter activity. Primers used to construct the PpD and pApD promoter mutants aSubstitutions marked in bold, insertions underlined, restriction sites in italics. aSubstitutions marked in bold, insertions underlined, restriction sites in italics. The PpD&#x2013;bgaH fragment inserted into pWL102 served as wild type in the PpD mutation studies. The PpD&#x2013;bgaH promoter mutants pD-M1 through pD-M8 each contained a 5-nt substitution upstream of PpD&#x2013;BRE. All mutants were constructed by PCR using PpD&#x2013;bgaH in pBluescriptSK+ as template and primer 3&#x2032;-PpD(4) plus the respective 5&#x2032;-mutation primer harbouring the 5-nt substitutions (Table 1). The promoter mutants pD+3, pD+5, pD&#x394;3I and pD&#x394;3II with insertions or deletions upstream of BRE were constructed using PpD&#x2013;bgaH and primer 3&#x2032;-PpD(3) plus the respective 5&#x2032; mutation primers (Table 1). All mutant-PpD&#x2013;bgaH fragments were transferred to pWL102 as XbaI&#x2013;BamHI fragment. Construct pApDUGA (3 UGA-stop codons introduced in p-gvpA starting at position 28) was constructed using primer pair gvpA-UGA-5&#x2032; and gvpA-UGA-3&#x2032; for the PCR (Table 1). Promoter mutants harbouring 5-nt substitutions (pApD&#x2013;M1 through M8, identical to those described for pD above) and an additional mutant pApD&#x2013;M9 were constructed by PCR using pApDUGA as template together with primer 3&#x2032;-PpA(WT) or 3&#x2032;PpD&#x2013;M9 plus the respective 5&#x2032;-mutation primer 5&#x2032;-PpD&#x2013;M1 through M9 (Table 1). The resulting XbaI&#x2013;BamHI gvpA&#x2013;PpA-PpD&#x2013;bgaH fragments were transferred to pWL102 and used to transform H. volcanii. Primers used to construct mutants with insertions, deletions or substitutions aSubstitutions marked in bold, insertions underlined, slash marks position of deletion, restriction sites in italics. aSubstitutions marked in bold, insertions underlined, slash marks position of deletion, restriction sites in italics. The PmcA&#x2013;bgaH mutants were constructed in a similar way by PCR. Mutant mcA&#x2013;InsI (TGT-insertion adjacent to BRE) was constructed using primer pair mcA&#x2013;XbaI and InsIforward for the first PCR, and mcA&#x2013;NcoI2a and InsI-reverse for the second PCR (Table 2). The third PCR was done with primers mcA&#x2013;XbaI and mcA&#x2013;NcoI2a. The mcA&#x2013;InsII mutant was produced using primers InsII-forward and InsII-reverse together with the primers mcA&#x2013;XbaI and mcA&#x2013;NcoI2a (Table 2). Construct mcA&#x2013;Del was produced using the primers Del-reverse and Del-forward, and construct mcA&#x2013;Sub using Sub-reverse and Sub-forward. Construct PmcDL&#x2013;bgaH was obtained using the mc-vac region in pBluescriptSK+ as template and primer pair 5&#x2032;-Xba&#x2013;PmcD and 3&#x2032;-Nco&#x2013;pA(1&#x2013;5)-PmcD (Table 2). The fragment contains the PmcD promoter region plus the region encoding the mRNA leader of mc-gvpD. All these promoter fragments were fused as XbaI&#x2013;NcoI fragments to the bgaH reading frame in pBluescript and transferred as XbaI&#x2013;BamHI fragment to pWL102 that was used to transform H. volcanii. All promoter sequences and fusions were controlled by DNA sequencing. The accession numbers of the p-vac subfragmentsin Genbank are X64729 (p-gvpACNO), X55648 (p-gvpDEFGHIJKLM) and X64701 of the mc-vac region. Prior to the transformation of H. volcanii each construct was passaged through the E. coli dam&#x2013; strain GM 1674 to avoid a halobacterial restriction barrier. Transformation was done as described (15), and transformants were selected on agar plates containing 6 &#xB5;g mevinolin ml&#x2212;1 (pWL102) and/or 0.2 &#xB5;g novobiocin ml&#x2212;1 (pJAS35). Mevinolin is a derivative of lovastatin that was obtained as a generous gift of MSD Sharp &amp; Dohme GmbH (Haar, Germany). The amount and presence of the desired constructs in each transformant were controlled by the analysis of the isolated plasmids. The BgaH activity was measured by ONPG assay in cell lysates of the respective bgaH transformants (16). The protein concentration was determined by the Bradford assay (17) using BSA as standard. RNA was isolated from H. volcanii transformants according to (18) from cultures at OD600 = 1.8&#x2013;2.0. Northern analyses involved electrophoresis of 2 or 0.02 &#xB5;g RNA on denaturing, formaldehyde-containing, 1.2% (w/v) agarose gels, followed by capillar transfer to nylon membranes (17). A strand-specific RNA probe complementary to bgaH mRNA was synthesized using the 2.2-kb bgaH fragment inserted in pBluescriptSK+ as template for T7 polymerase. S&#xED;milarly, a strand-specific p-gvpA RNA probe was produced using p-gvpA inserted in pBluescriptSK+. The RNA was labelled using the DIG RNA Labeling Kit (Roche, Germany). Northern hybridization was carried out as described by Ausubel et al. (17), but the hybridization solution contained 10% (w/v) dextran sulphate (Sigma, Germany), 1% (w/v) SDS and 0.5% (w/v) skim milk powder. Samples of H. volcanii and H. volcanii transformants were taken in early stationary growth (after 48&#x2013;54 h of growth) and processed for protein isolation as described (6). Soluble proteins (20 &#xB5;g) were separated on 12% tricine SDS&#x2013;polyacrylamide gels (19). Western analyses were performed as described (17). Two different antisera raised against cGvpE (10) and mcGvpE (4) were used in a dilution of 1:1000 (mcGvpE) or 1:10000 (cGvpE antiserum) in blocking buffer, and the reacting antibodies were detected using the ECL detection system (GE Healthcare, Germany). DNA sequence determination of the fusion constructs was done according to the Sanger method using the Sequi-Therm EXCEL II Long-Read DNA Sequencing Kit-LC protocol (Biozym, Germany). The fragments were separated using a Licor DNA sequencer. In silico analysis of the region upstream of PpD (and PmcD) indicated a sequence element related to the UAS of PmcA that could be a putative GvpE-responsive element (Figure 1C). In contrast, the PcD promoter of c-vac lacking the activation by GvpE did not show such a conserved sequence element (Figure 1C). An initial PmcDL&#x2013;bgaH construct (containing PmcD plus the region encoding the mRNA leader of mc-gvpD fused to bgaH) did not yield detectable BgaH activities in H. volcanii transformants. However, the PpD&#x2013;bgaH construct containing the direct fusion of the bgaH reading frame to PpD (&#x2018;leaderless&#x2019;) was useful. Transformants containing PpD&#x2013;bgaH together with pEex (p-gvpE reading frame expressed under ferredoxin promoter control) produced well detectable amounts of BgaH (35 mU/mg protein). To determine the PpD activity in response to the two other GvpE proteins, cGvpE and mcGvpE, PpD&#x2013;bgaH was tested in transformants carrying cEex or mcEex. The presence of each GvpE protein was confirmed by western analyses using an antiserum raised against cGvpE (10). The basal PpD promoter activity measured as BgaH activity in the lysate of the PpD&#x2013;bgaH transformants was with 1.2 mU/mg rather low, but much larger GvpE-induced activities were observed in the lysates of transformants harbouring in addition to PpD&#x2013;bgaH construct pEex (35 mU/mg), mcEex (410 mU/mg) or cEex (830 mU/mg). These results suggested that cGvpE was the strongest and pGvpE the weakest activator protein, similar to the results already described for the PmcA and PpA promoters (9,11). Analysis of mutants derived from PpD&#x2013;bgaH. (A) BgaH activities determined for the PpD&#x2013;bgaH wild type and the mutants in PpD&#x2013;bgaH+pEex transformants, including standard deviations (n = 4). (B) Western analysis to confirm the presence of similar amounts of pGvpE in each of these transformants. The label pE depicts GvpE. (C) Sequence of the intergenic region of p-vac with the two oppositely located BRE elements and PpD&#x2013;TATA-box shaded in grey. The arrow points in the direction of PpD transcription. The UAS element determined for PpD is underlined. Dots in the lines underneath depict nucleotides identical to wild type, and the respective nucleotide substitutions are given. The basal and GvpE-induced activities quantified by BgaH assay are given on the right. Analysis of mutants derived from PpD&#x2013;bgaH. (A) BgaH activities determined for the PpD&#x2013;bgaH wild type and the mutants in PpD&#x2013;bgaH+pEex transformants, including standard deviations (n = 4). (B) Western analysis to confirm the presence of similar amounts of pGvpE in each of these transformants. The label pE depicts GvpE. (C) Sequence of the intergenic region of p-vac with the two oppositely located BRE elements and PpD&#x2013;TATA-box shaded in grey. The arrow points in the direction of PpD transcription. The UAS element determined for PpD is underlined. Dots in the lines underneath depict nucleotides identical to wild type, and the respective nucleotide substitutions are given. The basal and GvpE-induced activities quantified by BgaH assay are given on the right. Analysis of pApD and of mutants derived from the dual reporter construct pApDUGA. (A) BgaH activities determined for the PpD&#x2013;bgaH in pApDUGA+pEex wild type and mutants, including the standard deviations (n = 4). pApD designates the original construct, and UGA the construct containing the 3 UGA stop codons in p-gvpA. The GvpE-induced activities quantified by BgaH assay are given on the right. (B) Sequence of the PpD&#x2013;PpA promoter region (given in opposite orientation as in Figure 2) with the two BRE elements and TATA-boxes shaded in grey. The arrows point to the directions of transcription. The two UAS elements determined are underlined, and the UAS of PpA is shaded in yellow. The various nucleotide substitutions are indicated underneath, and dots depict identical sequences. The mutations were identical to the ones introduced into the promoter region of PpD&#x2013;bgaH (Figure 2). The mutations affecting PpD are shaded in grey, and mutations affecting PpA are shaded in yellow. The relative amounts of p-gvpA mRNA in the transformants + pEex (as determined by northern analysis, Figure 4) are given on the right. (+) = presence and (&#x2212;) = absence of gvpA mRNA. Analysis of pApD and of mutants derived from the dual reporter construct pApDUGA. (A) BgaH activities determined for the PpD&#x2013;bgaH in pApDUGA+pEex wild type and mutants, including the standard deviations (n = 4). pApD designates the original construct, and UGA the construct containing the 3 UGA stop codons in p-gvpA. The GvpE-induced activities quantified by BgaH assay are given on the right. (B) Sequence of the PpD&#x2013;PpA promoter region (given in opposite orientation as in Figure 2) with the two BRE elements and TATA-boxes shaded in grey. The arrows point to the directions of transcription. The two UAS elements determined are underlined, and the UAS of PpA is shaded in yellow. The various nucleotide substitutions are indicated underneath, and dots depict identical sequences. The mutations were identical to the ones introduced into the promoter region of PpD&#x2013;bgaH (Figure 2). The mutations affecting PpD are shaded in grey, and mutations affecting PpA are shaded in yellow. The relative amounts of p-gvpA mRNA in the transformants + pEex (as determined by northern analysis, Figure 4) are given on the right. (+) = presence and (&#x2212;) = absence of gvpA mRNA. The basal PpD promoter activities of the pApDUGA wild-type and mutant constructs were 5&#x2013;20 mU/mg (data not shown). Only mutant pApD-M7 did not yield any basal PpD promoter activity, although the bgaH mRNA was observed in a comparable amount (data not shown). Since the pApD-M7+pEex transformant did not show any BgaH activity as well, we assumed that construct pApD-M7 was defect in the production of an active BgaH (Figure 3A). The other eight pApDUGA-mutant constructs confirmed the results described above for the various PpD&#x2013;bgaH mutants: pApD-M3 (intervening 4-nt sequence altered) and pApD-M6, M8 and M9 (mutations upstream of the PpD&#x2013;UAS) yielded similar GvpE-induced PpD activities as found for the wild-type pApDUGA (Figure 3A). Again, the strongest reductions in the BgaH activities were observed with mutants pApD-M5, M4 and M2 (&lt;31 mU/mg). All these results confirmed the 20-nt UAS upstream of the PpD&#x2013;BRE as important for the GvpE-induced PpD activity. Northern analysis to determine the amount of p-gvpA mRNA in pApDUGA+pEex transformants. (A) Nucleotide sequence of the PpD&#x2013;PpA promoter region with the two BRE elements and TATA-boxes shaded in grey. The two UAS elements are underlined. Lines and numbers above the sequence depict the various 5-nt mutations in mutants pApD-M1 through M9. (B) Total RNA of 0.02 &#xB5;g (bottom) derived from each transformant were separated on a formaldehyde containing, 1.2% agarose gels and hybridized a gvpA-specific probe. Amounts and quality of the RNA were checked by staining the 16S and 23S RNA (top; 2 &#xB5;g RNA applied in this case). Northern analysis to determine the amount of p-gvpA mRNA in pApDUGA+pEex transformants. (A) Nucleotide sequence of the PpD&#x2013;PpA promoter region with the two BRE elements and TATA-boxes shaded in grey. The two UAS elements are underlined. Lines and numbers above the sequence depict the various 5-nt mutations in mutants pApD-M1 through M9. (B) Total RNA of 0.02 &#xB5;g (bottom) derived from each transformant were separated on a formaldehyde containing, 1.2% agarose gels and hybridized a gvpA-specific probe. Amounts and quality of the RNA were checked by staining the 16S and 23S RNA (top; 2 &#xB5;g RNA applied in this case). Distance variants constructed for the PpD (A), PmcA (B) or PpA (C) promoter region. The sequence of each promoter region is given on top, with TATA-box and BRE shaded in grey. The UAS elements are underlined. Dots in the lines underneath depict nucleotides identical to wild type. Deletions are marked by xxx, and substitutions or insertions are indicated. The basal and GvpE-induced promoter activities quantified by BgaH assay are given on the right. Distance variants constructed for the PpD (A), PmcA (B) or PpA (C) promoter region. The sequence of each promoter region is given on top, with TATA-box and BRE shaded in grey. The UAS elements are underlined. Dots in the lines underneath depict nucleotides identical to wild type. Deletions are marked by xxx, and substitutions or insertions are indicated. The basal and GvpE-induced promoter activities quantified by BgaH assay are given on the right. Similar analyses were performed with the PmcA&#x2013;bgaH construct containing the PmcA promoter of H. mediterranei (Figure 5B). Two 3-nt insertions enlarged the distance between UAS and BRE (mcA&#x2013;InsI), or the space between the two 8-nt portions (mcA&#x2013;InsII). Both mutants showed a normal basal promoter activity in PmcA&#x2013;bgaH transformants, but all of them lacked the induction mediated by mcGvpE (Figure 5B). A 3-nt deletion in the spacer between the two 8-nt UAS portions (mcA&#x2013;Del) led to the loss of the GvpE-induced activity (Figure 5B), similar to the results obtained with PpD (Figure 5A). Altogether, these results demonstrated that the 4-nt distance between UAS-portions 1 and 2 and a close location of the 20-nt UAS to BRE are crucial for the GvpE-mediated activation. Mutant mcA-Sub contained a completely substituted PmcA&#x2013;UAS element (Figure 5B). No effect was observed on the basal PmcA activity, but the GvpE-mediated activation was completely abolished, demonstrating that the UAS-element is indeed essential for the GvpE-mediated activation. Four additional mutants were constructed with PpA&#x2013;bgaH to determine the effect of alterations in the two 8-nt portions 1 or 2 on the GvpE-induced expression (Figure 5C). Mutants pA1+&#x394;2 and pA&#x394;1+2 contained one of the 8-nt portions completely substituted, and pA1+1 and pA2+2 contained two identical 8-nt portions of the UAS (Figure 5C). The basal PpA promoter activities (determined in the presence of the &#x2018;empty&#x2019; vector pJAS35 in the respective transformants) were in the range of the PpA&#x2013;bgaH transformant or at the detection limit (0.5 mU/mg), indicating that the basal transcription was not affected (Figure 5C). With respect to the GvpE-induction, pA&#x394;1+2 transformants yielded a BgaH activity similar to wild type, suggesting that the proximal 8-nt portion located close to BRE was sufficient for the activation in this single promoter construct. In contrast, the PpA promoter in pA1+&#x394;2 was not activated by GvpE underlining that UAS and BRE must be in close contact. The two constructs containing the identical 8-nt portions of the UAS (pA1+1 and pA2+2) yielded slightly reduced (pA2+2, 72% of the BgaH activity of wild type) or stronger reduced GvpE-induced activities (pA1+1, 40%) (Figure 5C). The latter result could be due to the fact that the UAS portion 1 is active in both orientations, and a location of this element next to BRE might disturb the direction of the GvpE-mediated activation of PpA. These results underlined that both UAS portions were not equal in function, and that one of these UAS portions was required in close contact to BRE to yield a GvpE-stimulated promoter activity. In this report, we investigated the sequences required for the GvpE-mediated activation of the two oppositely oriented promoters, PA and PD, driving the expression of the two gvp gene clusters involved in the gas vesicle formation. A scanning mutagenesis previously performed with the related PmcA of the mc-vac region determined a 20-nt sequence adjacent to PmcA&#x2013;BRE sequence as important for the GvpE-mediated activation (13). This 20-nt sequence appears to be conserved between the three different PA promoters (Figure 1). A putative PpD-UAS should be located at a similar position upstream and adjacent to BRE, and in silico analysis yielded related, but slightly divergent sequences for the two GvpE-activated PD promoters in mc-vac and p-vac. The UAS element required for the GvpE-induction of PpD was determined by scanning mutagenesis with PpD&#x2013;bgaH using eight different 5-nt mutations, and all these variants were investigated in H. volcanii transformants in the presence (+pEex) or absence of pGvpE. None of these mutations abolished the basal transcription initiated at PpD, and the analysis of the transformants containing pEex in addition clearly defined the region required for the GvpE-mediated activation. As expected, this region was found close to the PpD&#x2013;BRE and consisted of two 8-nt sequence portions spaced by four non-conserved nucleotides. Any mutations further upstream did not affect the GvpE-induction of PpD. Additional mutants constructed to determine the effect of distance variations showed that the spaces between UAS&#x2013;BRE and also between the two 8-nt UAS portions were important. Similar results were also observed with distance variants of the PmcA&#x2013;UAS, where a 3-nt deletion, or several insertions between UAS and BRE resulted in the loss of the GvpE-mediated promoter activation. Thus, a very close location of UAS and BRE is required for the GvpE-mediated activation. In addition, mutants harbouring a complete substitution of the PmcA&#x2013;UAS lacked the activation by GvpE, indicating that the UAS sequence was essential for the GvpE-induced promoter activation. The consensus sequence YGAAAYGA could be derived from all 8-nt portions of the UAS elements found in the various gvp promoters activated by GvpE. This sequence is specific for the gvp gene clusters and does not occur throughout the genome sequence of H. salinarum NRC-1 (20). The close location of UAS and BRE suggests that GvpE could contact proteins of the basal transcription apparatus. It is possible that GvpE enhances the recruitment of TBP and thus activates the transcription initiation, similar to the transcriptional activator Ptr2 of Methanocaldococcus jannaschii (21,22). Comparison of the various scanning mutageneses performed with the mc-vac (A) and p-vac (B) promoter regions. The columns above the sequences indicate the specific BgaH activities determined for the various mutants (13, and this study). The respective mutations are marked as lines below each column and include the numbers of the various pApDUGA mutants in (B). The 8-nt portions of each 20-nt UAS element are underlined, and the TATA-box and BRE are shaded in grey. Arrows point in the direction of transcription. The 4-nt next to the centre of the region that were the most important ones for the GvpE-mediated activation of both promoters are indicated in bold. Comparison of the various scanning mutageneses performed with the mc-vac (A) and p-vac (B) promoter regions. The columns above the sequences indicate the specific BgaH activities determined for the various mutants (13, and this study). The respective mutations are marked as lines below each column and include the numbers of the various pApDUGA mutants in (B). The 8-nt portions of each 20-nt UAS element are underlined, and the TATA-box and BRE are shaded in grey. Arrows point in the direction of transcription. The 4-nt next to the centre of the region that were the most important ones for the GvpE-mediated activation of both promoters are indicated in bold. The promoter mutants carrying an UAS consisting of two identical portions yielded a slight reduction of the GvpE-induced activity (72%) in the case of pA2+2, whereas the pA-1+1 promoter version resulted in only 40% of the GvpE-induced activity determined for wild type. The latter result implied that the possible use of UAS-portion 1 in two orientations somehow disturbs the recruitment of the basal transcription apparatus by GvpE, if this sequence is placed adjacent to BRE. In summary, our results confirmed the almost complete overlap of the two distal portions of both UAS regulatory elements in the PD&#x2013;PA promoter region. This arrangement appears to be similar to overlapping operator sequences in the genome of bacteriophage lambda. To our knowledge, this is the first case of such an arrangement of regulatory elements in Archaea. Another promoter region, containing two oppositely oriented promoters that are co-ordinately regulated, has been characterized for the genes encoding the selenium-free [NiFe]-hydrogenases in Methanococcus voltae, but the distance between both TATA-boxes is with 290-nt significantly larger (23). The compact arrangement of the regulatory elements in PA&#x2013;PD might determine the amount and the time point for the activation of the both divergent gvp promoters during the gas vesicle formation, and it might be interesting to investigate the activity of both PA and PD promoters with the natural UAS-overlap compared to a construct harbouring two separated UAS elements with respect to the time-resolved expression during growth.
</content>
</document>
