<?xml version="1.0"?>
<document>
  <id>2241914</id>
  <title>Interaction of human tRNA-dihydrouridine synthase-2 with interferon-induced protein kinase PKR
</title>
  <abstract>
 PKR is an interferon (IFN)-induced protein kinase, which is involved in regulation of antiviral innate immunity, stress signaling, cell proliferation and programmed cell death. Although a low amount of PKR is expressed ubiquitously in all cell types in the absence of IFNs, PKR expression is induced at transcriptional level by IFN. PKR's enzymatic activity is activated by its binding to one of its activators. Double-stranded (ds) RNA, protein activator PACT and heparin are the three known activators of PKR. Activation of PKR in cells leads to a general block in protein synthesis due to phosphorylation of eIF2&#x3B1; on serine 51 by PKR. PKR activation is regulated very tightly in mammalian cells and a prolonged activation of PKR leads to apoptosis. Thus, positive and negative regulation of PKR activation is important for cell viability and function. The studies presented here describe human dihydrouridine synthase-2 (hDUS2) as a novel regulator of PKR. We originally identified hDUS2 as a protein interacting with PACT in a yeast two-hybrid screen. Further characterization revealed that hDUS2 also interacts with PKR through its dsRNA binding/dimerization domain and inhibits its kinase activity. Our results suggest that hDUS2 may act as a novel inhibitor of PKR in cells.
</abstract>
  <content>
 Interferons (IFNs) are cytokines with antiviral, antiproliferative and immunomodulatory properties, which they exert by inducing synthesis of several proteins (1,2). The IFN-induced, dsRNA-activated protein kinase PKR, a serine/threonine kinase, is a major mediator of the antiproliferative and antiviral actions of IFN (3&#x2013;6). Although induced at the transcriptional level by IFNs, PKR is present at a low, basal level in most cell types (7). PKR's kinase activity stays latent until it binds to one of its three known activators, double-stranded (ds) RNA, heparin and the protein activator PACT. In virally infected cells, dsRNA produced during viral replication or viral RNAs with extensive ds regions serve as PKR activators (8,9). Polyanionic agents such as heparin also activate PKR both in vitro (10) and in vivo (11). In addition, PACT is a cellular, protein activator of PKR, which heterodimerizes with PKR and activates it in the absence of dsRNA (12,13), thereby playing an important role in PKR activation in response to stress signals (14). The &#x3B1;-subunit of the eukaryotic protein synthesis initiation factor eIF-2 (eIF2&#x3B1;) is the most studied physiological substrate of PKR. Phosphorylation of eIF2&#x3B1; on Ser51 by PKR leads to an inhibition of protein synthesis (15,16). In addition to its central role in antiviral activity of IFNs, PKR is also involved in the regulation of apoptosis (17,18), cell proliferation (4,5), signal transduction (19&#x2013;21) and differentiation (22,23). The dsRNA-mediated activation of PKR has been characterized in detail (24&#x2013;29). The dsRNA-binding domain (dsRBD) of PKR is composed of two copies of the dsRNA-binding motif (dsRBM), a sequence motif conserved in many RNA-binding proteins (30,31). Binding of dsRNA to PKR through these motifs causes a conformational change (32,33) that leads to an unmasking of the ATP-binding site in the kinase domain and results in autophosphorylation of PKR on several sites (34&#x2013;36). The domains that are involved in dsRNA binding are also involved in mediating dimerization of PKR, which is essential for its kinase activity in the presence of dsRNA (37&#x2013;40). Although the same domain mediates PKR's dsRNA binding and dimerization, distinct residues have been identified that contribute to one or both of these properties (40). Heparin binds to PKR at a site that is nonoverlapping with PKR's dsRBD and leads to PKR activation (41,42). Activation of PKR by heparin in vascular smooth muscle cells leads to an arrest in cell cycle progression by causing elevation in p27kip1 protein levels, inhibition of Cdk2 activity and Rb phosphorylation (43). PACT interacts with PKR by binding to its dsRBD in a dsRNA-independent manner and activates PKR in response to cellular stress (14). Stress signals lead to phosphorylation of PACT at serine 287, which causes its higher affinity association with PKR leading to PKR activation, eIF2&#x3B1; phosphorylation and consequent inhibition of translation (44). PACT has three copies of dsRNA binding/dimerization motifs and the two amino-terminal copies are required for high-affinity binding to PKR (45). The third, carboxy-terminal motif is required for PKR activation presumably by making a direct contact with PKR's catalytic domain (45,46). Several cellular and viral inhibitors of PKR have been identified (47). P58IPK, the trans-activation response (TAR) RNA-binding protein (TRBP), nucleophosmin (NPM) and several virally encoded proteins inhibit PKR activity. Since PKR activation leading to eIF2&#x3B1; phosphorylation and inhibition of translation would be detrimental to viral replication, various viruses have developed efficient mechanisms to inhibit PKR activation (9,48,49). In this article, we report the identification of hDUS2 as a novel cellular PKR inhibitor. hDUS2 was identified as a PKR- and PACT-interacting protein using PACT as a bait protein in yeast two-hybrid screen. hDUS2 was reported recently to be the human homolog of Saccharomyces cerevisiae dihydrouridine synthase 2 (Dus2) enzyme (50). It was also shown to possess tRNA-dihydrouridine synthase (DUS) activity. hDUS2 has one copy of the conserved dsRBM and our results indicate that hDUS2 interacts with PKR and PACT via its dsRBM. Binding of hDUS2 with PKR resulted in an inhibition of PKR activity both in vitro as well as in mammalian cells. Furthermore, hDUS2 overexpression inhibited stress-induced apoptosis in HT1080 cells indicating that it acts as an important negative regulator of PKR activity in cells. The PACT coding region expressed as a GAL DNA-binding domain fusion protein was used as bait. A total of 3 million transformants from a human placenta matchmaker library (Clontech) were screened in the yeast strain HF7c (Clontech) and 250 colonies were recovered on triple dropout medium lacking histidine, leucine and tryptophan, out of which 22 tested positive for &#x3B2;-galactosidase. On further analysis, 18 of these were dependent on PACT to give a positive &#x3B2;-galactosidase reaction. These clones were subjected to a second screen to ensure that they gave a positive &#x3B2;-galactosidase reaction in a manner specific for co-expression of PACT. One of these clones (hDUS2), which did not contain a full-length cDNA insert, was analyzed further. Sequence analysis of the cDNA clones revealed that they originated from three unrelated genes. There were 14 clones isolated that coded for the PACT protein and the other three encoded a protein that has been characterized as a zinc finger protein just another zinc-finger (JAZ) that interacts with PKR. HF7c yeast reporter strain containing the LacZ-Gal4-inducible gene were co-transformed with the indicated plasmids and plated on selective medium lacking tryptophan and leucine. Double transformants were streaked on selective medium, replica-lifted on nitrocellulose filters and tested for &#x3B2;-galactosidase activity (51). The full-length open reading frame of hDUS2 was amplified by RT&#x2013;PCR using the sequence information from Genbank and the appropriate primers. The full-length open reading frame was then sub-cloned into pGBKT7 and pGADT7 (Clontech) vectors, and pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) (Invitrogen) vector. Cloning in pCDNA3.1 (&#x2013;) vector was designed such that it would add a flag tag at the amino-terminus of hDUS2. In vitro translated, 35S-labeled hDUS2 protein was synthesized using the TNT T7 coupled reticulocyte system from Promega. Five microliters of the in vitro translated 35S-labeled proteins were incubated with 1 &#x3BC;g of pure recombinant PACT or PKR and 20 &#x3BC;l of Ni-agarose (Novagen) in 200 &#x3BC;l of binding buffer [5 mM imidazole, 20 mM Tris&#x2013;HCl pH 7.9, 200 mM NaCl, 0.2 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride (PMSF), 0.5% IGEPAL (Sigma)] at 25&#xB0;C for 30 min on a rotating wheel. The beads were washed four times in 500 &#x3BC;l of binding buffer each time and the washed beads were then boiled in 20 &#x3BC;l Laemmli buffer (150 mM Tris&#x2013;HCl pH 6.8, 5% SDS, 5% &#x3B2;-mercaptoethanol, 20% glycerol) for 2 min and eluted proteins were analyzed by SDS&#x2013;PAGE on a 12% gel. Fluorography was performed at &#x2212;80&#xB0;C with intensifying screens. The in vitro translated, 35S-labeled PKR, PACT and hDUS2 proteins were synthesized using the TNT T7 coupled reticulocyte lysate system from Promega. The dsRNA-binding activity was measured by poly(I)&#x2013;poly(C)&#x2013;agarose binding assay. The translation products (4 &#x3BC;l) diluted with 25 &#x3BC;l of binding buffer [20 mM Tris&#x2013;HCl, pH 7.5, 0.3 M NaCl (or 50 mM NaCl), 5 mM MgCl2, 1 mM DTT, 0.1 mM PMSF, 0.5% NP-40, 10% glycerol) were mixed with 25 &#x3BC;l of poly(I)&#x2013;poly(C)&#x2013;agarose (Pharmacia) beads and incubated at 30&#xB0;C for 30 min with intermittent shaking. The beads were then washed four times with 500 &#x3BC;l of binding buffer each time. The proteins bound to beads after washing were analyzed by SDS&#x2013;PAGE followed by fluorography. HeLa cells were co-transfected in 100 mm culture dishes with 5 &#x3BC;g each of (i) negative control: HA-B56&#x3B1;/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) and flag-hDUS2/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;), (ii) HA-PKR/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) and flag-hDUS2/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) or (iii) HA-PACT/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) and flag-hDUS2/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) using the Effectene (Qiagen) reagent. At 24 h post-transfection, cell extracts were prepared. Cells were washed in ice-cold PBS and collected by centrifugation at 600 g for 5 min. They were lyzed by addition of an equal volume of lysis buffer (20 mM Tris&#x2013;HCl pH 7.5, 100 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM dithiothreitol, 100 U/ml aprotinin, 0.2 mM phenylmethanesulfonyl fluoride, 20% glycerol, 1% Triton X-100). The lysates were centrifuged at 10 000 g for 5 min and the supernatants were collected as total cell extract. One hundred micrograms of total protein was used to immunoprecipitate flag-hDUS2 with anti-flag mAb&#x2013;agarose in immunoprecipitation buffer (20 mM Tris&#x2013;HCl pH 7.5, 100 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM dithiothreitol, 100 U/ml aprotinin, 0.2 mM phenylmethanesulfonyl fluoride, 20% glycerol, 1% Triton X-100). The agarose beads were washed four times with 500 &#x3BC;l of IP buffer each time. The proteins bound to the beads were then analyzed by a western blot analysis with the anti-HA tag and anti-flag tag monoclonal antibodies (Sigma). PKR activity assays were performed using an anti-PKR monoclonal antibody (R &amp; D systems; 71/10). HeLa M cells were maintained in Dulbecco's modified Eagle's medium containing 10% (v/v) fetal calf serum. The cells were harvested when they were at 70% confluency. Cells were washed in ice-cold PBS and collected by centrifugation at 600 g for 5 min. They were lyzed by addition of an equal volume of lysis buffer (20 mM Tris&#x2013;HCl, pH 7.5, 5 mM MgCl2, 50 mM KCl, 400 mM NaCl, 2 mM DTT, 1% Triton X-100, 100 U/ml aprotinin, 0.2 mM PMSF, 20% glycerol). The lysates were centrifuged at 10 000 g for 5 min and the supernatants were assayed for PKR activity. A 100 &#x3BC;g aliquot of total protein was immunoprecipitated using anti-PKR monoclonal antibody (71/10) in high-salt buffer (20 mMTris&#x2013;HCl, pH 7.5, 50 mM KCl, 400 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 1 mM DTT, 100 U/ml aprotinin, 0.2 mM PMSF, 20% glycerol, 1% Triton X-100) at 4&#xB0;C for 30 min on a rotating wheel. Then 10 &#x3BC;l of Protein A-Sepharose slurry was added and incubation was carried out for a further 1 h. The Protein A-Sepharose beads were washed four times in 500 &#x3BC;l of high-salt buffer and twice in activity buffer (20 mM Tris&#x2013;HCl, pH 7.5, 50 mM KCl, 2 mM MgCl2, 2 mM MnCl2, 100 U/ml aprotinin, 0.1 mM PMSF, 5% glycerol). The PKR assay was performed with PKR still attached to the beads in activity buffer containing 0.1 mM ATP and 1 &#x3BC;Ci of [&#x3B3; 32P] ATP at 30&#xB0;C for 10 min. The standard activator of the enzyme was 0.1 &#x3BC;g/ml poly(I)-poly(C) or 0.116 pmol of pure PACT protein. Purified hDUS2 protein in varying amounts as indicated was added to test its effect on PKR activity. Labeled proteins were analyzed by SDS&#x2013;PAGE on a 12% gel followed by autoradiography. The effect of co-transfection of pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) empty vector, TRBP/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) and hDUS2/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) on the reporter pGL2-Control (Promega) in HeLa cells was measured as described before (52). HeLa cells were transfected in six-well plates in triplicate with the indicated plasmids using Effectene transfection reagent. At 24 h after transfection, the cells were treated with 100 U/ml of IFN-&#x3B2;. Cells were harvested 48 h after transfection and assayed for luciferase activity after normalizing for the transfection efficiency by measuring the total protein. HT1080 cells were grown to 50% confluency on coverslips in six-well plates and co-transfected with 500 ng of the indicated effector and 100 ng of pEGFPC1 (Clontech) plasmid using the Effectene reagent. The cells were observed for green fluorescent protein (GFP) fluorescence 24 h after transfection using an inverted fluorescence microscope, and were then treated with 0.1 &#x3BC;g/ml tunicamycin to induce ER stress and apoptosis. At 24 and 48 h after this treatment, the cells (coverslips) were washed twice with PBS and fixed in acetone:methanol (1:1, v/v) for 1 min, and were mounted in Vectashield (Vector Laboratories) mounting medium containing DAPI (4,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole). At least 300 fluorescent (GFP-positive) cells were counted as alive or dead, based on their morphology and nuclear DAPI staining. Intense DAPI staining indicates nuclear condensation, which is a hallmark of apoptosis. The experiment was repeated three times and the counting was done in a blinded manner to ascertain the validity of obtained numbers. The cells showing a normal flat morphology were scored as alive, and cells showing cell shrinkage, membrane blebbing, rounded morphology, partial detachment from the plate and chromatin condensation (intense DAPI stain) were counted as dead. Apoptosis (%) = (fluorescent cells with intense DAPI staining in the nucleus/total fluorescent cells) &#xD7; 100. Identification of hDUS2 as PKR and PACT interacting protein. (A) Yeast two-hybrid interaction assay. The indicated plasmids were transformed into yeast strain Hf7C and the transformants were streaked on triple dropout medium lacking leucine, tryptophan and histidine. A: hDUS2/pGBKT7 and empty vector pGADT7, B: hDUS2/pGBKT7 and PKR/pGADT7, C: hDUS2/pGBKT7 and PACT/pGADT7, D: empty vector pGBKT7 and hDUS2/pGADT7, E: PKR/pGBKT7 and hDUS2/pGADT7, F: PACT/pGBKT7 and hDUS2/pGADT7. (B) &#x3B2;-Galactosidase assay for the interactions in yeast. The indicated plasmids were transformed into yeast strain Hf7C and the transformants were streaked on double dropout medium lacking leucine, and tryptophan. After 4 days the growth was lifted on nitrocellulose membrane and &#x3B2;-galactosidase activity assay was performed after lysis of yeast cells on the membrane. Blue color indicates a positive interaction and white color indicates no interaction. (C) Biochemical interaction assay. In vitro-translated hDUS2 protein was allowed to interact with hexahistidine-tagged pure recombinant PKR or PACT proteins that were bound to Ni-agarose affinity beads. The bound proteins remaining on the beads were analyzed by SDS&#x2013;PAGE followed by phosphorimager analysis. Lane 1: total protein from the translation mix (20% of input in lanes 2&#x2013;4), lanes 2&#x2013;4: hDUS2 protein bound to beads. Lane 2: protein bound to his-DRIL1 beads: negative control, lane 3: protein bound to his-PKR beads, lane 4: protein bound to his-PACT beads. (D) Domain structure of hDUS2. A schematic representation of the DUS and dsRBM domains in hDUS2 protein. The DUS domain is shown as a hatched box and the dsRBM is shown as a gray box. The amino acid numbers are indicated on the top and bottom of the boxes. (E) Alignment of hDUS2 dsRBM with dsRBMs from three other human dsRNA-binding proteins PKR, PACT and TRBP. ClustalW alignment of the dsRBMs present in PKR, PACT and TRBP is shown. The conserved residues are shown in dark gray and similarities are shown in light gray. The consensus is shown at the bottom. Identification of hDUS2 as PKR and PACT interacting protein. (A) Yeast two-hybrid interaction assay. The indicated plasmids were transformed into yeast strain Hf7C and the transformants were streaked on triple dropout medium lacking leucine, tryptophan and histidine. A: hDUS2/pGBKT7 and empty vector pGADT7, B: hDUS2/pGBKT7 and PKR/pGADT7, C: hDUS2/pGBKT7 and PACT/pGADT7, D: empty vector pGBKT7 and hDUS2/pGADT7, E: PKR/pGBKT7 and hDUS2/pGADT7, F: PACT/pGBKT7 and hDUS2/pGADT7. (B) &#x3B2;-Galactosidase assay for the interactions in yeast. The indicated plasmids were transformed into yeast strain Hf7C and the transformants were streaked on double dropout medium lacking leucine, and tryptophan. After 4 days the growth was lifted on nitrocellulose membrane and &#x3B2;-galactosidase activity assay was performed after lysis of yeast cells on the membrane. Blue color indicates a positive interaction and white color indicates no interaction. (C) Biochemical interaction assay. In vitro-translated hDUS2 protein was allowed to interact with hexahistidine-tagged pure recombinant PKR or PACT proteins that were bound to Ni-agarose affinity beads. The bound proteins remaining on the beads were analyzed by SDS&#x2013;PAGE followed by phosphorimager analysis. Lane 1: total protein from the translation mix (20% of input in lanes 2&#x2013;4), lanes 2&#x2013;4: hDUS2 protein bound to beads. Lane 2: protein bound to his-DRIL1 beads: negative control, lane 3: protein bound to his-PKR beads, lane 4: protein bound to his-PACT beads. (D) Domain structure of hDUS2. A schematic representation of the DUS and dsRBM domains in hDUS2 protein. The DUS domain is shown as a hatched box and the dsRBM is shown as a gray box. The amino acid numbers are indicated on the top and bottom of the boxes. (E) Alignment of hDUS2 dsRBM with dsRBMs from three other human dsRNA-binding proteins PKR, PACT and TRBP. ClustalW alignment of the dsRBMs present in PKR, PACT and TRBP is shown. The conserved residues are shown in dark gray and similarities are shown in light gray. The consensus is shown at the bottom. hDUS2 interaction with dsRNA, PACT, and PKR. (A) dsRNA-binding characteristics of hDUS2. Binding of hDUS2 to dsRNA was analyzed by polyI:polyC-agarose-binding assay. The binding was assayed at 50 and 300-mM salt concentration as indicated. The T lanes represent total proteins from reticulocyte lysates. The positions of hDUS2, PACT, PKR and Luciferase (Luc) are indicated by arrows. (B) hDUS2 interaction with PACT and PKR in mammalian cells. HeLa cells were transfected with (i) HA-B56&#x3B1;/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) + Flag-hDUS2/pCDNA3. (-1), (ii) HA-PACT/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) + Flag-hDUS2/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) and (iii) HA-PKR/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) + Flag-hDUS2/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;). Twenty-four hours after transfection the Flag-tagged hDUS2 protein was immunoprecipitated using anti-Flag monoclonal antibody conjugated to agarose. The immunoprecipitates were analyzed by western blot analysis with anti-HA monoclonal antibody. The positions of HA-PKR, HA-PACT and Flag-hDUS2 are as indicated by arrows. hDUS2 interaction with dsRNA, PACT, and PKR. (A) dsRNA-binding characteristics of hDUS2. Binding of hDUS2 to dsRNA was analyzed by polyI:polyC-agarose-binding assay. The binding was assayed at 50 and 300-mM salt concentration as indicated. The T lanes represent total proteins from reticulocyte lysates. The positions of hDUS2, PACT, PKR and Luciferase (Luc) are indicated by arrows. (B) hDUS2 interaction with PACT and PKR in mammalian cells. HeLa cells were transfected with (i) HA-B56&#x3B1;/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) + Flag-hDUS2/pCDNA3. (-1), (ii) HA-PACT/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) + Flag-hDUS2/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) and (iii) HA-PKR/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) + Flag-hDUS2/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;). Twenty-four hours after transfection the Flag-tagged hDUS2 protein was immunoprecipitated using anti-Flag monoclonal antibody conjugated to agarose. The immunoprecipitates were analyzed by western blot analysis with anti-HA monoclonal antibody. The positions of HA-PKR, HA-PACT and Flag-hDUS2 are as indicated by arrows. In order to test if hDUS2 interacts with PACT and PKR in mammalian cells, we tested the ability of flag-tagged hDUS2 to interact with HA-tagged PKR and PACT in HeLa cells. As shown in Figure 2B, when flag-hDUS2 was immunoprecipitated with anti-flag antibody, HA-tagged PKR and PACT both co-immunoprecipitated with it indicating that hDUS2 interacts with both PKR and PACT. The negative control HA-B56&#x3B1;, which is an unrelated protein, did not co-immunoprecipitate with flag-hDUS2, thus demonstrating the specificity of interaction. These results demonstrate that hDUS2 forms a complex with PKR and PACT in mammalian cells. Mapping the hDUS2 interaction domain within PKR. (A) PKR and its deletion mutants DRBD and &#x394;170 were in vitro translated. Hexahistidine-tagged, pure recombinant hDUS2 protein was incubated with 5 &#x3BC;l of the reticulocyte lysates before pull-down with Ni-charged affinity resin. As a negative control, his-tagged DRIL1 protein that does not interact with PKR was immobilized on Ni-agarose beads in lanes 7&#x2013;9. The proteins that associate with recombinant hDUS2 are also pulled down with the beads and were analyzed by SDS&#x2013;PAGE followed by phosphorimager analysis. Lanes 1&#x2013;3 represent total proteins from the translation mix (20% of input in lanes 4&#x2013;9), lanes 4&#x2013;6 represent proteins pulled down with hDUS2 bound to Ni-charged beads, and lanes 7&#x2013;9 represent negative controls with proteins pulled down with DRIL1 bound to Ni-charged beads. (B) Mapping the PKR interaction domain within hDUS2. hDUS2 and its deletion mutant &#x394;307 were in vitro translated. Hexahistidine-tagged, pure recombinant PKR protein was incubated with 5 &#x3BC;l of the reticulocyte lysates before pull-down with Ni-charged affinity resin. As a negative control, his-tagged DRIL1 protein that does not interact with hDUS2 was used in lanes 5 and 6. Lanes 1 and 2 represent total proteins from the translation mix (20% of input in lanes 4&#x2013;9), lanes 3 and 4 represent proteins pulled down with hexahistidine-tagged pure recombinant PKR bound to Ni-charged beads, lanes 5 and 6 represent negative controls with proteins pulled down with his-tagged pure DRIL1 bound to Ni-charged beads. Mapping the hDUS2 interaction domain within PKR. (A) PKR and its deletion mutants DRBD and &#x394;170 were in vitro translated. Hexahistidine-tagged, pure recombinant hDUS2 protein was incubated with 5 &#x3BC;l of the reticulocyte lysates before pull-down with Ni-charged affinity resin. As a negative control, his-tagged DRIL1 protein that does not interact with PKR was immobilized on Ni-agarose beads in lanes 7&#x2013;9. The proteins that associate with recombinant hDUS2 are also pulled down with the beads and were analyzed by SDS&#x2013;PAGE followed by phosphorimager analysis. Lanes 1&#x2013;3 represent total proteins from the translation mix (20% of input in lanes 4&#x2013;9), lanes 4&#x2013;6 represent proteins pulled down with hDUS2 bound to Ni-charged beads, and lanes 7&#x2013;9 represent negative controls with proteins pulled down with DRIL1 bound to Ni-charged beads. (B) Mapping the PKR interaction domain within hDUS2. hDUS2 and its deletion mutant &#x394;307 were in vitro translated. Hexahistidine-tagged, pure recombinant PKR protein was incubated with 5 &#x3BC;l of the reticulocyte lysates before pull-down with Ni-charged affinity resin. As a negative control, his-tagged DRIL1 protein that does not interact with hDUS2 was used in lanes 5 and 6. Lanes 1 and 2 represent total proteins from the translation mix (20% of input in lanes 4&#x2013;9), lanes 3 and 4 represent proteins pulled down with hexahistidine-tagged pure recombinant PKR bound to Ni-charged beads, lanes 5 and 6 represent negative controls with proteins pulled down with his-tagged pure DRIL1 bound to Ni-charged beads. PKR's interaction with hDUS2 is mediated by dsRBM1 motif within its DRBD. PKR and its point mutants were analyzed for interaction with hexahistidine tagged pure, recombinant hDUS2 by Ni-agarose pull-down assay. PKR and its point mutants were in vitro translated. Hexahistidine-tagged, pure recombinant hDUS2 protein was incubated with 5 &#x3BC;l of the reticulocyte lysates before pull-down with Ni-charged affinity resin. As a negative control, his-tagged DRIL1 protein that does not interact with PKR was immobilized on Ni-agarose beads. The proteins that associate with recombinant hDUS2 are also pulled down with the beads and were analyzed by SDS&#x2013;PAGE followed by phosphorimager analysis. The percent interaction was calculated using quantification of radioactivity present in the PKR band in the total and bound samples as follows: % interaction = 100 &#xD7; (amount of radioactivity in the bound sample/amount of radioactivity in the total sample). The percent interactions of the point mutants are expressed relative to that of the wild-type PKR with wild-type PKR value taken as 100%. The amount of radioactivity in the negative control (this was never above background in any of the samples) was subtracted from the amount of radioactivity in the bound sample before calculations. Error bars represent SE calculated based on values from three different experiments. PKR's interaction with hDUS2 is mediated by dsRBM1 motif within its DRBD. PKR and its point mutants were analyzed for interaction with hexahistidine tagged pure, recombinant hDUS2 by Ni-agarose pull-down assay. PKR and its point mutants were in vitro translated. Hexahistidine-tagged, pure recombinant hDUS2 protein was incubated with 5 &#x3BC;l of the reticulocyte lysates before pull-down with Ni-charged affinity resin. As a negative control, his-tagged DRIL1 protein that does not interact with PKR was immobilized on Ni-agarose beads. The proteins that associate with recombinant hDUS2 are also pulled down with the beads and were analyzed by SDS&#x2013;PAGE followed by phosphorimager analysis. The percent interaction was calculated using quantification of radioactivity present in the PKR band in the total and bound samples as follows: % interaction = 100 &#xD7; (amount of radioactivity in the bound sample/amount of radioactivity in the total sample). The percent interactions of the point mutants are expressed relative to that of the wild-type PKR with wild-type PKR value taken as 100%. The amount of radioactivity in the negative control (this was never above background in any of the samples) was subtracted from the amount of radioactivity in the bound sample before calculations. Error bars represent SE calculated based on values from three different experiments. hDUS2 inhibits PKR activity in vitro and in vivo. (A) PKR kinase activity assay. PKR immunoprecipitated from HeLa cell extracts was activated by the addition of 0.1 &#x3BC;g/ml of poly(I): poly(C) (lanes 2&#x2013;5) or 0.116 pmol of recombinant PACT (lanes 6&#x2013;9). The effects of addition of increasing amounts of recombinant hDUS2 protein were assayed. Lane 1: no activator added, lanes 2 and 6: no hDUS2 added, lanes 3 and 7: 1.45 pmol (80 ng) hDUS2, lanes 3 and 8: 7.25 pmol (400 ng) hDUS2, lanes 4 and 9: 36.25 pmol (2 &#x3BC;g) hDUS2. The position of phosphorylated PKR is indicated by an arrow. (B) Translation inhibition assay. The translation inhibition assay was performed in HeLa cells grown in six-well plates. The reporter pGL2C (200 ng) was co-transfected using Effectene reagent with indicated amounts of the empty vector control or expression constructs for TRBP, hDUS2 or PKR. The amount of DNA in each well was kept constant at 600 ng by addition of required amounts of empty vector pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;). At 24 h after transfection, the cells were treated with 100 U/ml interferon-&#x3B2; and 24 h after the treatment the luciferase activity was measured in the cell extracts and normalized to the total protein in the extract. All expression constructs were in pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;). (C) hDUS2 overexpression relieves the translation inhibition caused by activated PKR. The translation inhibition assay was performed in HeLa cells grown in six-well plates. The reporter pGL2C (50 ng) was co-transfected using Effectene reagent with indicated amounts of the empty vector pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;), expression constructs for PKR, hDUS2 and DRIL1. The amount of DNA in each well was kept constant by addition of required amounts of empty vector pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;). At 24 h after transfection, the cells were treated with 100 U/ml interferon-&#x3B2;. Twenty-four hours after the treatment the luciferase activity was measured in the cell extracts and normalized to the total protein in the extract. All expression constructs were in pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;). hDUS2 inhibits PKR activity in vitro and in vivo. (A) PKR kinase activity assay. PKR immunoprecipitated from HeLa cell extracts was activated by the addition of 0.1 &#x3BC;g/ml of poly(I): poly(C) (lanes 2&#x2013;5) or 0.116 pmol of recombinant PACT (lanes 6&#x2013;9). The effects of addition of increasing amounts of recombinant hDUS2 protein were assayed. Lane 1: no activator added, lanes 2 and 6: no hDUS2 added, lanes 3 and 7: 1.45 pmol (80 ng) hDUS2, lanes 3 and 8: 7.25 pmol (400 ng) hDUS2, lanes 4 and 9: 36.25 pmol (2 &#x3BC;g) hDUS2. The position of phosphorylated PKR is indicated by an arrow. (B) Translation inhibition assay. The translation inhibition assay was performed in HeLa cells grown in six-well plates. The reporter pGL2C (200 ng) was co-transfected using Effectene reagent with indicated amounts of the empty vector control or expression constructs for TRBP, hDUS2 or PKR. The amount of DNA in each well was kept constant at 600 ng by addition of required amounts of empty vector pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;). At 24 h after transfection, the cells were treated with 100 U/ml interferon-&#x3B2; and 24 h after the treatment the luciferase activity was measured in the cell extracts and normalized to the total protein in the extract. All expression constructs were in pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;). (C) hDUS2 overexpression relieves the translation inhibition caused by activated PKR. The translation inhibition assay was performed in HeLa cells grown in six-well plates. The reporter pGL2C (50 ng) was co-transfected using Effectene reagent with indicated amounts of the empty vector pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;), expression constructs for PKR, hDUS2 and DRIL1. The amount of DNA in each well was kept constant by addition of required amounts of empty vector pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;). At 24 h after transfection, the cells were treated with 100 U/ml interferon-&#x3B2;. Twenty-four hours after the treatment the luciferase activity was measured in the cell extracts and normalized to the total protein in the extract. All expression constructs were in pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;). hDUS2 overexpression inhibits stress-induced apoptosis. HT1080 cells were grown to 50% confluency on coverslips in six-well plates and transfected with 500 ng of pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) + 100 ng of pEGFPC1 (white bars) or 500 ng of hDUS2/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) + 100 ng of pEGFPC1 (black bars) using the Effectene reagent. The cells were observed for GFP fluorescence 24 h after transfection using an inverted fluorescence microscope. At this point, they were treated with 0.1 &#x3BC;g/ml of tunicamycin. The morphology of cells was monitored at regular time intervals. At 24 and 48 h after treatment, the cells were fixed and mounted in Vectashield with DAPI nuclear stain. At least 300 fluorescent (GFP-positive) cells were counted as live or dead based on their morphology and nuclear condensation indicated by intense DAPI fluorescence. The experiment was repeated three times and the data is represented as averages of these values. The assays were counted in blinded manner to ascertain the validity of observed differences. The percentage of apoptotic cells were calculated using the formula, % apoptosis = (fluorescent dead cells with intense DAPI fluorescence/total fluorescent cells) &#xD7; 100. The P-values, calculated using statistical analysis, are as indicated above the bars. hDUS2 overexpression inhibits stress-induced apoptosis. HT1080 cells were grown to 50% confluency on coverslips in six-well plates and transfected with 500 ng of pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) + 100 ng of pEGFPC1 (white bars) or 500 ng of hDUS2/pCDNA3.1(&#x2013;) + 100 ng of pEGFPC1 (black bars) using the Effectene reagent. The cells were observed for GFP fluorescence 24 h after transfection using an inverted fluorescence microscope. At this point, they were treated with 0.1 &#x3BC;g/ml of tunicamycin. The morphology of cells was monitored at regular time intervals. At 24 and 48 h after treatment, the cells were fixed and mounted in Vectashield with DAPI nuclear stain. At least 300 fluorescent (GFP-positive) cells were counted as live or dead based on their morphology and nuclear condensation indicated by intense DAPI fluorescence. The experiment was repeated three times and the data is represented as averages of these values. The assays were counted in blinded manner to ascertain the validity of observed differences. The percentage of apoptotic cells were calculated using the formula, % apoptosis = (fluorescent dead cells with intense DAPI fluorescence/total fluorescent cells) &#xD7; 100. The P-values, calculated using statistical analysis, are as indicated above the bars. PKR activity is regulated very tightly in cells and several cellular proteins have been described as inhibitors of PKR (47). One of the best-studied proteins is p58IPK, which is a member of the tetratricopeptide repeat family (62&#x2013;64). P58IPK inhibits PKR activity by interacting directly with it and by preventing its dimerization (65). Influenza virus evades the host antiviral response partially by recruiting p58IPK to repress PKR-induced eIF2&#x3B1; phosphorylation (66). TRBP is a cellular protein that was identified by its ability to bind human immunodeficiency virus type 1 (HIV-1) TAR RNA (67). TRBP inhibits PKR activity by sequestration of its activator dsRNA, and also by direct interaction with PKR (38,58). Recent data suggests that in astrocytes, low TRBP levels support and innate HIV-1 resistance via PKR activation (68). Thus, TRBP may play a major role in viral expression by regulating PKR activation. NPM is an abundant nucleolar phosphoprotein implicated in ribosome biogenesis (69). NPM interacts with PKR and inhibits eIF2&#x3B1; phosphorylation and PKR-mediated apoptosis (70). NPM has also been implicated in mediating antiviral activity of the tumor suppressor ARF thus linking the Arf/mdm2/p53 pathway to PKR (71). The heat shock proteins Hsp70 and Hsp90 have also been shown to bind to PKR and inhibit its activation (48,72). In addition to these cellular inhibitors of PKR, numerous viral proteins and RNAs have been established to act as PKR inhibitors during viral infection thereby evading the host cell's innate antiviral response (8,49). In this article, we describe hDUS2 as a novel inhibitor of PKR activity. hDUS2 was reported recently to have 39% homology to Dus2 enzyme of Saccharomyces cerevisiae and to possess tRNA&#x2013;DUS activity (50). It was also shown to exist in a complex with EPRS, a glutamy-prolyl tRNA synthetase and to enhance general translational efficiency in mammalian cells. hDUS2 was identified as a PACT-interacting protein in our yeast two-hybrid screen using PACT as a bait. Further characterization of the interaction between PACT and hDUS2 (data not shown) indicated that this interaction was mediated by the single copy of dsRBM present in hDUS2. Our work on PKR and PACT has demonstrated that PKR and PACT interact with each other via the dsRBM motifs (45). The amino-terminal two copies of dsRBM present in PACT are essential for mediating the high-affinity interaction with PKR via the two dsRBMs present in PKR. We reasoned that hDUS2 may also show interaction with PKR via the two dsRBMs. Originally identified as a PACT-interacting protein, hDUS2 did indeed interact with PKR equally well, both in vivo (in mammalian and yeast cells) and in vitro. Although there are two copies of dsRBM present in PKR, our results indicate that hDUS2 interacts with PKR mainly via the amino-terminal copy of the motif. Thus, the two dsRBMs do not contribute equally to PKR's interaction with hDUS2 and the first or the amino-terminal motif is responsible for mediating the interaction. Within this motif, mutations at position 41 (phenylalanine), 60 (lysine) and 68 (alanine) affected the interaction between PKR and hDUS2 adversely, thereby identifying these residues as essential for the interaction. Mutations of the same residues in motif 2 did not show much effect on the PKR&#x2013;hDUS2 interaction. In addition to this, the interaction between hDUS2 and PKR is by direct protein&#x2013;protein interaction and not likely to be mediated via dsRNA since mutations F131A, K150A, K154E and A158D that are known to destroy PKR's dsRNA binding (26,52) have very little adverse effect on PKR&#x2013;hDUS2 interaction. Although hDUS2 carries one copy of the conserved dsRBM, it does not interact with dsRNA with high affinity. This may be attributed to the lack of a crucial conserved lysine at position 58 of the conserved motif (Figure 1E). This lysine has been shown to be essential for the high-affinity interaction with dsRNA (52). hDUS2 carries an aspartic acid residue at this position, which may contribute to its lack of high-affinity dsRNA binding. Recombinant hDUS2 protein showed a marked inhibition of PKR's kinase activity in vitro. The inhibition was effective when PKR was activated either by addition of dsRNA or recombinant PACT. However, hDUS2 was effective in inhibiting PACT-induced PKR activation more efficiently than dsRNA-induced PKR activation since even the lowest amount of hDUS2 (80 ng) showed a marked reduction in PKR autophosphorylation when activated by PACT. This may be due to the ability of hDUS2 to interact both with PKR and PACT. hDUS2's interaction with PACT may inhibit PACT's interaction with PKR in addition to inhibition by directly interacting with PKR, thus resulting in a more efficient inhibition. The biological significance of this if any is currently unknown. hDUS2 also showed inhibition of PKR in mammalian cells as seen in the translation inhibition assay. However, hDUS2 did not inhibit PKR activation as efficiently as PKR's well-studied inhibitor TRBP (Figure 5B). Since this is not due to lower level of expression of hDUS2 as compared to TRBP (data not shown), we conclude that hDUS2 is not a strong inhibitor of PKR in vivo. However, since the results shown in Figure 5C indicate that when overexpressed, hDUS2 can inhibit activated PKR it can be speculated that hDUS2 may regulate PKR activity under conditions (or in cells) where its expression is elevated. Thus, hDUS2's inhibition of PKR may be of biological relevance under conditions where hDUS2 expression is upregulated in mammalian cells. In this context, it has been recently reported that hDUS2 is overexpressed in human nonsmall cell lung carcinomas (NSCLC). It was observed that upregulation of hDUS2 was a relatively common feature of pulmonary carcinogenesis and that selective suppression of hDUS2 by SiRNA showed reduced growth rate in NSCLC cell lines (50). Inhibition of PKR activity in NIH 3T3 cells by expression of a trans-dominant negative PKR mutant has been shown to lead to cell transformation and tumor formation in nude mice (4,5). Overexpression of PKR inhibitors p58IPK and TRBP also results in tumorigenesis (73). It remains to be tested if overexpression of hDUS2 also can lead to cell transformation. In addition, it would also be interesting to examine if hDUS2-mediated inhibition of PKR is involved in tumorigenesis in cases of NSCLC. Since our results demonstrate that hDUS2 can inhibit apoptosis, overexpression of hDUS2 in NSCLC may offer a growth advantage to cancer cells. hDUS2 has been shown to enhance the translation rate in mammalian cells possibly by enhancing the tRNA modification activity of EPRS complex (50). In view of the results presented here, it is also possible that hDUS2 may enhance the rate of translation by inhibition of eIF2&#x3B1; phosphorylation brought about by activated PKR. This may be of biological significance in cancer progression since enhanced PKR expression is reported in some types of cancers. In melanomas and colorectal cancers, PKR overexpression can be correlated with enhanced PKR activity (74). However, in breast cancer cells, PKR overexpression does not correlate with increased PKR activity (17,75). It is thought that an inhibitor of PKR may be expressed at high levels in such cancers, leading to an inhibition of PKR activity. In future, it would be of interest to examine if hDUS2 may be involved in PKR inhibition in these types of cancers.
</content>
</document>
